<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>birb plays games - Uni</title><link href="http://birb.uk/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://birb.uk/feeds/by_uni.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://birb.uk/</id><updated>2020-12-15T14:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Sturgeon's Law: The Year's Top 10%</title><link href="http://birb.uk/2020wrap.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-15T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-15T14:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Uni</name></author><id>tag:birb.uk,2020-12-15:/2020wrap.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The top 10% of games I played this year, since I was hiding all year and 10% of the total was greater than 10.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sturgeon’s Law is as follows: &lt;br /&gt;
90% of everything is crap. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, instead of doing a top 10, I thought I would do a top 10%. With ~120 games beaten this year (not including replays), that gives us a top 12. There isn’t an exact order to these, but the confidence goes up as you go down the list, until my game of the year at the very bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resident Evil 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Compared to the smashing success of the Resident Evil 2 remake, this game got almost no positive reaction at all. Fans were upset that some of their favorite sections from the original were cut, and that no free DLC or extra modes were added for replay value. It seems like a pretty bad deal all around, but it’s less of a downgrade than it may seem. I replayed the original for a point of comparison, and found that the remake actually does a pretty good job reworking it into a smoother experience. The best example is the removal of the clock tower sequence, which is considered emblematic of a remake that cut too much. However, as memorable as the clock tower imagery is, nothing that happens there contributes to the overall plot. The area is fairly small, and it doesn’t introduce any new enemies. The question the developers had to ask was if the smoother progression of the narrative was worth the blowback from fans of the original, and they decided to take the risk. Even if they miscalculated the response, they still achieved the goal of giving Resident Evil 3 the action-movie pacing it was originally envisioned with. That’s the line that always divides fans with remakes, whether you would prefer the original flaws to be left intact, or reworked with potentially warped hindsight. However, with the remakes of Resident Evil 2 and 3 both being so fundamentally different in style from the originals that the “remake” designation is stretched to the breaking point, the latter option is easier for me to accept. I can also understand being annoyed at the lack of replayability options compared to the multiple campaigns of RE2, but the additional difficulty modes and persistent item shop did a good job of keeping me interested all the way through the ultimate inferno mode. This review is more defending the game rather than explaining why you should play it, and that’s because I understand that even the other Resident Evil fans who are most willing to replay the game found the content to be lacking. It may make it into my top games of the year, but in this case, I don’t feel like my confidence in a recommendation is proportional to my level of enjoyment. I enjoyed the RE2 remake a lot, this is essentially more of the same. How much that’s worth is up to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Castlevania: Bloodlines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just like Resident Evil 3, the confidence I have in recommending this doesn’t match how much fun I had with it. It’s classic Castlevania, and your enjoyment will be based entirely on your opinion of those games. If you aren’t a big fan, this game isn’t so amazing that it would convert you, but it’s still really good. That surprised me, with how most classic-vania attention is focused on Rondo of Blood and Super Castlevania 4, but Bloodlines represents a fusion of their best traits. The easy way to see this is with the differences between the two available player characters, John Morris and Eric Lecarde. John Morris plays like the standard whip-users of the series, only attacking to the sides and relying on subweapons for flexibility. Playing with him makes the game feel challenging like Rondo, just without some of the insane difficulty spikes that game is known for. Meanwhile, Eric Lecarde can attack in 8 directions and spin his spear, like how Simon in Castlevania 4 can freely target his whip. Also similarly to Castlevania 4, there’s an abundance of setpieces and atmospheric details to break up the standard hallways full of enemies. Whichever game prompted you to play Bloodlines, you’ll still have a great time, which is pretty impressive. I just wouldn’t recommend it if you haven’t played any classic-vanias before, since it uses passwords and limited continues, which can make it a frustrating starting point. I would instead point you towards the first one on NES, being the short and sweet game that all the others call back to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Batman: The Video Game&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Licensed games tend to be pretty bad, and Batman: Arkham Asylum is thought to be the first Batman game that did any good, but this NES action platformer managed to get it right. Coming late into the NES life cycle, the developers could use their years of experience to make everything look and sound amazing. It’s beautifully made all around, and the controls are smooth and well considered. You have fixed-arc jumps if you hold forward when jumping, but you can adjust your arc freely if you jump without a direction, letting you choose to focus on midair shooting or precise landing. Walljumps work without Strider-esque mashing, and there’s a little animation that plays before bounding off the wall so you can easily adjust to your new trajectory. It’s also nice that the difficulty doesn’t waste your time, with continues not sending you back to the beginning of the stage. The only time you lose progress is if you have to use a continue on a boss, which sets you back to the start of the most recent level. The only things I dislike are how your batarang ammo is maintained among deaths, so you have to farm it between attempts, and that the final boss is too hard. Other than those two gripes, Batman would be my recommendation for anyone wanting to start playing classic NES platformers. It hits all the same highs as its contemporaries, with none of the frustrating lows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sekiro: Shadows Die Twice&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I made this list in the same way I determine my top ten overall games. I take the games from my spreadsheet, delete the ones I actively dislike, then merge-sort the rest. Doing it this way helps avoid bias, as evidenced by the fact I’m talking about Sekiro right now. I didn’t like this game at all at the start, since it seemed like a confused mix of elements. It has a lengthy narrative intro and a heavy focus on stealth mechanics, with neither playing much of a role in the rest of the game. The level design is open ended like other From games, but without the weapons and armor which made exploration rewarding. Worst of all, the combat seemed mindless since stamina management was removed. You can just mash the attack button until your enemy parries and turns the tables, then you block until it's your turn again. I was left wondering if Sekiro was supposed to be about the narrative, the stealth, the combat, or the exploration, when each seemed to be watered down for the sake of the other. However, now that I've looked it over and beaten the game a second time, I can see that I wasn’t giving it enough credit. The combat actually does have some nuance, but the techniques are learned naturally over time instead of through an explicit upgrade system, which is something I really appreciate. The stealth is poorly introduced rather than poorly implemented, with its primary usage for most of the game being rapid repositioning and reengagement, not waiting in the bushes. After the clunky intro, the story hits a nice stride where new beats are frequent, but spaced out enough to allow for consideration. Once you reach the end of the game, it all comes together for amazing showdowns that look and sound like cinematic choreography. In the end, Sekiro isn’t bad at all, its first few hours just set you in the wrong direction. Luckily, being poorly explained is only a problem for so long, but the solid mechanics remain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brigador: Up-Armored Edition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A big draw of roguelikes is the moment where you find a powerful combination of abilities that feels amazing to use. Achieving victory after multiple failed attempts is a great feeling, and one that keeps people trying and retrying for hundreds of hours. However, replaying the same content for only a chance at a payoff can get frustrating, and leave players wanting a more structured challenge instead. Brigador is a twin-stick mecha combat game that attempts to merge the strengths of roguelike satisfaction and linear challenge: you have an extensive suite of mech customization options, and an even more extensive set of randomized missions and difficulty modifiers to tune your experience. Harder missions reward you with more money for parts, and it forms a loop where you get more interesting mechs to take on more interesting missions. With a mission-based structure and permanent unlocks, the roguelike comparison seems questionably relevant, but that’s the sort of mindset I recommend when approaching this game. How much value you’ll get is dependent on how much you like pushing yourself in terms of difficulty, experimenting with mech setups to tackle specific challenges, and trying over until you get the big payoff. What makes the process so enjoyable is how perfect the game feel is, with the weight of your mechs, the power of your weapons, and the sounds of destruction all being incredibly satisfying. Even if this was just a linear twin-stick shooter with twenty missions, I would think the combat is cool enough to be worth the price, but you get a huge range of missions and mechs that could last you a hundred hours. If you’re even remotely interested in the concept, you’ll get your money’s worth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total War: Warhammer 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Warhammer 2 has a lot more going on than the historical Total War games. Untethered by the limits of realism, the door is blown wide open for a much more varied set of mechanics. Each faction’s units, goals, strengths, weaknesses, magic, and technology are incredibly different from each other, but this complexity actually makes this game easier for newcomers to play. With each faction being so specialized and distinct, it’s easier to understand how you should be strategizing. In a game like Shogun, your faction’s unique feature may be strong cavalry, but how much should you play into that? If you try to make a full cavalry army, you’ll either get destroyed by spearmen or run out of money, and finding the middle ground where you can take advantage of your bonuses without going overboard can take multiple campaigns. Compare that to an example from Warhammer, where the Skaven faction is geared towards swarming with cheap units and bombarding with powerful ranged gunners. The balance to strike is obvious, use the disposable units to tie up the enemy as you gun them down. If you have a magic user available, they can destroy anyone who flanks the gunners or turn the tables wherever the front line is breaking. Even if you’ve never played Total War before, this sort of strategizing will come naturally, and you can start having fun without the sort of Youtube tutorials strategy games often rely on. The accessibility combined with the abundance of content makes it easy for me to recommend, but the real question is if I can recommend buying it. There’s a ton of DLC, which is always a major turn-off, but you really don’t need to load up. Paradox games might lock entire game-changing mechanics behind DLC, but that’s not the case here. It’s just factions and faction leaders which you can pick depending on how interesting they seem to you. Personally, I would recommend buying Warhammer 1 and 2 to start, which will give you all the base factions from both games to use in 2’s combined campaign. The DLC factions are mostly based on gimmicks that shake up the standard gameplay, which isn’t a priority when you’re just starting out. Buying it this way also makes it fairly cheap to get into, especially when measured against the hundreds of hours you can get from it. If you’ve ever been interested in Total War, it’s easily worth your time and money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Earthbound&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can’t talk about this game without addressing the Undertale elephant in the room. The fanbases of the two games practically overlap, but I ended up in the sliver that loved Earthbound but not Undertale This was surprising given their similar premise, being simple RPG’s with a vibrant cast of adolescent characters on a humorous but mind bending quest. What ended up making the difference between the games is that Earthbound does a better job at actually feeling like a journey, conveying the joy of conquering challenges, the anxiety of being far from home, and all the feelings in between. Each area you visit feels different and contributes a unique perspective on the game’s themes, and the plot is kept simple to let those messages get the full focus. The lighthearted presentation and jokes may be what people talk about, but the jokiness belies the wistfulness of an adult writer thinking back on childhood, and it frequently gave me a moment of pause. At least, it did that some of the time. Sometimes it’s just crude 90’s humor. And truthfully, a lot of the journeying can be dull, with the simplicity of the RPG mechanics not feeling so great when you have to fight basic enemies for hours. In particular, I would say the hump of the game is in between the end of the intro and getting your second companion. Once you get over that stretch, the combat starts feeling a lot better, and the story keeps escalating until a wonderful finale. I hope the fanbase and the excessive hype behind it haven’t soured people on actually playing this game, because it does deserve appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Desperados 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Shadow Tactics: Blades of the Shogun had prerelease marketing that consisted almost entirely of “Did you like Desperados and Commandos? Then play this!”. It’s a pretty bold strategy when both of those series had been dead for a decade and weren’t the kind of mainstream hits that most people would recognize. Even so, the move paid off, and Shadow Tactics was praised as a great iteration on the isometric stealth gameplay those series were known for. Then, the Shadow Tactics team actually got to use the Desperados IP for their next game, and iterated upon their iteration of iterative franchises. Suffice to say, Desperados 3 doesn’t shake up the formula at all, it’s just another layer of refinement on a stealth system that works. Stealth where you can see every guard and every view cone is so fundamentally solid that all the game really needed was a polished interface, fun abilities, and interesting scenarios to use them in, and all three goals were met. At first, the characters seemed too similar to the ones from Shadow Tactics, but enough changes and powerful new abilities were included to make it fresh. The final character in particular allows for so much creativity that the game becomes something new entirely, and I played for hours just testing out all the possibilities. The variety in missions actually gives you a reason to take your time experimenting in this way, and it’s not just sneaking around plain bandit camps. However, one of my few criticisms of Desperados 3 is that you may feel like you’re always surrounded by bandits anyway, since you’re repetitiously sneaking up behind guys, killing them, and dragging them into bushes instead of slipping by without a trace. The variety in the other aspects is enough to keep things fresh, but I would certainly like to see some thought put into the ghost playstyle when the next game adds another layer of polish. It still might not be at the point where I would suggest this to people who aren’t stealth fans, but it comes extremely close. If you are a fan, it’s an unqualified recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, it's one of two games on this list that actually came out this year, so it wins my Game of 2020 award. Good work Mimimi Games!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metal Gear 2: Solid Snake&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When a series gets popular after a style change, the original games enter a limbo state. The fanbase gets split into two, and depending on how widely available the originals are, their unique qualities can be forgotten. Metal Gear is in a particularly weird place with this, being a narrative-focused series where everyone outside Japan missed out on the story of the first two entries. However, with the Metal Gear Solid games being cinematic 3D experiences, most people seemed ok with just ignoring the old 2D top-down games. Many of the unique moments from Metal Gear 2 were reused in Metal Gear Solid anyway, so it became even easier to ignore the old ones. Even if people wanted to play them, there wasn’t a way you could do that until Metal Gear Solid 3 Subsistence included translated versions. All of this is to say that for a multitude of reasons, Metal Gear 2 has become a footnote in the Metal Gear franchise, when it’s actually a fantastic game that fans of the series and stealth fans in general should play. It hits the perfect middleground for stealth games, where the information about your visibility is perfectly clear but the situations are varied enough to be consistently challenging. Without the need for the Solid games’ abstracted Soliton radar view, Metal Gear 2 actually has the denser spread of challenges and the more interesting set of gimmicks. The amount of twists on basic stealth mechanics like noisy floors, hiding spots, gadgets, and security systems is honestly mind-blowing for a game from 1990, and it’s kept short enough to where none of the gimmicks wear out their welcome. In a way, it’s like Metal Gear Solid but without the downsides commonly associated with those games. There are no long monologues of questionable relevance, no slumps in the pacing, and no abandonment of stealth mechanics after the first hour. Fans and non-fans can enjoy it equally, it’s just a great game that can stand alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blood: Fresh Supply&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you play a lot of games, it’s easy to forget the staggering level of work that goes into game development. You expect guns to go bang and enemies to fall over, and that seems easy enough, but every sound and reaction effect needs to be purpose-built to feel satisfying and suit the game’s tone. Every weapon needs an entire suite of secondary animations, like trying to shoot without ammo or using an alternative fire mode. Enemies should react differently to being shot, set on fire, or electrocuted, so the complexity multiplies with every new weapon and enemy type. Having variety and reactivity in this way is a massive undertaking, but Blood proves how polish in these areas can elevate a game to greatness. In most shooters you get a boring handgun by default, but here, you get a flare gun. It doesn’t just set enemies on fire when you hit them, it fizzles menacingly until they burst into flames and start flailing wildly. You might expect to get a hunting rifle for long distances, but in Blood you get a voodoo doll, sadistically jabbing it to take down enemies. The focus is on B-movie horror brutality, but it’s done in such a tongue-in-cheek way that it never feels mean spirited. You’re just there to have a good time sprinting at the insane speed of a 90’s shooter protagonist, blasting cultists with some of the most satisfying weapons ever put into a computer game. The cherry on the top is the custom difficulty system, which lets you tweak the game to whatever you find the most fun. There’s the usual damage modifiers for you and the enemies, but also settings for enemy counts and aggression levels for each type. You can make it a run-and-gun with hordes of weak enemies, or a horror shooter where you have to be careful with your resources. As long as you enjoy shooters, you can have fun with Blood. Since a rerelease took until 2019 and it never got a quality sequel, it’s been criminally overlooked, so I encourage even the shooter skeptics out there to rediscover this classic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outer Wilds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Some games are recommended because they’re perfectly polished, some get recommended because they iterate on the systems people already like, and Outer Wilds doesn’t meet either criteria. There are times I got frustrated, times I tried correct solutions that didn’t work, and times I was pretty bored, but I still recommend it. The reason why is because of a third criteria that’s hard to find in large-scale exploration games: total originality. I value the experience of discovering Outer Wilds’ uniqueness more than I value the comprehensiveness of my recommendation, so to keep it short and spoiler-free, it’s a first-person spacefaring adventure about uncovering the cause of a natural disaster. You’re not given any direction on how to accomplish this, you just hop in your spaceship and head out to whatever planet looks best to you. There’s no hand-holding or patronizing tutorials, you’re expected to go and explore just for the joy of uncovering a mystery. All the triumphs, the beautiful moments, they’re all earned by your diligence, and success isn’t just handed to you. While being left to your own devices can make the times you’re stuck feel a little agonizing, the payoff at the end is easily worth it. If that sounds even remotely interesting, please give this game a chance. If there’s any game that deserves a chance to surprise you, it’s this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alien Soldier&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Solo game development is a high-risk high-reward prospect. The developer’s dream game might not appeal to anyone else, or it may be crippled by the need for one person to exceed in all the arts of game making. However, if the game does manage to come together, you can get totally unique experiences that just exude personality. For Alien Soldier, it was the vision of a Treasure employee named Hideyuki Suganami who wanted to follow up Gunstar Heroes with the ultimate 2D shooter. Even though the Genesis’ hayday was over by the start of development in 1994, he wanted to make the definitive action game for it before 3D hardware had totally overtaken the market. That’s a tall task for one guy, but I would be confident in stating he succeeded. Alien Soldier really might be the best 2D shooter of all time, and you can feel Suganami’s understanding of the genre through all the mechanical polishes most people wouldn’t even think about. For example, most sidescrolling shooters either lock you in place as you shoot or force you to shoot in the direction you’re moving, but in Alien Soldier you can freely swap between the two to handle different enemies. You swap weapons with a weapon wheel, but since some players might push right to rotate the wheel clockwise, and others would push right to select the option on the right, there’s also a linear display to prevent confusion. In a nice touch for expert players, the health/ammo/damage bars can be set to either be graphics, numbers, or hidden entirely. These polishes still aren’t standard in 2D shooters, and most don’t have the smart pacing that this game does either. Alien Soldier has short levels that mostly serve as a way to recharge your health and ammo between the incredible boss fights, and there’s no wasted time or filler levels. It’s the ultimate example of an “all killer, no filler” game, it’s wonderfully imaginative and challenging from front to back. My only suggestion for when you play (and a hint at the game’s over-the-top personality) is to flip the difficulty from SUPERHARD to SUPEREASY. Hard mode is meant to play like an arcade game with its limited continues, but easy mode lets you just select a new set of weapons when you die, in case your current set is unsuited to the current challenge. It really is hard to talk about this game without getting into another one of those little polishes. I could gush about all the little things this game gets right all day, and still wouldn’t be able to convey how cool and fun this game is. Please play it, it’s $1 on Steam and easy to emulate. Actually, I’ve offered to buy people copies before, and I’m extending that offer now. Just hit me up and I’ll buy it for you. That’s how much I want people to try this game.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="recommendations"></category></entry><entry><title>Rambling vague complaints at TLOU2</title><link href="http://birb.uk/TLOU2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-24T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-24T19:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Uni</name></author><id>tag:birb.uk,2020-06-24:/TLOU2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Unorganized vague critical rambling about TLOU2 that isn't from a fanboy of the first game or someone who hates LGBT people&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This will contain spoilers for both games in the series. These games are solidly focused on their narratives, so I didn’t see a way I could write in a spoiler-free way that wasn't just two sentences saying the gameplay is the same. This is essentially a combination of review and recap for people not interested in the games, or have already played and need a review of what just happened. Continue at your own risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Labeling a narrative as predictable isn’t the useful criticism it seems to be. If an audience walked into a Bond movie and was asked to guess what was going to happen, they would probably be closer to 70% correct than to 30%. The movies follow a formula, and while audiences can be fairly secure in the fact that everything’s going to be ok, they stay excited and tense anyway. It’s hard to avoid having a sense of empathy for the hero’s struggle, and this connection makes the story enjoyable regardless of its predictability. In the case of The Last of Us, this principle was used to the game’s advantage. The game opens with Joel losing his daughter in the first days of the zombie outbreak, and one timeskip later, you see him meet Ellie, a girl of the same age. It’s easy for audiences to draw the parallel and extrapolate where this story is heading. The relationship between Joel and Ellie may start out pretty cold, but they’ll grow together, Joel will begin to see Ellie as a surrogate daughter, and there will be a moment at the end of the journey where Joel has to decide if he can give her up. This predictable trajectory lets audiences appreciate the little moments that build the relationship, and steep in the dread of their separation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the first game’s clear structure, The Last of Us 2 struggles to communicate what the story is about. The best way to demonstrate is to give a rundown of its introduction. You start out playing as Joel, shortly after the events of the first game. He and Ellie have moved into Jackson, the town Joel’s brother, Tommy, established in the last game. Joel talks with Ellie, but their relationship has gotten noticeably colder, and it’s obvious something between them has changed. It then skips to the game’s present-day, four years later. You play as Ellie, and are introduced to the friends she’s made over the years, most notably her new girlfriend Dina. After getting acquainted, riding around the town, and discussing news with the locals, you play as Abby, a new character who is searching for somebody outside the town. You then go back to Ellie, spending time on patrol with Dina, and you learn a little more about their history. As a blizzard rolls in, they stop their patrol and hitch up in a mountain cabin. You switch back to Abby, who was attacked by an infected horde when she broke from her group in a reckless search for the mysterious individual. She’s rescued by Joel and Tommy, and they all retreat to the cabin where Abby’s group was staying. As it turns out, Joel was the man they were looking for, and they start torturing him. You switch back to Ellie, and she’s informed that Joel has gone missing. She races to the cabin with Tommy, charges in, and is restrained by the group as she watches Abby kill Joel. Ellie and Tommy are spared, and time skips forward to the point where they are discussing what to do next. Tommy convinces Ellie that she should wait before chasing after the killer, and she agrees to wait for a day. He uses that time to head out before her, and a day later, Ellie and Dina leave town to find Tommy and learn about the group that killed Joel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I went into a much higher level of detail for the second game, and I could have made the first game sound worse, it’s not strictly due to bias. Even with some fluff of its own, its plot thread is singular and consistent. The pre-outbreak sequence establishes Joel as a character, a post-outbreak sequence establishes the setting, Joel meets Ellie, and the game begins in earnest within the space of an hour. The second game establishes three characters with their own motivations in multiple hours of non-linear events, and after all that, it’s hard to tell what exactly the point of it was. It's worth keeping in mind that my summary even leaves out plot threads that don't end up mattering (LGBT intolerance in the town, townspeople not knowing Ellie is immune, hordes have been approaching the city, Tommy knows Ellie's secret, general romantic drama, etc) so the amount pointless baggage being placed on the audience is even higher than I'm making it sound. If the point of all this exposition is to make you want to go after Joel’s killer, why is so much time spent in flashbacks, learning about a setting where the game won’t be taking place, talking to people who don't matter, and playing as the killer herself? The audience has to assume that all these moments factor into the greater narrative, but coming up with a line of best fit for it all is impossible. Mystery in a story can be a good thing, but mysteries are exciting when the audience understands the central conflict, not because the conflict is confusingly established. The only arc the audience has a grip on is that Ellie will go after Abby, they’ll fight, and she’ll probably realize that revenge won’t bring Joel back. It’s enough to get the ball rolling, but the narrative would be better served with a presentation that establishes itself in a more concise and focused manner. Regardless, this is the point where the journey begins, so now’s a good enough time to quickly address the gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s almost exactly the same as the first game. This is another case where I’m not trying to sound dismissive, but the enemy roster has a grand total of one addition. The human enemies work without any notable differences, except that they seem a little keener this time around. With your new ability to go prone, stealth is slower than before, and crawling from bush to bush to avoid detection is common. You also have some new things to craft and new skills to buy, but there’s no way of getting around the fact that 80% of your time will be exploring empty buildings, pulling open drawers, avoiding Clickers, and doing stealth takedowns just like before. The biggest difference is how little it’s tied to the story this time around. The first game was broken into seasons, which served as episodes with unique settings and conflicts. With the intro, four seasonal episodes, and a fifteen hour run time, the story developments were coming at a steady pace every few hours. The relationship growing between episodes provided a constant through-line, and the slow moments highlighted how Ellie and Joel are changing. The Last of Us 2 doesn’t follow this structure, and you don’t even have a consistent companion to help guide the story in this way. Instead of pivotal moments between seasons, you occasionally get flashback sequences showing vignettes of Ellie and Joel’s interaction between games. The idea may have been to have the flashbacks show the lessons Ellie learned from Joel in the past as she applies them in the present, but I struggled to find any such connection. A flashback of visiting a museum happens around the time Ellie catches up to one of Abby’s collaborators and tortures information out of her, and I’m still trying to reconcile the two scenes. Was the point to show a loss of innocence? If so, that was already one of the major themes of the last game, and there’s no reason to rehash it here in a clumsier way. Was it to show Ellie had a strong bond with Joel, that motivated her to avenge his death? That’s something we already established, given the fact we’re on this adventure in the first place. The flashbacks just further confuse what this story is really about, hinting at a development in Ellie and Joel’s relationship that informs the current plot, but they only vaguely tie together. You just fall into a pattern between the non-sequitur flashbacks of collecting materials, crawling, killing another one of Abby’s friends, and hoping it starts clicking eventually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, after cutting through all of Abby’s collaborators, Ellie and Abby finally confront each other. Abby kills one of Ellie’s new friends (he’s only mentioned one time in the rest of the game, so no big loss), shoots Tommy, and threatens to kill him. She makes Ellie drop her weapon, and it seems like the bad guy has won, when…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cliffhanger!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You spend the next ten hours in an extended flashback as Abby, going over what she’s been up to the last few days. You hang out with all the characters you have been systematically hunting thus far, and she has her own flashback sequences similar to Ellie’s within her own giant flashback. To put it mildly, this is a neck-breaking lurch in pacing. You go from having a fully upgraded character and customized weapons to one with absolutely nothing, and from the conclusion of a story to another long intro sequence where you meet new characters, visit their home, and get re-tutorialized. It’s not hard to see the idea behind this, with the parallels between the two characters being highlighted to a painful degree. Each had loved ones taken by the other, both are out for revenge, both had caring father figures that they lost, both loved going into flashbacks about visiting museums, the amount of similarities makes the direction unmistakable. While this is as blatant as you can get, we previously established that predictability can be a good thing, and this type of storytelling has potential. The issue with it comes down to the aforementioned lurch in pacing. It could have been presented as two stories running in parallel, building suspense as two unstoppable forces scream towards an unavoidable collision. It could have been presented just from Abby’s point of view, letting us judge Ellie’s actions in a more objective way. Even without any story reorganization, it could have let us analyze Joel in this way, given that Abby’s father was the surgeon Joel killed when rescuing Ellie at the end of the last game. Out of all the ways this story could have fleshed out the characters, we’re left with the one that’s simultaneously the least interesting, the most jarring, and the way that comes across as treating the audience as idiots by dumping 10 hours of explanation on them. I think this will be a deal breaker for a lot of players, who will find it hard to engage with the story through the eyes of someone who killed a beloved character, especially after being ripped away from their hero before the journey is complete. Even players who are more receptive to the idea will start her campaign not realizing this isn’t just another quick flashback, and excitedly rush through it to see the conclusion of Abby and Ellie’s confrontation. However, there’s a lot of story to go before you can get to that point, and it’s a frustrating process to realize what exactly you’re in for. You spend hours on patrol, hours walking across town to visit an old friend, and the rest of it saving the lives of two runaways from a militant luddite society. The details aren’t worth going into, the takeaway is the parallel to Ellie’s story. She has complicated relationships with her friends, she risks her life for the benefit of others, she brutalizes her enemies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, after hours of buildup and just as many hours of waiting, the confrontation finally begins. Abby is immediately disarmed, and the two begin a punchup. One horrible boss fight later, Abby wins the fight, spares Ellie a second time, and says she doesn’t want to see Ellie ever again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, we reach the end of the game. About a year passes, Ellie and Dina move onto a farm and Dina has a child, fathered by that guy who existed exclusively to get shot earlier. They live a happy life raising their child and their sheep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not really though. Ellie is haunted by the fact Joel still hasn’t been properly avenged, and Tommy is trying to get her to see it through. Despite the fact that Abby has beaten her twice already, killed her father figure/mentor, killed the father of her child, crippled Tommy’s leg and shot his eye out, and only decided at the last moment to not slit Dina’s throat, Ellie chases after Abby once more, abandoning her peaceful life. Abby meanwhile has abandoned her militaristic ways, searching for members of her late father’s (slightly) more peaceful organization. However, she gets kidnapped by slavers, and Ellie races to catch up. She finds Abby near death, rescues her, and it looks like she’s going to show mercy, but instead demands a fight to the death to settle the score. This time Ellie is about to win, but she has another flashback of Joel just before the kill, and decides not to kill Abby. Abby rides off, Ellie returns to an empty home, the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, at the end of all that complicated story presentation, we somehow ended up back at the story we had guessed after pushing aside all the extraneous details: Ellie went after Abby, they fought, and she realized that revenge won’t bring Joel back. The question I’m left with at this point is why we had to spend so much time laboriously defining a message the audience would have understood just fine without the extra work. A personal arc like in the first game could have carried the experience, but the extra hours of exposition don’t actually establish one, and Ellie is single-minded in her quest for revenge until the last 10 minutes of the game, abandoning her wife and child for the sake of revenge about an hour before the game ends. The setup could have worked just like it did before, with a predictable and straightforward framework that lets the audience appreciate Ellie’s personal journey. Instead, we end up with a confused mix of subplots that don’t end up mattering, themes that were discussed in the first game, and an overloaded cast of characters presented in an unpredictable structure that jumps perspectives and time frames constantly. It’s not that The Last of Us 2’s story is outrageously bad as people have made it sound, it’s just told in the most confused way possible. With how much more streamlined the game could have been by focusing on Abby instead of Ellie, I’m wondering why her campaign wasn’t the focus rather than a pace-breaking distraction. The answer may be obvious when you consider how much controversy the game generated when you only play as her for half the game, and I’m going to go over the controversy as a fun way to wrap this up, and make the horrible comments I’ve read serve a purpose somehow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Killing Joel was disrespectful to fans of the series, and it throws the previous game's development in the trash&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to see where this complaint is coming from, no one likes to see their favorite characters die, but Joel is a product of his environment. The reason why he’s so beloved is because of the ways he’s been formed by his apocalyptic existence, and to put him off-limits to the harsh justice of the setting is to do a disservice to the character. It would be wrong to say the game would be strictly worse if he survived, but arguing his death is disrespectful is equally incorrect. I also don't understand how his death could somehow invalidate his character arc, when his death is a direct consequence of how he bonded with Ellie so much he couldn't let her go. His fate is certainly tragic, but it's entirely consistent with how the world was established in the first game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) Joel never would have let his guard down, he trusts no one, and he would never enter the house of someone he didn’t know, or tell them his name&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think people who say this are forgetting the details of the last game. Joel started out fairly guarded, but he worked with a partner. He worked as a smuggler, brokering deals between people he may not know and trusting it’s not a setup. He trusted the leader of the Fireflies enough to travel across an entire country to bring Ellie to their facility. Between games, he settled in with a community of people, and lived a peaceful life with them for four years. He mentions how he has a good relationship with the traders and migrants who pass through, and he was close to the town when this incident went down. You also have to consider the lack of alternatives he had at the time, running away from a massive horde of infected in a blizzard with minimal survival supplies. If people were arguing that the blizzard and horde were contrived, that’s something I could understand, given that severe weather is never a gameplay element after that point, and there is never another horde attack. I just think people are looking at how Joel’s a dangerous guy and treating him like Batman, a super-survivor who never makes mistakes and is justified in all his actions. The perspective that he’s an amazing guy may lead to the next controversy, saying...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) It's horrible to make people play as Joel's killer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this seems to be an odd complaint for the setting. It’s repeatedly emphasized just how horrible Joel’s actions were towards others, including ambushing and killing civilians. Being unable to empathise with Abby is natural, but declaring her as more horrible than the other protagonists is an overreaction. If you reject the idea that Joel could be at the receiving end of his own brutal style of justice, you’ve turned him from an interesting character into Batman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4) It uses violence to a depraved extreme&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a third time, people are either misremembering the first game or ignoring it for the purpose of piling on criticism. Cutting people’s throats open with broken glass was a full-on game mechanic (shivs) and you see a guy literally shoot himself in the head after killing his kid brother. Meanwhile, I've seen an incredible amount of criticism surrounding the fact you have to kill a dog in this game, with people saying it's just too much. I don't follow the logic saying the latter is more excessive than the former.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5) It’s misery porn&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See above&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6) The game is agenda-pushing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LGBT people do not need to justify their existence. Similarly, I’ve seen a load of dog-whistle hatred directed towards Dina, who is Jewish. I believe a large part of the outrage surrounding the game comes from the loathsome cunts who stir shit like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I guess that’s pretty much it. If I had to say whether I liked it or not, I wouldn’t feel too strongly either way. Even though I’ve criticised it for about five pages, there are plenty of things to appreciate. I didn’t experience a single bug, the animation is incredible, and the gameplay is extremely polished even if it’s extremely samey. It also reinforces the themes in a couple elegant ways, like naming all the enemies and giving them relationships with each other, and it’s not presented as a big dramatic sacrifice when main characters die. They’re just talking one second, then they get shot and fall over. Abby’s story in particular does this well, where you spend hours watching her risk her life to save a former enemy, betraying her organization, and going into the ground-zero for the zombie plague just to get them some medical supplies, only for the rescue-ee to wordlessly take a bullet and die soon after. It’s not a belabored point, Abby never comments on how this reflects the futility of violence, she never mentions regretting spending all that time on something pointless, it just happens and she’s forced to keep it together and stay alive. That’s why I find it hard to get angry about this game even when it has so many issues. It does have a good story and great impactful moments like this, there are just way too many stories and way too many pointless moments for the quality ones to ring true. I would still be willing to play The Last of Us 3, but I hope they’re willing to reign in the scope next time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="TLOU2"></category></entry><entry><title>Uni's 2019 Wrapup</title><link href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-26T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-26T12:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Uni</name></author><id>tag:birb.uk,2019-12-26:/uni-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Uni spent a way too long writing like 38 pages of short game reviews of the things he played in 2019 so you better read it&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="a-look-back-at-about-11-games-from-2019-and-77-that-werent"&gt;A Look Back at about 11 Games from 2019 and 77 That Weren't&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year my retro-game-safari really took off, and I got to hit a lot of the games I had been meaning to play for years. Just like last year, the table of contents is alphabetized so you can find the games you're interested in quickly, but the paragraphs are ordered by when I played them so you can see my memory resolution increase over the course of the document. I'm not including replays like Shatterhand or games that don't have a defined end like Starcraft 2. Enjoy, and thanks for being here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#428"&gt;428: Shibuya Scramble&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#actraiser"&gt;Actraiser 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#aerobiz"&gt;Aerobiz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#aloneinthedark"&gt;Alone in the Dark&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#babaisyou"&gt;Baba is You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#bg2"&gt;Baldur's Gate 2: Shadows of Amn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#bastion"&gt;Bastion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#catherine"&gt;Catherine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#cavestory"&gt;Cave Story+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#chronotrigger"&gt;Chrono Trigger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#chulip"&gt;Chulip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#clocktower"&gt;Clock Tower&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#crashbandicoot"&gt;Crash Bandicoot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#ctr"&gt;Crash Team Racing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#cuphead"&gt;Cuphead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#darkwood"&gt;Darkwood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#deathstranding"&gt;Death Stranding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#deusex"&gt;Deus Ex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#dmc5"&gt;Devil May Cry 5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#dinocrisis"&gt;Dino Crisis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#discoelysium"&gt;Disco Elysium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#dkc"&gt;Donkey Kong Country&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#doom"&gt;Doom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#doom2"&gt;Doom II: Hell on Earth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#dragonslair"&gt;Dragon's Lair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#edf5"&gt;Earth Defense Force 5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#eternaldarkness"&gt;Eternal Darkness: Sanity's Requiem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#eye"&gt;E.Y.E: Divine Cybermancy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#fatalframe"&gt;Fatal Frame&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#fear"&gt;F. E. A. R.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#ff7"&gt;Final Fantasy VII&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#fetbb"&gt;Fire Emblem: The Binding Blade&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#gatoroboto"&gt;Gato Roboto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#godhand"&gt;God Hand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#grimfandango"&gt;Grim Fandango Remastered&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#halflife"&gt;Half Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#hauntingground"&gt;Haunting Ground&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#jakanddaxter"&gt;Jak and Daxter: The Precursor Legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#jetsetradio"&gt;Jet Set Radio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#journey"&gt;Journey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#silius"&gt;Journey to Silius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#k0"&gt;Katana ZERO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#killer7"&gt;Killer 7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#killerisdead"&gt;Killer Is Dead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#kungfu"&gt;Kung Fu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#mm11"&gt;Mega Man 11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#ghostbabel"&gt;Metal Gear: Ghost Babel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#mm"&gt;missed messages.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#ninjagaiden"&gt;Ninja Gaiden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#ninjagaiden2"&gt;Ninja Gaiden 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#observation"&gt;Observation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#outlast"&gt;Outlast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#ttyd"&gt;Paper Mario: The Thousand-Year Door&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#quake"&gt;Quake&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#rainworld"&gt;Rain World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#ratchetandclank"&gt;Ratchet &amp;amp; Clank&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#re"&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#re0"&gt;Resident Evil 0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#re2"&gt;Resident Evil 2 (2019)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#re6"&gt;Resident Evil 6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#re7"&gt;Resident Evil 7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#shadowofthetombraider"&gt;Shadow of the Tomb Raider&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#slaythespire"&gt;Slay the Spire&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#slycooper"&gt;Sly Cooper and the Thievius Raccoonus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#spyro"&gt;Spyro the Dragon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#stalker"&gt;S.T.A.L.K.E.R.: Shadow of Chernobyl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#smb"&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#systemshock"&gt;System Shock: Enhanced Edition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#systemshock2"&gt;System Shock 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#titanfall2"&gt;Titanfall 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#morrowind"&gt;The Elder Scrolls 3: Morrowind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#zelda"&gt;The Legend of Zelda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#linksawakening"&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Link's Awakening&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#majora"&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Majora's Mask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#messenger"&gt;The Messenger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#tombraider"&gt;Tomb Raider&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#2hu16"&gt;Touhou 16: Hidden Star in Four Seasons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#lunanights"&gt;Touhou Luna Nights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#unavowed"&gt;Unavowed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#underrail"&gt;Underrail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#umiharakawase"&gt;Umihara Kawase&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#viewtifuljoe"&gt;Viewtiful Joe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#wolf2"&gt;Wolfenstein II: The New Colossus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#wildguns"&gt;Wild Guns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#yomawari"&gt;Yomawari: Night Alone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2019.html#shit"&gt;Zero Escape: Zero Time Dilemma&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p id="messenger"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Messenger&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It’s a bad sign when the game I sit down to review on this beautiful October afternoon is one I have a hard time saying anything about. Starting from the basics, it’s a 2D Ninja Gaiden style platformer… until it isn’t. It’s all about exploration in the second half. Kinda. You can just get hints that tell you exactly where to go and it’s the same as before. The inelegant merging of ideas extends to the writing, which flips between clever banter and referential meme humor. The best encapsulation of these issues is how a beautiful and well-executed setpiece is followed up by the game literally stating “that event alone is totally worth a second playthrough if you ask me!”. The flicker of appreciation that had begun to grow was immediately stamped out with yet another out of place gag. If you can logically assess the quality of the gameplay, this game can be enjoyable, but the huge amount of awkward missteps prevent anything but the weakest of recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="428"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;428: Shibuya Scramble&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Visual novels aren’t typically my thing, but Spike Chunsoft’s Nine Hours, Nine Persons, Nine Doors is in a cozy spot on my top ten. These guys also developed Danganronpa: Trigger Happy Havoc, which had me completely gripped for a full twenty-four hours. 428: Shibuya Scramble got a better reception than either of those games, and was finally brought to the PC late last year, so I had to pick it up. Even without the prestigious context, a quirky live-action visual novel was still unique enough to be worth a buy. Sure enough, my first few hours were a blast. Instead of being a strictly linear narrative, you swap between various characters to see different perspectives of the plot, so you have a perfect setup to enjoy the intrigue and dramatic irony. However, starting at about the halfway point, the humor and charm this setup is made for gets replaced by straight-faced drama. To give you an idea of just how straight-faced I’m talking about, finishing the game unlocks an animated prequel story. There are no decisions or interactions, it’s just a direct telling of one character’s tragic backstory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wanna guess how long it is?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TWO AND A HALF HOURS. If this long-winded drama was just as good as the humor, maybe I could have finished the whole thing, but it wasn’t even close to the same quality. Even though I truly love parts of this game, the ball and chain of melodrama weighs it down too much to recommend it to anyone but an extreme visual novel enthusiast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="clocktower"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clock Tower&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Resident Evil is embedded in the popular consciousness as the starting point of the survival horror genre. Given that Clock Tower was released on the SNES, it’s pretty easy to see why that perception is incorrect. Not only did Clock Tower do mansion-exploring horror before Resident Evil, it was pioneering a stealth-focused style of horror almost a decade before Haunting Ground. For such an ambitious concept to be executed in a way that holds up to this day is an amazing feat. The aspect I’m most impressed by is the physicality of the protagonist, who doesn’t have the endurance to constantly sprint everywhere and fend off monsters, which is a given in most games. You actually have to save your energy for when you really need it and to use strength as a last resort. Having limited resources is the keystone of survival horror, but this is the only game I know of where the limitation is physical wellbeing rather than the standard ammo and lifebar. It’s a cool concept that’s worth checking out, especially for fans of the genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="yomawari"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yomawari: Night Alone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now that I’ve finished gushing about a good survival horror game, allow me to not say much about a survival horror game I don’t like. The best way to sum up my thoughts is that Yomawari copies the weaknesses of Silent Hill without the advantage of its strengths. Silent Hill has lackluster gameplay that mostly consists of walking from point A to point B, but it’s propped up by a uniquely holistic style of narrative presentation where every detail, from your controls to the enemy design, is relevant to your understanding of the world. Yomawari has wandering and item collection, but the plot and presentation are similarly point A to point B. While big-headed-child-alone-in-a-scary-world is a proven concept, Yomawari brings nothing but the basics to the table. There may be a workable concept here, but it’s not a unique one, so I can safely put this as the first anti-recommendation of the wrapup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="fetbb"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fire Emblem: The Binding Blade&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I can’t give any useful criticism of this game, to be honest with you. I played this game because I wanted to check out classic Fire Emblem, and just like with my other Fire Emblem experiences, I thought it was ok at best. If you’ve played other games in the series, this one will be just what you expect. If you haven’t, then this wouldn’t be the game to start with. If you are one of those newcomers, I would recommend the one just called Fire Emblem on the Gameboy Advanced. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="bastion"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bastion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Bastion is one of the most powerful gods on the indie-gaming pantheon, next to the likes of Braid and Fez. It was part of the first wave of indie titles which brought the concept to the public eye, thanks to its wholly original visual presentation and simple but rewarding third person action gameplay. The problem is that you’re reading a review written in 2019 and not 2011. It’s still a fun and good looking game, but indie development has gotten more ambitious since then, and Bastion’s ideas have been refined in subsequent games. If you haven’t played it yet, I would caution against thinking of it as one of the all-time-great indie titles, but I would still say it’s definitely worth a playthrough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="cavestory"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cave Story+&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If Bastion deserves your attention for its spot in indie gaming history, then you know what I’ll say about this one. Cave Story wasn’t the first indie game, but it’s to indie gaming what Super Mario Bros. is to platforming, the game which set the template for years to come. However, just like Bastion, being early to the party can have its disadvantages. It has a quirky pacing for its plot and difficulty that serves as a reminder for how it didn’t have many similar games to turn to for guidance, and the lack of a unique selling point can make it seem bland among its peers today. However, the quirkiness is executed just well enough to contribute to the charm, and it never gets so difficult that people are going to bounce off of it. If you’re in the mood for a charmingly simple indie platformer, you can’t go wrong here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="stalker"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S.T.A.L.K.E.R.: Shadow of Chernobyl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Stalker has a reputation for being the Fallout for cool hardcore gamers, but this perception may be part of why the game is considered so niche in the first place. Starting up Stalker and expecting to dive into the loop of exploration, combat, and gathering will leave you feeling disappointed in all three respects. In Stalker, these pillars of open world shooting have all been designed to convey the harshness of the irradiated zone, rather than to provide a traditionally enjoyable experience. The best example of this is how looting enemies for weapons, something that’s a no-brainer in other rpg’s, is almost pointless. Life is cheap in the zone, guns are everywhere, not having one at hand means you’re probably already dead. That’s great from a worldbuilding perspective, but it goes against the open-world standards to a degree that anyone trying to play with those assumptions is going to have a bad time. This is why fans of it, including myself, will say that you should play Stalker and enjoy it specifically for the ways it alienates you. The resulting atmosphere is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Appreciating some clunkiness does not mean appreciating bugs. I recommend installing the Zone Reclamation Project (ZRP) mod, as it is the lightest-touch bug fixing mod out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="majora"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Majora’s Mask&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Majora’s Mask is hard to critique when its flaws are a direct result of how the game was able to be made at all. Ocarina of Time was a smash hit, so taking advantage of a veteran development team and the assets they made to quickly put out game seemed like a great idea. Even as someone who isn’t a Zelda fan, I have to say that it really, really was. The creative freedom afforded by low development risk lead to what is easily the most artistically ambitious game in the series. Taking a franchise centered on freedom and exploration and putting a timer to it was an incredibly bold move, and the morbid atmosphere it serves to strengthen is even bolder. Sadly, that ambition has a double edge, and the limitations are hard to miss. Watching different characters deal with unavoidable disaster is incredibly interesting, but either through the N64’s limited memory or the low amount of development time, the interaction with them is barebones. Most characters have about three different versions of dialog, and you complete a quest by talking to them at a specific time with a certain mask on. The rigidity and lack of depth can make you feel a certain detachment from the narrative, and the immersive quality takes a huge hit. Even so, the experience as a whole is fairly captivating, and I can attest that it holds up enough to win over at least a few Zelda skeptics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="re2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resident Evil 2 (2019)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This game is considered a remake of Resident Evil 2, but that’s not entirely true. That’s even when using the term “remake” somewhat loosely, like in the case of Resident Evil for the Gamecube. The key point when considering the difference between the two is continuity of the core challenge. In the original games and the remade Resident Evil, the core challenge is applying character and resource limitations wisely, allocating your reserves in proportion to the difficulty of a given challenge. This isn’t what Resident Evil 2 REimagined is about, but it’s hard to notice that at first. It’s not because of the over-the-shoulder perspective or the enhanced movement, but in the inability for players to wisely invest resources. To cut to the chase, similar to Resident Evil 4, this game has an invisible difficulty adjustment system. I won’t divulge everything it does so you can enjoy the game without being spoiled, but I believe that just knowing it exists will prevent frustration. Resident Evil 4’s adjustments could be handled gracefully with its linear structure and item drops coming from enemies, adjusting your supply levels without interrupting the pacing at all, but Resident Evil 2 didn’t use this type of system. It instead has set locations for items and a small nonlinear play space, so the only place to make changes was with the enemies. Players in a rough spot may cripple zombies with a single bullet and incapacitate them with four, when a well-performing player may require five and ten respectively. If you enter a new room and intelligently devise a plan, only for it to be thwarted by enemies that are suddenly incredibly durable and aggressive, the difficulty adjustment is why. You have to put aside your frustration and accept that the game is trying to make sure you stay on the edge of your seat, even if it means being unfair. In a genre about making smart decisions, these foggy parameters cripple the experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since arguments about difficulty can easily be dismissed with a “get good” and it seems like such a minor issue get worked up about, I feel the need to finally show my badge. I beat Resident Evil 2 six times, including a hardcore S+ run with each character, where the enemies are stronger, you can only save 3 times, and have to beat it in two hours. The reason I enjoyed doing all that is the same reason why I said you should know about difficulty adjustment before starting the game. Once the cryptic mechanics are demystified, the game can be enjoyed as the most cinematic action game ever created. There isn’t a Devil May Cry level of depth, but the reactivity from each enemy in such a nuanced environment leads to an incredibly satisfying gameplay system to master. That’s why I recommend it under the caveat that you give it your full attention over multiple playthroughs. After all, if I stopped after my first run, this review would have ended after the first paragraph. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="lunanights"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Touhou Luna Nights&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Well, that Resident Evil 2 review sure got long huh. Let’s make the followup review short and sweet, because that’s a perfect description of the game itself. It’s a four hour long love letter to the Touhou series, presented as a sidescrolling search action game. That’s standard indie-game fare, but with a suite of fun time-manipulation powers and beautiful presentation, it’s elevated into a joyous experience. A lot of that joy will be derived from your appreciation for the franchise, so I wouldn’t go so far as to say everyone should pick this game up, but for Touhou fans it’s a no-brainer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="2hu16"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Touhou 16: Hidden Star in Four Seasons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This one will be even shorter. This is another Touhou game with all the standard Touhou stuff. Fun! If you want to check out the series, you can find the games on MoriyaShrine.org, but a few of the latest ones (including 16) are available on Steam. English patches can be found pretty easily, and older games have pre-patched versions ready to go. My personal favorite is the tenth game, Mountain of Faith. The one I started with and consider to have the most manageable difficulty for beginners is the seventh game, Perfect Cherry Blossom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="umihara"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Umihara Kawase&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For a lot of these reviews, I expect that people have a general idea of what the game I’m talking about is like. Nothing too complex, just what the game looks like and the genre it falls into. Here, I have no such luxury: Umihara Kawase is a platformer for the SNES centered around your ability to use an elastic fishing hook to navigate levels and defeat fish. The amount of nuance this hook requires is absolutely insane. Applying pendulum physics with a standard rope would already be tricky, but the movement and complexity created by its elasticity makes for a game that seems unassuming at first, but will quickly push you to the limit. Luckily, the way you progress through the game is designed with that difficulty in mind. There are about 50 stages, but you only need to beat about 10 to finish the game. Most have multiple exits, so you can plan your route through the game based on the specific skills each one expects from you. You also start with ten lives, which will get blown through extremely quickly in your first couple hours, but feels generous once you get the hang of it. It can be frustrating at first, but it’s a great game to keep installed and visit when you have a few free minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="actraiser"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Actraiser 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While the term “action game” is well-defined for 3D games, it’s more nebulous for sidescrollers. There isn’t a landmark title that fills the role of Devil May Cry to separate the casual hack-and-slash games from the more demanding action titles. At least, there isn’t one that’s popularly accepted, because Actraiser 2 has enough depth and challenge to fill the role. At the start, you would be forgiven for thinking it’s a simple spin on the Castlevania formula with its plodding movement and combat, but the game will beat the shit out of you until begin appreciating the real capability of your moveset. It’s a fantastic example of character growth not being tied to a progression system, but through smartly designed challenges that prompt discovery of unobvious mechanics. To put it simply, there’s a reason the player character is called “The Master”. The hero of the story will be the person who pays attention and learns; everyone else will be destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="linksawakening"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Link’s Awakening&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There are three well known facts about Link’s Awakening: it started out as a port of A Link to the Past, it has a lot of references to other Nintendo games, and it’s pretty good. This information can be interpreted two ways. In a direct interpretation, it’s a quirky spin on the Zelda franchise built on A Link to the Past’s framework. For the cynically minded, it’s a cut-down expansion pack with some additional referential humor. Surprisingly enough, even a Zelda skeptic like myself has to admit it’s the former. Even with the limitations of Gameboy hardware, Link’s Awakening has a personality of its own while retaining the quality of its Super Nintendo cousin. That said, it’s easy to see why this game was next on the list for a remake. Having so few buttons to work with means that pausing for item switching is required constantly, and there are a couple pacing issues with the backtracking between dungeons that could be smoothed out. I haven’t played the remake, so I can’t comment on how well it addressed those problems, but I can say that they’re not big enough problems to scare you off from enjoying a classic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="ghostbabel"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metal Gear: Ghost Babel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While there may be three well known facts about Link’s Awakening, the only thing people hear about Ghost Babel is that it’s weirdly good for a Game Boy adaptation of such a cinematic series. While Metal Gear did start out in 2D, this game came out two years after Metal Gear Solid, so it had to find a way to join the old style of gameplay with the new cinematic presentation. Ghost Babel is somewhat successful in this regard, with a narrative that lives up to the series’ standard while maintaining adding to the stealth mechanics with some unique gadgets. However, even with fun tools, the stealth isn’t robust enough to support the level of backtracking the game relies on in the second half. The 3D games transition to action setpieces towards the end for this very reason, but the limitations of the Game Boy meant the potential for impressive cinematography was limited. While it makes for a remarkable achievement for the console, it’s probably not going to wow anyone other than series fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="morrowind"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Elder Scrolls III: Morrowind&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If Skyrim had an alternate title, a natural choice would be “Dragonborn”. The narrative surrounds the return of the destined hero, who follows in the footsteps of a mythical figure at the center of a religious conflict. Oblivion’s alternate title would be similar, with something like “Hero of Kvatch”. The quests focus less on the destiny of the hero and more on their heroic role in a variety of events. What I consider to be beautiful about Morrowind is that there isn’t a title that works nearly as well. Morrowind’s story is actually about Morrowind. Progressing through the main story slowly unravels the history of the land, the values of its people, and the goals of the organizations they created. I don’t want to give any spoilers past that, because I consider it to be the gold standard of story presentation in an open-world RPG. The only caveat is how dated every other element feels. The movement is incredibly slow, which makes the sparse map features feel even more spread out. Even in the later games the combat is lackluster, so the primitive implementation here feels especially stiff. It took me three or four tries to get past how dated some of the elements of this game are, but I’m glad I was eventually able to push through. If you’ve bounced off this game in the past, I recommend doing yourself a favor and trying again, even if that means installing a couple mods to smooth things out. Get the interface and movespeed just how you like it so you can appreciate a classic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="dkc"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Donkey Kong Country&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Mario games are the strongest influence on the platforming genre today, but it represents just one of many styles that have developed over time. Sonic games are the first alternate approach most would think of, but cinematic platformers were the clear inspiration for Donkey Kong Country. Another World is considered a founder of the subgenre, being one of the first games to show that platformers could actually present an atmospheric experience. Donkey Kong utilizes some key sensibilities of the genre, prioritizing natural environments over readable ones, moody tracks over catchy loops, and limiting the amount non-diegetic elements on screen. One final similarity is in the difficulty, but this is where the strength of cinematic platforming turns into a traditional platforming weakness. In cinematic platformers, the difficulty is usually meant to enforce a deliberate pacing. You’re meant to feel like your life is actually on the line, and that you should carefully consider each move before making it. Donkey Kong’s implementation of that difficulty however sticks with Mario tradition, testing how well you can learn new level gimmicks. Just as you’re getting immersed in the atmosphere, brutally difficult level gimmicks break the flow and leave you wishing that the environments were more clearly defined. This means you can either interpret the game either as a traditional platformer that’s beautifully atmospheric, or as a cinematic platformer with bad pacing. With atmosphere being something I’m personally drawn to in games, I leaned towards the latter. The high difficulty of the later parts of the game let down what I felt were its best qualities, even though it still makes for an all-around decent game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="dmc5"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Devil May Cry 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Reviewing the fifth game in a series is of questionable usefulness. If you’re a fan, you’ve probably followed the game’s release to some degree, and if you’re not, the fifth entry is rarely the best point to jump in. While that sounds like a cop-out to not write anything helpful at all, I would still like to take the time to say that this game is sick as hell. I’ve beaten it five times and completed the 101 level challenge mode twice, and I keep it installed so I can jump back into it whenever I want. It’s a worthy entry in what is arguably the most celebrated action franchise of all time, bringing the best bits of each entry together into one explosive package. That should be enough to convince the Devil May Cry fans, so if you’re one of them, you can stop here. For everyone else…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I said above, the fifth entry is rarely the best place to enter a series, and this is no exception. There is some disagreement about that among fans, with some saying that the gameplay is such a focus that people should have no qualms skipping the story, but I disagree. While the story is simple, it was designed to satisfy the fans who have been patient enough to follow the series over its 18-year lifespan. Missing out on all that context will remove a lot of the charm from the game, and if you enjoy the combat alone, you probably would have enjoyed the previous entries as well. So, if the series interests you, pick up the HD collection on your platform of choice. The first game may feel a little old, but it’s polished enough to reward your patience. If you really can’t get past its age, Devil May Cry 3 is an improvement in every way, and is also a prequel, so you won’t feel lost. If both disappoint, you at least got to try out a legendary series for cheaper than diving straight into this game would be. If you end up loving them, you’ll be in a perfect place to appreciate everything 5 has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="wildguns"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wild Guns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you were given a minute to write down every video game genre you could think of, there’s one I bet you would miss: the arcade port. It doesn’t even seem like a genre, as it doesn’t explicitly describe the gameplay, but arcade ports were big business in the early days of console gaming. Paying full price for something that can be beaten in an hour seems pretty bad to modern sensibilities, but when considering how arcade games were meant to be addictive and endlessly replayable, choosing an arcade port for one of the few games you could buy each year was a solid choice. This is the heritage of Wild Guns, a game that replicated the replayability and pace of arcade games in an entirely original title for consoles. It’s a straightforward shooting gallery, but the fun presentation is what makes me so quick to recommend it to people. It’s a beautiful pixel-art presentation of a cybernetic Old West, creating a level of energetic absurdity reminiscent of the Metal Slug series. The gameplay also has some nuance, with a system where you can shoot enemies’ bullets out of the air to charge up your special meter, granting you an Old West vulcan cannon when filled. To facilitate this system, you can always see where enemy shots are going to land, so the game feels entirely fair even when the challenge starts escalating. In this way, it’s a perfect merging of console and arcade difficulty sensibilities. Wild Guns is quick and addictive like an arcade game, without the need for token-taking difficulty spikes, making it sit comfortably near the top of my favorite SNES games of all time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="aerobiz"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aerobiz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Airport business. This is a simulator about airport business on the SNES.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel like I should just end the review there, but I need to say that this game actually delighted me. Being a simulator on such limited hardware meant the game couldn’t be too complicated, and the limited control scheme meant that it had to be accessible. Strategy games today often require lots of time investment to understand, and Youtube research is recommended, so this game was refreshing in how simple it was to pick up and how satisfying it was to learn on my own. Naturally, these limitations have the double-edge of not providing enough depth to satisfy for more than a couple playthroughs. If you’re into the simulation genre, it could be fun to check this out and see the nascent stages of a genre that’s grown so much. If you’re not, maybe it shouldn’t be this game specifically, but I recommend trying out a simulation game. I felt a real sense of accomplishment with growing my business, a type of strategic satisfaction that puzzle games and war games never quite provided. Expand your horizons!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="killer7"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Killer 7&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can’t talk about The Witness without talking about John Blow, and you can’t talk about Killer 7 without talking about Suda 51. Well-known today as that quirky Japanese auteur developer, Killer 7 was the breakout game that established his unique style. His games commonly emphasize the visual spectacle of violence, otherworldly aesthetics, and incomprehensible plots about assassins. Describing the gameplay of Killer 7 will convey even more weirdness: it’s a nonlinear first person rail-shooter with seven playable characters. While the environments look like they would fit in a standard first person shooter, your character only moves forward and backward along a track, shooting enemies that get in your way as you find the collectibles needed for progression. It’s an odd system, but one that streamlines an experience that’s more about narrative atmosphere than gameplay. In fact, it’s streamlined to a fault. Your map shows every relevant location, where all the collectibles are located, and which character is needed in each location to surpass obstacles. The only real agency you have is in the shooting, which is kept fairly basic. The other giant caveat that I’ve alluded to is that the game is about the focus on narrative atmosphere rather than a coherent plot. This is a game for people who appreciate stories where you can form your own opinion or create your own closure, interpreting the emotions of scenes rather than a strict telling of events. I’m finding it hard to describe the appeal here, which is the best summary of why people should give it a try. It’s not so solidly designed that I would say I generally recommend it, and I think even the people who would be interested might bounce off of it, but it’s just so intriguing that you should try it anyway. You never know when you’ll win the niche-appeal lottery and find your new favorite thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="re7"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resident Evil 7&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It’s common for Resident Evil fans to discuss the series as if it’s two different series put together. Since the first three games form a survival horror trilogy, and the next three are almost entirely action oriented, mentally separating them has helped organize discussion and view the games by their own merits. With Resident Evil 7, a new trilogy may be beginning, with a more contemporary first-person style that references our current horror media. This means that it’s a great way for series newcomers to check out the franchise, but there have been a couple drawbacks with this style compared to the others. Resident Evil and Resident Evil 4 were each revolutionary enough to launch an entire genre, and bring a new type of horror experience to the world. Resident Evil 7 doesn’t have that ambition, and is content to build off the standard set by Outlast and Amnesia. It’s a well executed game overall, but there isn’t a moment that will take you by surprise with something totally original. However, seeing as this game is a response to the criticism that Resident Evil 6 was so action-packed that it lost the soul of the series, maybe a convservative approach is just what was needed to reorient the direction of the franchise. If Resident Evil 8 does something more interesting, I’ll look back on 7 fondly, but until then I’m left thinking it’s competent but ultimately bland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="shit"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zero Escape: Zero Time Dilemma&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hoo boy. I love bad games because I get to drop any attempt at writing a good review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I really love the Zero Escape series. Nine Hours, Nine Persons, Nine Doors is in my top 10, and its sequel Virtue’s Last Reward was also pretty enjoyable. The great characters and interesting atmosphere got me enthusiastic for visual novels in general, and they’ve served as a constant source of creative inspiration. Then, this game comes along. It’s not even like it’s a straight-up horrible game, you still have some interesting decisions to make and a couple nice bits of drama, but it’s... all wrong. The best I can do is to have you picture what it would be like if your favorite video game series got shelved for years, then had a chance with one last game to wrap up the franchise for good. The developers then decided that with such a low budget, it would be best to make it a porn parody of the rest of the series. Everyone could have some laughs, some characters could bang, and the plot could be wrapped up all at once in a way that didn’t set fan expectations too high. That’s pretty much exactly what this game feels like. Old characters are brought back in an ultra-flanderized form, the animations are laughably bad, the story is full of holes, and the amount of nonsensical melodrama makes it feel like a critique of the worst parts of the previous entries. There were multiple points where I just sat there, laughing in total shock of what the hell I was looking at. I laughed enough that I could almost recommend the game to fans of the series for that alone, but I can’t in good conscious tell anyone that they would enjoy this game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="re6"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resident Evil 6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is the infamous entry in the Resident Evil franchise where it threw off all pretense of being survival horror, and it took a strong critical beating for doing so. However, being a fan of the classic entries in the series, that feeling of betrayal was already pointed at Resident Evil 4. This means that I could play Resident Evil 6 without the bitterness, and enjoy it as a pure action title. On that level, I have to say it’s actually pretty successful. The shooting may seem extremely standard at first, but the melee system is an underappreciated aspect that elevates the entire game. Similar to how you could kneecap enemies in Resident Evil 4 to allow for kicks and suplexes, Resident Evil 6 lets you stun enemies and perform instant kills after you set them up with the right damage type. Appropriately enough, there are six categories of context sensitive attacks: headshot, attack from behind, coup-de-grace, mini stun, downed enemy, and counter. Headshots or sliding shots cause a mini stun, stacking two mini-stun types leads to a full stun, full stuns can be followed up on with a melee attack for high damage or set up with another stun for a super stun which has its own properties… the list of moves goes on and on. Digging into this system and developing my own style was gratifying, and ability to pull off the crazy moves that are typically only found in cutscenes was some fantastic visual spectacle. However, even as someone willing to defend this commonly panned game, I have to admit the faults. There’s a key-hunting section that appears in every campaign that is an absolute chore, and Chris’ campaign as a whole feels extremely phoned-in. The goofy B-movie plot and wrestlemania chain kills also have limited appeal, and probably won’t carry you through the 20 hours of gameplay unless you’re a big fan of the series, so even action fans shouldn’t take my praise as a strong recommendation. If you can find it for relatively cheap and can set your expectations aside, you’ll at least get your money’s worth. Just do yourself a favor and start on Leon’s campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="godhand"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;God Hand&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
God Hand’s critical reception has become a notable moment in gaming history. IGN famously gave it a three out of ten, citing bland environments, repetitive enemies, and dumb humor as reasons why this was one of the worst action games ever produced. The game was so poorly received that it lead to the shuttering of Clover Studio, home to some of the most legendary talent in the industry like Hideki Kamiya and Shinji Mikami. Fans of action games still burn at the unfairness of it all, and will gladly take any opportunity to explain why God Hand is actually one of the coolest games ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not an action game fan though, so I have to concede to both sides. I think that for a large amount of people, God Hand will legitimately be a three out of ten game. The environments are just as bland as IGN said, and the enemies are just as repetitive. The camera can be extremely annoying, and you’ll die repeatedly from times where it just wouldn’t move fast enough to show you what’s going on. The extreme difficulty can also be a massive turn-off, but this is a point that leads straight into my next thought, which is that this game kicks ass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important thing to realize about God Hand is that the intended experience is getting your ass kicked. In most games, death means you failed, but that's not the case in God Hand. This game has a dynamic difficulty system that’s put right in front of your face, and you can watch the meter ratchet up as you land attacks or dodge enemies. At the first level, you can beat up enemies easily and feel like a typical action game hero, but the fourth level is called Level Die for a reason. Enemies will block your combos and throw you off balance, with two hits being enough to send you back to the checkpoint. This enforces a pace where the game is always pushing you one step beyond your current limit, with death serving as a difficulty recalibration. The clarity of the system mitigates frustration, and it can be used to judge how effective your combo strategy is. The build-your-own-combo system seems like it would have a few setups that are objectively better than the rest, but this isn't the case. When checking out streams and let’s-plays, I was shocked at how differently everyone had set up their move list, a testament to how the system is perfectly balanced for anyone's unique style. Making changes and exploring the full potential of each move was incredibly satisfying when I could tell that the changes let me stay on Level Die longer than ever, even when it still meant I would die in under a minute. The frustration with repetitive death is mitigated with cathartic moments like unlocking special God Hand attacks, or in the beautifully absurd cutscenes which release some of the built up tension. I wish I could share some examples of some humorous or rad moments, but considering how rewarded I felt when beating a level and seeing more insanity unfold, I wouldn’t want to give any of it away. I implore that you try out this game, as it’s in my top 5 best games of the year, and there’s nothing out there like it. Play at least through the first boss, and if you aren’t charmed, then I’ll be satisfied that you gave it a good try. That’s what me and the designers have in common: we both want you to beat God Hand, and won’t let you quit until you've shown that you're truly doing your best. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="bg2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baldur’s Gate 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What’s striking about Baldur’s Gate 2 is just how modern of an RPG it feels like, even when it’s over twenty years old. The narrative focus isn’t so much on the main plot, but in the ways the diverse cast of characters interact and are affected by their adventure. Doing side quests is encouraged with how many companion interactions are included, letting players approach the game at their own pace and build a relationship with the party. However, there’s a pretty big catch to all this, in that the game’s appeal is so centered on the party dynamic that if you don’t like your companions there’s no reason to keep playing. The presentation of the main plot is confusingly bad, with your party essentially serving as mercenaries who serve plot-relevant characters without having any motivation or agency of your own. The gameplay is nothing special, just the most basic isometric RPG stuff without anything exciting to plan around. If you’re the type of RPG player who loves chatting up companions in New Vegas or Mass Effect, you’ll be able to see why this game inspired two decades of RPG’s, but if you expect interesting gameplay or narrative payoff, this one is better left on the shelf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="re0"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resident Evil 0&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Resident Evil series was in trouble around the time of this game’s release. While the first three installments had been massive successes, the subsequent games weren’t so lucky. Resident Evil 3 was followed up by Resident Evil Survivor, a terrible light-gun game which wasn’t actually compatible with a light gun in the American release. Code Veronica was well-received, but didn’t sell well given that it was a Dreamcast exclusive at the time. Resident Evil Gaiden was awful, another light gun game came out to minimal fanfare, and the Gamecube Remake was similar to Code Veronica in its positive reception and low sales. Clearly, something had to be done to rejuvenate the franchise and address the critiques that had stuck to the franchise since the first installment. Firstly, item boxes had to go. Critics always hated the backtracking to put away items, so this game allows you to drop items and manage inventory on the fly. Basic zombies are less common now that people had started getting tired of them. Your carry capacity has also been doubled, as a result of this game’s flashy hook of controlling two characters at once. The first of the two is Rebecca Chambers, a combat medic who will be familiar to those who have played the first game. Her focus is on healing and puzzle solving, when her new partner Billy Coen is more experienced with combat. He has more health and deals more damage, but can’t mix chemicals or herbs, so swapping characters and intelligently splitting supplies is key. Controlling both at the same time is emblematic of how the game’s goal seems to be to combine the survival horror and action oriented tones of the franchise, retaining a Resident Evil identity while streamlining it in key ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was the theory, in any case. Resident Evil 0 is a perfect example of how you can design something that sounds brilliant on paper, but it won’t succeed without understanding the reality of player psychology. Having an inventory system where you can just pick up and drop items to maintain flow sounds great, but would players actually leave stuff behind scattered across the map? Most wouldn’t, and would instead deposit non-critical items in a centralized location for later. Would players split up the team to cover more ground? Probably not, you can still only control one character at a time, and leaving a character alone leaves them open for attack. Billy is also so much stronger than Rebecca that you’ll want to use him for all the combat encounters you can. To encapsulate both these issues at once, it’s commonly recommended to just throw Rebecca’s gun in the trash because she’s weak and you’ll be coming across so many items to ferry from place to place that having an extra slot can save you a lot of time. The measures meant to streamline the experience ended up making it clunkier and slower, and the rest of the game definitely wasn’t good enough to make up for it. The enemies which took the place of zombies are frustrating to deal with, and all the locations after the intro are rehashes of areas seen in previous games. You couldn’t even go into this looking for an interesting story, seeing as it’s a prequel set immediately prior to the events of the first game. Each time the game tried to add a twist, it just made the game less satisfying. It’s a shame that this was the last classic-style Resident Evil, because it’s not a high note to go out on. It’s best to imagine that Resident Evil 0 came out before the remake of the first game, so it can be enjoyed as an interesting but flawed iteration that set up the true swan song of the genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="rainworld"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rain World&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you had a dream for an entirely original game concept, how much would you be willing to compromise your vision for more sales? If it was possible to quantify such a thing, imagine that making it more appealing to the mainstream by 5% would also increase reception and sales by 5%. Would you stick to your guns and create a completely uncompromised game, even if it meant a Metacritic score of 50? Maybe making it just a little easier or a little more direct would be enough, just so you get to the 70 range and get a trickle of word-of-mouth sales. It wouldn’t be a best-seller, but if someone was interested enough to buy it, they would be likely to finish the game with a positive experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rain World decided not to compromise even 1%. This game wants to make a statement about nature, and saw the tiniest bit of compromise to make it fair or predictable as antithetical to the message. For starters, you play as a lonely Slugcat, a defenseless rodent trying to locate the rest of its kind in a journey across an industrial zone overtaken by nature. While predators can snap you up in one bite and machines can crush you effortlessly, all you’re able to do is pick up stuff, throw items, climb, and eat. Your journey is a progression from water lock to water lock, hiding each night from a torrential flood of rain which also kills you instantly. To not starve in the middle of the night, you need to have at least four stocks of food, and surviving a night increases your progression meter by one. Filling this meter to a certain level is required to open the doors between the major areas, but dying means the loss of two levels. This means that to progress to a new area, you have to scour for food sources on a time limit while avoiding unpredictable instant-kill predators and any mistake means you have to repeat the process at least two more times. Once you get to a new area, there isn’t always an immediate water lock, so you have to quickly explore and avoid the new predators after spending most of your time just entering the area in the first place. While those are just the basics, it gives a taste of just how brutal the survival in this game is. I quit the game three times before pushing myself to finish it, and even then I wasn’t exactly having fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I'm belaboring the point of just how little fun I had in this uncompromising murderscape is twofold: firstly, to let you know what you’re getting into if you do decide to buy it, which you just might when you hear that secondly, all the pain was worth it. It all paid off. The slow reveal of the game’s themes was absolutely magical. The ending was a perfect mesh of story and gameplay satisfaction, where I felt like I accomplished something and really learned something. It’s the most satisfied I’ve ever felt when completing a game in my entire life. It’s probably going to end up in my top ten games of all time. If all this sounds intriguing to you, and you think you can handle the pain, I’ll be cheering for you every step of the way. Stay dry, Slugcat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="deusex"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deus Ex&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A lot of games claim to be inspired by Deus Ex, but it’s hard to tell what that actually implies. The most common elements would be an open approach between action and stealth, character upgrades focusing on opening up new routes, and a plot with room for player choice. While Deus Ex has all these things, they only capture the surface level of what is so impressive about the game. What stands out is the level of reactivity to the player that’s much more than just chastising players who kill too much. It’s actually just the opposite, to give one example. Taking out a terrorist cell with lethal force will have some people within your organization respect you more, but others will quietly voice their distaste. Characters will react to the path you took, the weapons you used, or if you did something really bizarre. A lot of choices aren’t presented in a binary way, and choosing to thoroughly assess your options can even affect the outcome in its own rite. It’s extremely impressive how elegantly the game reacts to all the ways players could interact with it, so getting invested in it and being perceptive actually pays off. Antiquated presentation makes the buy-in for that experience relatively high, but it’s worth the personal investment even after so many games have tried to serve as the definitive successor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Just like with STALKER, learning to appreciate an old game shouldn’t mean you have to appreciate a barely functional game. I highly recommend Kentie’s launcher, which lets it work perfectly on modern systems. No gameplay or art assets are modified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="catherine"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Catherine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The common consensus of this game is that it’s two unrelated halves welded together. There’s the block-pushing puzzle half, and the romance anime half. While I agree that it’s weird how separate each element is, I found it to be an interesting sort of pacing. The gameplay is a hectic puzzler where you have to think on your feet, rearranging a wall of blocks to get to the top as each layer below slowly collapses and prods you to keep moving. It hits a sweet spot where you have to be decisive but calm, with simple mechanics that require you think multiple steps ahead. The low-key romance anime interludes were a nice cooldown period, and you can choose to spend however much time you want chatting people up until you’re ready to take on the next level. The problem is that it’s easy for one of these two parts to disappoint, given that neither are good enough to stand on their own. If you become annoyed by one half and interested only in the other, the amount of interruption will be frustrating. The weaker half was definitely the story for me, with a lot of moments I found pretty questionable, only staying afloat with some good dialog and interesting bizarre moments. The gameplay on the other hand more easily held my interest, with loads of room for creativity once I got a grip on the various techniques, even if the creative potential is at the expense of depth. If there’s a running theme here, it’s that Catherine is a game with a lot of components that barely work, but work nonetheless. It’s a good pick-it-up-on-sale candidate if the sound of this odd construction intrigues you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="mm"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;missed messages.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I downloaded this visual novel because it’s about depression and social isolation, which are two things that I deal with, so I thought it would be interesting to hear someone else's experience. But, it ended up being 15 minutes long and not particularly fulfilling, so I'm just putting it on here for completeness. I’ll take this as an opportunity to thank anybody who's reading this, because that means all this work that I'm putting into this has purpose. It's good to know that people care about what I do, and I appreciate you for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="ff7"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Fantasy VII&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When a reviewer gives a negative opinion of a well-received game, you'll commonly see comments that the author is just biased against the genre. While bias is always a factor, I don't think that's particularly relevant criticism of an inherently subjective style of writing. Reviews reflect a single person's personal experience of the game, and shouldn’t be taken as anything more than that. Each review contributes to the larger understanding of the game, which should be used as the guiding point for consumers more than any singular piece. That's why it's important for people of different backgrounds to contribute to the forum and represent a game’s entire potential audience. In short, a reviewer should simply be honest about their biases and not pull punches about their true feelings. In the spirit of this, I would like to say that I am very biased against JRPG's, but I would also like to say that I absolutely loved Final Fantasy 7. I was dreading playing it for the longest time, because it's not a genre I'm interested in, and because I already knew about The Big Spoiler. I figured that without the impact of the biggest emotional moment, it would just be a slog with standard RPG combat and nothing to keep me motivated. However, not only was the combat way better than I was expecting, the story had more twists and turns that completely caught me off guard. I'm almost thankful for The Big Spoiler because it shielded the other reveals from being talked about, ones that I think are much more satisfying and interesting. While I want to dissect what made it so enjoyable, it’s probably better for me to temper the positive vibes, because it's received enough of that over the years. I don’t have any unique perspective to share, and it’s so widely beloved that you should check it out regardless of the specifics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="k0"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Katana Zero&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It's always worth celebrating innovation, but making something derivative can have its own benefits. Being able to analyze existing ideas and refine them can help push a genre forward and give fans an experience they can easily understand and enjoy. Katana Zero amazes me because it is entirely derivative, yet completely unpolished. It's as if the developers set out to copy games that they haven’t actually played. You have the brisk ultra violent action from Hotline Miami without the quick restarting that prevented it from getting frustrating. You have a system that asks for quick and elegant clears like in Ninja Gaiden, but the level design doesn't support at all. You have a slo-mo gauge that should require intelligent usage like Devil Trigger in Devil May Cry, but it simply regenerates on a timer. This creates a system where you feel like you should be competing levels in a cinematically violent flow, but you keep tripping over hurdles that kill momentum. The game even plainly displays this fact to you with its post-level replays that are in real-time. Almost all of them will include multiple moments you had to sit around for a few seconds waiting for your gauge to recharge, or time you had to spend doing some awkward platforming. Not only is there a total lack of momentum in the moment to moment gameplay, there’s none in the chapter to chapter progress. The amount of talky interludes is absolutely insane, and it doesn't lead to any narrative payoff. The story ends on a sequel bait cliffhanger, which is a pretty bold move for an indie studio. Ending the story before I can get interesting means I don’t care how it's going to end, accomplishing the exact opposite of what was intended. I don't recommend this game at all, you should just play one of the games it borrowed from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="gatoroboto"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gato Roboto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Speaking of derivative games, this game sets out the copy Metroid. You might be thinking, “Of course it does, it's an indie game”, but this one is copying Metroid rather than Super Metroid. Naturally, this means the power ups are bog standard for the genre, with the usual sort of missile upgrade and power upgrades, nothing that will take you by surprise if you've played literally any other game in the genre. It’s like they came up with the concept of a cat in a robot suit being the protagonist and counted on it being funny enough to carry the entire game, because nothing else is interesting enough to be the selling point. It’s cute, but not cute enough to keep you fixated for more than two hours. If you have a couple bucks to spend and want a Metroid-inspired game, you could do worse, but I don't see why you wouldn't just pick up Hollow Knight to do a lot better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="eye"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E.Y.E.: Divine Cybermancy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is possibly the king of obscure games. That's not because it’s the most obscure game ever made, but because its completely bizarre presentation encapsulates what’s great about niche games. To oversimplify it, it’s essentially a total conversion mod of Half Life 2 that's mixed with Warhammer 40K fan fiction. Being built off of Half Life 2 can make it feel cheap, but leveraging the Source engine’s physics to emphasize the power of your character was a smart decision. The player character slowly becomes more and more hilariously overpowered with each new cyber-ability, eventually being able to jump over buildings and sprint as fast as a car, so having weight and impact was critical to making progress rewarding. If you can stay interested in the game long enough to unlock those abilities, you’ll definitely have a fun time with it. However, the game is so dark and so narratively confusing that I think most people will drop out of it before it gets the chance to shine. Playing it co-op certainly helps, but this has its own issues with the way mission progress is saved only to the host. Your character progress is saved regardless, but repeatedly losing content is demoralizing. The highs of maxing out your abilities are fairly equally matched with the lows of losing progress and parts that drag. If your desire to play as a godlike space marine is strong enough to withstand even the clunkiest level design, you should give this game a try, because there isn't any other game out there that does it quite as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="unavowed"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unavowed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is a modern adventure game that plays exactly how most modern adventure games seem to play out. That is to say, it's a visual novel where you can pick up items and rub them on each other. Your interest will hinge almost entirely on whether you're interested in the story, which is essentially a Dresden files modern supernatural mystery. If you're OK with adventure games and you like that sort of story, this is the game for you. In fact, this is very much the game for you, considering how much written content this game has. Each mission only allows for two people from your scooby gang of supernatural detectives, so there’s a ton of interactions  that can only been seen on subsequent playthroughs. Puzzle solutions are also unique to each character’s abilities, so the developers put a lot of consideration into how genre fans would dig into it. It’s an easy recommendation if you’re that type of person, if not, it’s a safe pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="slaythespire"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slay the Spire&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In my Final Fantasy 7 review, I mentioned how I think any review can be valid as long as the author is honest about their biases. To be consistent, I’ll disclose that I am very biased against roguelikes and there are few I like at all. Slay the Spire was able to dodge a lot of that distaste with the absolute clarity in its mechanics. Even with the RNG inherent in a card-based roguelike, most randomness outside the deck itself has been stripped out. Enemies always display their next move and behave the same across runs, so you can plan for every move of a fight before it even begins. All the encounter types are shown on a map where different paths can be chosen, so it’s easy to account for different possibilities and adjust plans based on what you need. It’s a fair system that lets you enjoy the interesting mechanics with minimal repetition. The only point where the game breaks down is if you decide to go for the ultimate final boss. This boss is so difficult that each character only has one consistent win condition, and if you don't get set up with it, you'll lose pretty much every time. The game normally allows for a variety of playstyles, so it’s disappointing that the final content most players will experience is a tactical bottleneck. Considering you need to go out of your way to encounter that issue though, it’s a pretty easy recommendation even to people who aren’t typically roguelike fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="joe"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Viewtiful Joe&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When revealing Actraiser 2, I mentioned that there wasn't a definitive 2D action game. Viewtiful Joe seems like it should fill that position, as a 2D action game created by the makers of Devil May Cry. That's not exactly the case though. While Actraiser 2 has a lot of nuance in its controls and loads of different techniques for the player to discover, Viewtiful Joe is more about dodging attacks and punching enemies in slow motion. I previously complained that Katana Zero used a slo-mo meter that should have worked like Devil Trigger, and Viewtiful Joe makes the same mistake. To demonstrate how much the game wants you to use this meter, here’s a list of everything it does:&lt;br /&gt;
Damage dealt is doubled&lt;br /&gt;
Attack range is slightly increased&lt;br /&gt;
Enemies with armor that normally can’t be hurt can now be damaged&lt;br /&gt;
Most enemy attacks will automatically be dodged&lt;br /&gt;
Combos can be performed&lt;br /&gt;
For the game to put so much power behind an automatically regenerating meter means the flow of the action is entirely dictated by how quickly it refills. With combos being locked behind its use, most of the game just feels like a stylish beat-em-up. If that’s all you’re looking for, this game has enough charm to be worth the time, but it’s not what I would recommend if you’re looking for action. Out of all the Capcom and Clove Studio action games, this is probably my least favorite, even if it’s still basically alright. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I would like to note that I’m hesitant to speak about this game at all, given that Matthewmatosis has a video on it coming up, and he’s much better at analyzing action mechanics than I am. I’ll probably look like an idiot for saying what I did. Even so, I stand by it, just be sure to check out his review too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="dragonslair"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dragon's Lair&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you have no idea what this game is, you might want to check it out on YouTube and see how it looks. Even by today’s standards it looks absolutely amazing, and this was an arcade game that came out in 1983. Just for some context, in 1982, Joust and Pole Position were released. In 1984, Marble Madness was released, Atari’s first game to be written in C. Suffice to say, this was the most visually impressive game of all time when it came out. The tradeoff was in how simplistic the actual gameplay is. You’re essentially just watching a movie, with the twist that you need to provide directions to the protagonist as he encounters various hazards. If he’s attacked from the right, you hit the left button and he'll dodge the left, and you just watch until the next encounter occurs. What makes it frustrating is that the timing for inputs can be very tight, and you're not actually shown what button you should hit or when exactly the window is. Considering there’s no life bar and any mistake leads to instant death, it is quite possibly the most token takey game ever made. You wouldn't lose much just by watching someone play this game and avoiding all the trial-and-error trickery this game used to earn more quarters. It’s a fun piece of arcade history, but the best way to experience it is with a no-commentary playthrough on Youtube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="edf5"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Earth Defense Force 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you’ve played an Earth Defense Force game before this, one you will be completely unsurprised with this game. It works the exact same as all the previous mainline entries. For anyone unfamiliar, that means it's still a co-op focused 3rd person shooter where you go against thousands of enemies at a time, taking out giant ants, frogs, and aliens that are all modeled like there were on the PS2. These games look extremely cheap, but the priority for scale makes it feel like an incredibly pure gaming experience.  The best way to describe it is that this is what someone in 1985 would imagine games of the future would be like. It wouldn't be a game that's cinematic and emotional, it would be a game with an entire city to run across, thousands of enemies to shoot, and giant explosions. It's a cheap thrill by design, but not many games dedicate themselves to being so unapologetically gamey that it's a refreshing change of pace. It may not stick in your mind for very long, but you'll still enjoy it the whole way through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="chronotrigger"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chrono Trigger&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After Final Fantasy 7 warmed me up to the JRPG genre, I decided to try my luck again and finish Chrono Trigger. It seems I had been too harsh in my initial assessment of the genre, because I ended up liking this game a lot as well. While it would be easy to point to the combat system or the plot as the reason why, it’s the less obvious elements like pacing and structure that made the game work so well. While there aren’t explicit chapters, the plot is broken into vignettes set in one of the game’s six time periods. For each time-period shift, the party members in the spotlight usually changes as well, so the story is always progressing on three levels. Firstly, the plot offers a slow progression that pays off occasionally in big moments. Secondly, hopping among time periods steadily provides details about how the world changed over time. Thirdly, the party members are always commenting on the plot, the world, or their own personal situation, providing a constant source of narrative progression. Even the sidequests use this three-part design on a smaller scale, so there’s never a point where the expectation is to run through some padded content to get your team some more levels. Nothing goes to waste, leading to a perfect pacing most RPG’s struggle to establish. It’s a great example of a holistically designed game that’s greater than the sum of its parts, so if you can give Chrono Trigger time to impress you, it almost certainly will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="eternaldarkness"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eternal Darkness: Sanity's Requiem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The mansion is a sacred setting for survival horror games. Mixing the familiarity of the home with the possibility of lurking danger is a proven method for creating a setting that’s relatable, yet mysterious. This would seem like a perfect fit for a Lovecraftian horror game, with the mansion representing the game’s universe as a whole. Things may seem normal on the surface, but the search for understanding will lead to some horrible discoveries. That's not what this game does though. After the intro, most of the time spent in the mansion is within a singular room that’s used as a chapter select. From there, each chapter is a flashback to a different time and place, so there’s barely any reason to get invested in the situation of the character you most identify with. These flashbacks provide a little intrigue by presenting the plot through different characters’ perspectives, but it's not an effective way to convey horror. Since there's a reset button after every chapter, you never have to worry about the consequences of any of your actions. As a result, the horror is limited entirely to the subject matter of the narrative rather than its presentation. Nothing demonstrates is better by the fact that you can regenerate your health at the cost of some magic points, which you can only regain by… walking. The game has a sanity system that warps reality around you, but there are also spells to regenerate it for free, so the effects that were so well thought out will almost never occur. The gameplay ends up being about walking around, listening to people talk, and occasionally doing some subpar melee combat. Without a big redeeming quality, this game belongs on the ever-growing stack of Lovecraft-inspired games that failed to live up to the source material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="titanfall2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Titanfall 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When discussing presentation in games, it can be difficult to pin down what exactly that means.  The best way to summarize it is that presentation is the way a game conveys its goals. Effective presentation is when no two elements collide, and nothing was included simply out of obligation or genre standard. Put simply, good presentation isn’t just about looking pretty, it’s about design harmony. Titanfall 2 on the other hand is very pretty to look at, but its presentation is rather confused. There are a couple levels based around gimmicks, a couple based around parkour, and a bunch that are mostly bog standard first person shooting. The goal was variety, but when the unique selling point of the game is the movement abilities and command of a mech, it's odd to focus so much of the game on the least unique aspects. Instead of using the standard stuff as a way to introduce challenge and enhance the cool stuff, the priority is reversed to where the interesting gameplay is used to ferry you between normal shooting galleries. As a multiplayer-focused game, I can't exactly blame it for representing the mechanics in the way they would be used in multiplayer, but as a result a lot of potential goes unrealized. It's an overall enjoyable campaign, but the high points sting when they hint at how much better the game could have been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="tombraider"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tomb Raider&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Describing what a movie is about is pretty easy. Most of the time it’s just a direct depiction of a story, so summarizing the plot is good enough. Things are a little different for games, because the gameplay and the story can be emphasized in varying degrees. For example, Tomb Raider seems to be about preventing powerful artifacts from falling into the wrong hands, when it's actually about jumping. As overly simple as that seems, its focus on the mechanics of jumping makes for the most compelling movement I've ever seen in a game. Modern games have jumping and climbing as an ancillary part of combat and exploration, but in Tomb Raider it’s the gameplay in itself. Even jumping straight up requires decision making, because grabbing onto things isn’t handled automatically. Forward jumps require you to actually build momentum with a run, and trying to jump before you’ve taken enough steps will lead to you sprinting off a cliff. While mostly used for combat, side jumps have their own niche uses, and so on. Every motion needs to be carefully considered against your list of options, because choosing poorly will make you lose part of your very scarce health supply. A system of limited save points also means that screwing up and falling into spikes can be extremely punishing, and you get used to taking every step seriously. It’s a nuanced and tense system for platforming that has gone woefully underutilized by the games of today. This is another case where I could describe all the little interactions and things you can do to improve your gameplay, but taking away the discovery would take away part of what makes this game so cool. In the latest Tomb Raider games, there’s nothing like this to discover. You'll automatically grab and stick to walls by moving the control stick and that's pretty much all that’s ever required. The sense of danger isn’t from the mechanics, but from the movie magic and visual spectacle. Even though the original doesn’t have those technological advantages, the sense of presence and personal involvement is so much greater than the modern interpretations of the genre. It accomplishes so much with so little that it's become one of my favorite games of all time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="haflife"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Half Life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Half Life is just like Tomb Raider in how it made me disappointed in the evolution of its genre. The maturity of Half Life’s story might be what most games learned from, but it’s the relentless variety that should have been the real source of inspiration. A science facility is such fertile ground for seamlessly joining a variety of gameplay themes, with each chapter in a different part of the facility that has its own suite of challenges. Industrial facilities justify a slow-paced exploration where the facility is your enemy, offices allow for a tense atmosphere when aliens could be hiding around any corner, and wide-open zones are used for fast-paced gun battling.  Those general categories will also get a unique twist in each iteration, creating variety in a system that was already keeping you on your toes. Even with so many different styles of play, the smart pacing between sections and distinctive environment design keeps the game feeling cohesive. If I played this game with absolutely no historical context, I would think it's one of the better shooter campaigns I’ve played. That is until the very end levels, at least. I won’t spoil exactly what happens if you’re one of the two people who don't know how the game ends, but suffice to say, they went overboard on creating something unique and ended up with a confusing mess. That's just one stain on an otherwise great game though, so it’s just the tiny parenthetical to avoid disappointment during an otherwise fantastic game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="systemshock"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;System Shock: Enhanced Edition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you're going to compile a list of games that haven't aged well, System Shock would be a good first entry. The interface is the most arcane I have ever used in a game, which on top of early 2.5D FPS technology meant that starting this game was like running into a brick wall. I could see it being too much to get over for 90% of people, but if you can commit to it, you’ll be surprised at how good this game still is. The crux of its quality is its infamous villain, SHODAN, and how it beautifully it frames the entire game. With the gameplay being about exploring a space station, having the antagonist be a personification of the station’s malice keeps the narrative feeling present, and all your victories are direct shots against your enemy. Pulling apart the station for resources isn’t just something you do to increase your strength, it cripples SHODAN’s control over the station and turns the tables in your favor. It’s beautiful ludonarrative synchronicity, a quality I feel was lost as subsequent games copied the format. The Bioshock games also have you repairing and reclaiming your environment, but with a plot that’s been disconnected from the setting itself, it can feel like a tedious distraction before the real conflict begins. Playing System Shock will give you so many little revelations like this, and you begin to understand where so many design tropes in successful first-person shooters came from. I recommend at least trying it out, even if I fully expect a lot of people to bounce straight off of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="systemshock2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;System Shock 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can tell how much I liked System Shock when I decided to go straight into System Shock 2. It didn't exactly disappoint, but my appreciation was stunted by knowing what it was able to build off. While the setting and villain formed a brilliant combination in the first game, this one falls victim to the disconnected story and gameplay I was referring to in the previous review. About 80% of your time is fixing random things that get in your way, sticking you in a narrative holding pattern until the big moments of development. The gameplay itself has been strengthened enough to hold up the weakened overall structure, but it’s disappointing that this compromise was made at all when the same pieces that made the original great are still here. However, the key word to that criticism is “compromise”, and the two games form a balance of priorities where one isn’t necessarily lesser than the other. With accessibility being one of System Shock 2’s advantages, this game is a much easier recommendation than the first one, even if it has the sting of missed potential. The story can be easily understood even if you skip the first game, but I would still recommend going in order if you can. It may not be required, but with how each game compliments the other, it would certainly give you the richest System Shock experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="cuphead"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cuphead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This game is easy to review due to its complete honesty. Its hook is the 1930’s art style, with the gameplay being very basic platform shooting that everyone can understand. If you’re interested enough in the art style to play a middling shoot-em-up, then this game is for you. If you're expecting satisfying gameplay and fair boss fights, this isn’t the place. The game relies heavily on trial and error, with bosses usually having four sets of attack patterns to vastly overpower your ability to survive two hits. Furi was another game that focused on difficult boss battles, but it struck a balance with its difficulty by rewarding players with two lives after every phase, capping at three. This ensured players have at least two chances to learn the patterns before getting kicked back to the start, unlike in Cuphead where you can get immediately destroyed by a new attack you don’t understand. Also unlike Furi, the attack signifiers can be incredibly vague, so chances are good that players will get hit by each attack at least once without any concrete way to have predicted it. The visual design and soundtrack are just barely enough to make this game worth purchasing, but I wouldn’t blame anyone who gets frustrated and disenchanted with it before the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="killerisdead"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Killer is Dead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Mediocre games are usually hard to recommend, but sometimes an unfocused experience can be the most broadly appealing. Killer is Dead doesn’t have particularly deep mechanics for an action game and it doesn’t have an emotionally engaging story, but creator Suda 51’s excessive design sensibilities make it a joy to play. Everything is so cranked up past the point of sanity that you want to keep playing just to see where he’s going with all this. He wanted a protagonist with a cool name, so he went with something so cool that it wrapped around into uncoolness a few times, and landed on “Mondo Zappa”. Cybernetics are cool, so Mondo has a cybernetic arm that’s about the size of his torso. Tarantino-esque violence can look pretty cool, so naturally the gameplay is about using a giant katana with a hilarious amount of blood spray. It’s a beautifully campy presentation, with the unifying idea being simple enjoyment. It would be a great pickup for people looking for the video game equivalent of a comic book, or are interested in an unintimidating entry point to the action genre. It’s also incredibly cheap during Steam sales, which makes the half-baked elements much more palatable. Four bucks and a sense of humor are low requirements for seven hours of fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="kungfu"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kung Fu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For anyone unfamiliar with this game, which I imagine would be most people, this is a very early NES beat-em-up that has five levels which can each be beaten in about a minute. So, the game itself isn't very interesting, but I found it fascinating to consider what gaming was like when Kung Fu was released. Video game titles were things like “Tennis” or “Baseball” and had the optics of a toy more than our current expectation for interactive movies. You just picked it up and played with it until you got bored or won and moved on to something else. Considering how much is expected of even cheap games nowadays, having to pay full price for something like this would incite a riot. At the most simple level though, it offers toy-like fun, and that should always be worth something. It’s sad that the concept of simple toy games seems to have lost its last shot in the spotlight when the mobile market got dominated by microtransaction riddled garbage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="ninjagaiden"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ninja Gaiden&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ninja Gaiden is one of the most influential platformers on the NES, but the first thing someone should understand before playing it is that it doesn't actually abide by the sensibilities of a platformer. Games like that are typically about balancing speed and caution, with speed allowing you to clear longer gaps and avoid more enemies, and caution letting you anticipate the danger of hazards past your vision range. When playing Mario games, most people just hold the run button down by default, but this balance is the reason why Mario doesn't always move at maximum speed. It demarcates the two priorities you can have one traversing a level, letting you deliberately switch between the modes of reckless efficiency and safety. Ninja Gaiden’s buttons on the other hand are jump and attack, hinting that the two gameplay states aren't between caution in speed, but of speed and aggression. There is absolutely no room for caution here, taking any steps backwards will have enemies immediately respawn and kill you in seconds. How soon enemies respawn when you start backpedaling can make the game feel extremely unfair, but the level design begins to shine once you discover the flow among the hazards. When you need to make it to the boss and are effortlessly slicing through every enemy without pause, it gives you the unique satisfaction only great action games can deliver. I’ll add the parenthetical that there are some parts where I think the difficulty spikes into unfair territory, but for the most part I would say that satisfaction is worth the effort. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="silius"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journey to Silius&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There is a hardware bug in the NES that prevented developers from using differential pulse-code modulation for their music. If a sample byte is fetched from memory at the same time the game is reading from the controller, a conflict occurs that corrupts the controller data. This meant software workarounds were required, such as Mario 3 repeatedly repolling the controller until two consecutive inputs matched. Sunsoft also went this extra mile, and it let them make some of the best tracks on the console. That music is why I played this game, and it's pretty much the game's only redeeming quality. It's a very basic side scrolling shooter without anything unique other than the fantastic soundtrack. It's particularly frustrating because it's from that era of games with limited continues, meaning that you have nine lives to beat five stages, some with multiple bosses. It's an exercise in frustration, and you're better off experiencing this game by youtubing the soundtrack rather than playing it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="ninjagaiden2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ninja Gaiden 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Technologically speaking, it’s hard to argue that Ninja Gaiden 2 is anything but superior to the first game. It looks better and controls much more smoothly, with new level gimmicks and a more fleshed out story to keep the experience fresh. The tradeoff was that with all the fancy new additions, the tight focus on action with momentum was lost. Falling platforms, wind effects, or levels lit only by flashes of lightning is neat to see on the NES, but gimmicks like these should serve to enhance the core gameplay rather than supplant it. Unlike Ninja Gaiden, caution is a very viable strategy, with new power-ups that are strong enough to let you brute force most challenges as long as you can avoid falling into a pit. Again, these power ups are cool and fun to use, but once the novelty wears off, it doesn't give you the same level as the first game. It may have its strengths, but there’s a reason why this isn't known as the Mario 3 of its franchise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="zelda"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Legend of Zelda&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Breath of the Wild’s attempt to bring Zelda back to its roots revitalized the discourse surrounding the original entry. Since this game was advertised as being a return to the classic ideals, the positive reception has been shared with the old one, and their shared tutorial-free open design has received a ton of praise. The only downside for modern audiences who want to check out the original is that it’s known for being extremely confusing and a game that you can't complete without a guide. Since I was already on an NES kick, I decided to put both of these ideas to the test, and I was surprised at how wrong both of them were. The game is certainly as open as people have been saying, but the caveat is that going outside recommended areas will lead to getting your ass kicked incredibly quickly. The idea that you’re left with no direction in a gigantic open world really isn’t true, it’s just that the direction is given implicitly rather than explicitly. Design like that may be harder to pick up on as a kid, but since I’m a big kid now, I was able to complete this game fairly quickly without using a guide. With this perspective, the genius of Zelda’s world design became a lot easier to appreciate. The way you’re always close to the next bit of progression while still being allowed to figure things out on your own gives the advantage of a linear difficulty pacing while still feeling completely open. In short, the truth about this game lies in between the two conceptions about it, in how it forms the perfect illusion of openness and mystery even when your journey has actually been planned from the start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="ttyd"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paper Mario: The Thousand Year Door&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It’s common for turn-based RPG's to be recommended with the qualification that it only gets good tens of hours in. One would think this wouldn’t apply to something as straightforward as a Mario RPG, but I bounced off The Thousand Year Door on my first playthrough for this reason exactly. The first two chapters of it are about as standard as an RPG can be, fighting a dragon in a castle and following it up with exploring a dungeon inside a big tree. You won't be blamed for thinking it's the world’s most generic RPG with Mario on top, but then the third chapter cranks the personality up to eleven. From that point forward, the charm is so strong that it actually got me interested in Mario games in general. It does so many fun things with the Mario universe that it reminded me why the series is so big in the first place. There’s a lot of fun to be had in a lighthearted game with a small but polished set of mechanics, and it’s a smart way to have mass appeal that’s also free from compromise. Some games drop the ball when trying to court audiences with additional features, but Mario is appealing specifically because it lacks those elements. The Thousand Year Door doesn’t even have a basic character attribute system, each party member just has a defense number, a health value, and a special move. That’s all it needed to make everyone feel unique, and no confusing elements were required. Anyone can understand this game and have a good time with it, at least as long as you don’t need a meaty challenge to hold your interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="dinocrisis"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dino Crisis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The goal for Dino Crisis in development was to make a more fast-paced style of survival horror, which the developers referred to as panic horror. Instead of scrounging bullets to take down shambling zombies, you have a good amount of options to take down dinosaurs who are much faster and stronger than you. Preparation is the key to panic horror; you need to learn how to assemble your inventory and develop backup plans for the inevitable surprise attacks. It’s a fun and fresh take on the genre, but it does feel limited by the Playstation’s limited hardware and Resident Evil development heritage. The mental picture of dinosaurs chasing you as you frantically activate laser grids is one thing, but the reality of stiffly navigating hallways as the dinosaurs get stuck on corners is another. If Dino Crisis lived up to the strength of its premise, I think I would like it even more than Resident Evil, but it never got the refinement its sister series enjoyed in sequels and remakes. I can still give this game a recommendation, but it pains me how much more I feel this series could have been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="ctr"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crash Team Racing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cart racers live and die by how well they stand up to Mario Kart, and this game definitely passes the test. Mario’s carts are floaty and simple to drive so you can focus on track gimmicks and items, but Crash focuses on weightier carts that require skillful driving on a more standard set of courses. For this reason, I don’t think I could declare a winner between Mario Kart 64 and Crash Team Racing, because they both succeed at their own unique style. They’re both just fun games. Go play both if you’ve somehow gone this long without doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="crashbandicoot"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crash Bandicoot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With Crash Bandicoot’s style of 3D platforming being set in long hallways, it can be pretty easily compared to 2D platformers, with the best example being Donkey Kong Country. Both were visually groundbreaking games with immersive environments and brutal difficulty, taking players across a variety of zones filled with their own unique challenges. So, just like in my Donkey Kong Country review, I have to point out that the challenge and immersion didn’t mix well. Some levels are absolutely enchanting with their details and visual polish, but as visual styles get reused for increasingly difficult stages, the magic wears off and you're left repeatedly running down a corridor and getting smashed. Being the initial attempt at the concept means it deserves some level of forgiveness, but after the good first impression wears off, you'll definitely wish you were playing one of the later games in the series. It certainly belongs on the list of historically important games to play, but I wouldn't predict that people would fall in love with it today as they did back then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="spyro"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spyro the Dragon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Playstation needed an answer to Mario, and it got one with Crash Bandicoot and Spyro the Dragon, but as a unit rather than individually. Crash covered the platforming challenges, while Spyro handled the fun open spaces and colorful atmosphere. While completely devoid of challenge, it’s a beautiful game with a lot of quirkiness that gives it a Mario-like charm. However, if you're playing this game for the first time, it's going to be hard to get over just how much this game was geared towards kids. Challenge isn’t even something I highly value in games, but with just how little brain activity this game requires until the last couple stages, it can be painfully dull. If you can succeed in turning your brain off there will be plenty to appreciate, but you're not going to have very much fun in the gameplay itself. Just like Crash, this game belongs on the list of historical games you should check out, but more because of its status as a founder rather than an exemplar of its genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="journey"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Journey is one of the first games labeled as a walking simulator since it came out about a year before Gone Home, where the term exploded in popularity. It was one of the pioneers of games entirely about a visual experience rather than any form of traditional gameplay challenges. This makes it difficult to critique, because the only criteria the game seeks to be judged by is how visually beautiful you find it to be. Surely enough, I found it to be visually spectacular, but those scenes went in one ear and out the other. Not having to think much while playing can be immersive, but that can come at the cost of not imprinting itself deeply in memory. It’s well executed, but shallow. That’s a perfectly acceptable design priority, but it’s hard to generate enthusiasm about. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="observation"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Having bought this game on the premise alone, I think I should share exactly what I heard: this is a narrative focused game that’s like essentially 2001 A Space Odyssey if you were playing as HAL. It’s a fairly accurate description, when you control the AI that runs a space station as you communicate with the sole survivor of an undefined disaster. Uncovering the mystery through its limited camera system is a novel experience, albeit a slow one with how sluggish the cameras move around. It suits the mood for a game that’s trying to tell a story through its environment and a slow burning sense of suspense, and over time you begin to form a picture of what the station was like before you came online. I was afraid that meant I was in for an understated ending that wouldn't feel satisfying, but the story actually has a conclusion that left me with a positive impression. It's not one of the best video game stories I've ever seen, but if you want some well presented pulp sci-fi, here it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="jetsetradio"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jet Set Radio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If there's one truth about pop culture trends, it's that they don't age well. It takes something incredibly special to actually last, and I was surprised to see that Jet Set Radio somehow pulled it off. Even though it's steeped in the extreme sports and bright colors of the early 2000’s, it remains timeless by including their strengths in a holistic game design. From the basic starting point of knowing players will want to move around quickly on skates, the developers knew that the sense of speed and flow was critical. So, the maps are laid out as a network of corridors which feed into each other. If players can recognize how different paths link, momentum can be transferred gracefully as you navigate to each objective. With the goal being to recognize optimal paths, having small maps that the Dreamcast could handle didn’t feel like a limitation at all, and instead a smart choice to facilitate a smooth skating experience. The bright cel-shaded art style also let the developers squeeze a lot of power out of the hardware, so going fast and spinning the camera around wouldn’t be a problem at all. This neatly works together with how the levels are a series of corridors, meaning that render distance is kept minimal without feeling artificially constrained. With it being so well-engineered, the only gripe I can think of is how the game can feel pretty bad before you get to the starting point of that design, moving at high speed. Getting moving from a dead stop takes a long time, and the imprecise nature of moving on wheels means the smallest mistakes causing you to fall down feels like a repeated slap in the face. For the first hour of gameplay, you may be wondering if I made up everything I’ve said about speed and momentum, but after some practice, the game’s qualities will click into place. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, this game was a bitch to get working on PC with a controller. I’ll save you the trouble and just tell you to download x360ce and map your controller with it, then you’re good to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="underrail"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Underrail&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Researching games before you buy them is critical if you want to be a smart consumer. On the other hand, it’s also important to know when to stop. It's good to get an honest assessment of a game’s strengths, but picking apart the gameplay mechanics and planning strategy is usually going too far. The only reason I’m saying “usually” instead of “always” is because of a game like Underrail. This is an RPG that’s so demanding that if you don’t do build research and planning before you begin, you’ll almost definitely hit a brick wall and be unable to finish the game. Even with a Google doc that laid out exactly what I needed to do, this game was still pretty difficult, so I can’t imagine what it would be like going in blind. Actually, it’s fairly easy to imagine, given the hundreds and hundreds of complaints I saw during my research from people who made builds that weren’t good enough and had to quit before the end. The isometric, post apocalyptic RPG stylings may have made people think it would be simple like Fallout 2, but this game’s structure is very different. Most of the time your progress entirely relies on combat effectiveness rather than your capacity for clever approaches, and you’re not going to be able to talk your way through things with any reliability. If the idea of forty hours of isometric turn-based combat after a couple hours of build research doesn't immediately scare you off, then you need to seriously consider playing this game. The upside to having a game this complex is that it has a crazy amount of options to play around with once you know what you're doing. The reason why the research is required is so you can have the right skills to surmount a few difficulty walls, not because the whole thing is so punishing that it's impossible to play if you're not optimized. After getting through the first playthrough, you know enough to just make up fun gimmick builds and take the systems to their limit. For anyone that fits within the overlap between RPG fans, difficult game fans, and optimization fans, this is the game for you, but if you don’t fit into at least two of those categories then it’s best to give it a pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="babaisyou"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baba is You&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Describing this game as a simple block pushing puzzle game would be doing it a disservice, even if it’s an accurate thing to say. While you are pushing blocks, and it is a puzzle game, the focus is less on the geometry of blocks and more about what they can represent. To explain what I mean, the title of the game is actually pretty descriptive of what you see in game. The blocks are tiles with words on them, corresponding to the ones in the title. You have subject tiles like “Baba”, verb tiles like “is”, and objects tiles like “you”. An example puzzle would be a wall being in the way between you and the win flag. If nearby tiles said “Wall is stop”, you could move the “stop” tile away from the other two, and walk through the wall which can no longer stop you. While that description makes it sound fairly simple, the amount of possibilities this system allows for a huge problem space. Luckily, the difficulty is presented in a very friendly way, with each completed level opening up multiple options, and getting to the credits only requires about 25% completion. Not only does this help people having trouble with the game, it can also give you an easy out if it still feels too much like a standard block pushing puzzle. While I was one of those people, I have to admit that the cute concept and low price makes it at least worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="smb"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
If you’ve never committed to sitting down and beating Super Mario Bros. all the way through, you probably should. It’s not just a cultural touchstone for video games, but for pop culture in general. Consider it a homework assignment from me to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="aloneinthedark"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alone in the Dark&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When reviewing Eternal Darkness I mentioned how the mansion is a sacred setting for survival horror games, and when discussing Clock Tower I mentioned that horror games started way before Resident Evil. Both of those statements were allusions to Alone in the Dark, arguably the first modern-styled survival horror game. It has all the same key hunting, puzzle solving, and limited supplies, along with a few other inclusions that were way ahead of its time. In particular, it told the story through notes and books around the mansion rather than directly stating, which seems like a trend that only started catching on after Bioshock did it fifteen years later. If you're interested in playing historical games then you'll be delighted by this one, but on the other hand, the technology is so painfully dated that I don't think it'll impress you on any level other than how influential it was. It's a neat game to visit, but not one that can be recommended strictly on its own merits anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="grimfandango"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grim Fandango&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There’s more than one way to tell a story. We're used to a style where events are plainly recounted, but visual media allows for a less direct conveyance of information. Aesthetic details can flesh out the world without getting in the way the plot, leveraging the strengths of the medium to quickly draw people in. This is Grim Fandango’s biggest success: its world is entirely unique, and it enriches the narrative without needing wordy exposition. That’s a good quality for the game to have, given how difficult it is to verbally summarize what it’s about. It's an adventure game set in the Aztec land of the dead, with the basic plot hook being that you're a travel agent helping people with their four year journey to eternal rest. Clients are offered travel packages based on their deeds in life, but after one client gets cheated out of a premium package, your adventure begins. It’s a mishmash of mystery, romance, and comedy presented in an exaggerated film-noir style that somehow ties the disparate elements together. It's easy to see how all that would make the world of Grim Fandango incredibly compelling, but there's still another type of storytelling the needs to be addressed. An interesting world can be a great setup for a story, but there still needs to be at least some plot to keep things moving. This is where the game is much weaker, and it fails to have a solid narrative focus throughout. It's split into four chapters, and the first two live up to the setting’s potential, but the beginning of chapter three marks a downturn in quality. To put it in a spoiler-free way, all narrative momentum comes to a screeching halt and a cliche villain takes the spotlight for the rest of the game. It feels like an obligation to see it through rather than a continuation of the quality you were enjoying the first half.  Lucasarts puzzles are already notorious for making people bounce off a game, so when they just keep coming and the quality keeps dropping, Grim Fandango leaves a bad last impression. It's still good as a whole, but those frustrations add up to where it can't be recommended to anybody but genre fans, unless they are very patient or ok with using a guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="outlast"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outlast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Polish is a quality that's hard to quantify, but Outlast is a good example of how a lack of it in key areas can bring down an entire experience. This is a survival horror game where the main resource you manage is the batteries in your night vision camera, so players should be anxious that they’ll run out and be left alone in the dark. However, with the dark sections being so dark that you can’t see at all, you receive an extremely generous supply on top of getting a free refill when you load a checkpoint. Not only does this keep you safe regardless of how poorly you play, even the people who play well can abuse the system by loading immediately after the game says it’s saving. Feelings of vulnerability won't last long when you're constantly reminded that any mistake can be corrected by a loading a checkpoint from a minute ago. You’re also constantly reminded of the controls, with text boxes popping up whenever you encounter something with contextual actions available. Little things like this kill immersion, like how there’s a crosshair in the middle of the screen even though aiming is never required. Some of this stuff can be turned off in the menu, but leaving them enabled by default means that it’ll sublty subtract from the enjoyment until players get fed up and go look for how to turn it off. With so many of these little problems and a few too many cheap jump scares, Outlast feels little more than satisfactory. It wouldn't need much change to be great, it’s plain to see how much better it could have been with a little more thought put into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="re"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resident Evil&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Everyone knows the remake of this game is one of my favorite games of all time, but I had never actually played the original until now. All the enjoyment I got out of this game ended up coming from comparing it to the remake, because this game in itself is not very good. The key hunting gameplay that this game established felt great in the remake since it got you engaging with the atmosphere of the mansion, but the level of detail is so low in this version that the mansion just feels like a normal house. Everything is brightly lit and furniture is sparse, so it’s a trek across endless boxy rooms and encountering a minimal variety of enemies with not much else going on. In essence, it’s the ultimate barebones survival horror experience, with everything except the basic framework removed. I’ve played the other Playstation Resident Evil games and I like them a lot, so this one is falling victim to its own status as an innovator. It doesn’t hold up, but it gave us a lot of good games and spectacular remake, so I should probably let it off the hook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="hauntingground"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Haunting Ground&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is considered the swan song of classic survival horror by virtue of being the last one Capcom developed without over-the-shoulder action. It came out just a few months after Resident Evil 4 redefined the genre for a new decade, so it was an attempt to correct the flaws of the old style so the formulas could coexist. However, as you can probably guess given the lack of sequels or similar games, that plan didn’t work out. It ended up being what is essentially a clone of Clock Tower, where you play as a disempowered teenage girl navigating a mansion and avoiding pursuers as you do standard key item hunting. There are gimmicks on the side like alchemy and bonding with a dog companion, but there’s no avoiding that the game is 90% running from room to room looking for keys. Since the only enemies you regularly encounter are the pursuers, who are dealt with one-at-a-time in their dedicated chapters, it's weird how little horror there is in comparison to the amount of tedium. If being chased was going to be the only meaningful gameplay, it should have been more nuanced than entering contextual hiding places once you’re out of sight. It’s so simple and predictable that the parts meant to be a climax of tension end up being little more than interruptions as you try to reach the next story moment. All this game ended up accomplishing was compiling all the things people were tired of into a single package, and it was eye-opening to see why people had become so disinterested in a genre I love. I have to give the game points for giving me a new sense of understanding for survival horror history, but I would have preferred a good game instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="fatalframe"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fatal Frame&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When reviewing Outlast, I mentioned how constant checkpoints and unlimited supplies can prevent a feeling of vulnerability that I think is important to horror games. Oddly enough, this is another survival horror game focused around using a camera, and it has the exact same design flaw. In this case, it’s how the save points scattered around the haunted mansion can be used as many times as you like and provide you with an unlimited supply of film for your ghost-exorcizing camera. While moving from room to room should be a tense experience where you’re unsure when ghosts will strike, having a HUD element to tell you when one is nearby so you can ready your infinite ammo weapon eliminates that possibility. The design of the ghosts themselves is spectacular, but this visual aspect is the only place where horror actually manifests itself. Fighting them is also a shallow and repetitive process, pointing at them until your indicator changes color and snapping the picture. The story isn't enough to rescue it either, sitting comfortably among the bog standard plots of the horror genre. There are enough good ideas here to where the potential of the sequels intrigues me, but I can say that this entry doesn’t live up to the series’ reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="discoelysium"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disco Elysium&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Just as there are innumerable ways to tell a story, there are innumerable ways to internalize one. As a story is presented to an audience, it gets filtered through each person’s unique perception of the world, and it’s this adjusted view that is then consciously considered. Shakespeare’s plays are the closest thing we have to objectively good stories, but even these can have wildly different meanings to each person. This is where Disco Elysium puts a lot of faith in its audience, expecting people to confront their biases and consider alternatives in a mature way. It’s an isometric RPG where the main murder-mystery plot is almost an afterthought, with the actual purpose of the narrative being discussion of a wide range of philosophical topics, and the roleplaying is how your character sees the world. It's the only RPG I've seen that takes advantage of how a player's choices reflect back on them, and it allows the game to engage the audience on a more personal level. The game assumes that you’re interested in this sort of dialog and can entertain alternatives, playing devil’s advocate to question you for every decision. It accomplishes great things with the RPG format, but the payoff relies almost entirely on that trust in the audience’s willingness for discussion. If you want the game they give you direct plot payoff or conclusive ending, you probably won’t leave fully satisfied. If you want to engage with it as a normal RPG and learn which stats will give you the best outcome, the game won’t give you that either. The only kind of person this game will pay off for is for someone who finds joy in ruminating on different ideas and reflecting on how they shape the world. If you're not that kind of person, the game won't exactly be miserable, but only a small subset of people will grasp the full breadth of its quality. At least for them, this could be one of the best games they've ever played. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="darkwood"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Darkwood&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I don't consider myself to be a game designer, but let's pretend we're game designers for a minute. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to make a survival horror game, with a more literal sense of survival than something like a zombie game. Players will have to survive in the wilderness, hiding from creatures and maintaining their hideout at night with supplies they gathered during the day. Given these constraints, what player behaviors should be incentivized and disincentivized? Personally, I think the virtue of diligence is the critical component. Players should be rewarded for thoroughly scrounging for supplies and making sure enemies don't sneak up on them, and maintaining every potential weak point of their hideout during the night. Players should be punished for any form of carelessness, whether that be in supply expenditure or by being killed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this hypothetical discussion in mind, it's fascinating how Darkwood, a game with that exact setup, doesn’t follow those ideas in the slightest. The game’s emotional climax should happen every night as you have to defend your home from monsters, but if the monsters kill you, the only penalty is not getting a small amount of money. You keep all your supplies, and get fast forwarded to the next morning. It can actually be optimal to die every single night if you would use more value setting up your defenses than you would earn by surviving the night. If you die while exploring, there is a penalty of leaving your backpack behind where you died, but only half the items from the pack get left behind, and you can circumvent the penalty altogether by putting items in your quick bar instead. The developers seem to understand this problem, given that higher difficulty modes have a limited amount of lives. Losing them all means losing your save, no continues allowed. The gap between these difficulty settings is ludicrously high, meaning that you'll either have almost no tension or you’ll be manic with tension as you risk losing 10 hours of progress. I applaud anyone with that level of determination, and I bet it makes the game a much better experience if you have the patience for it, but there has to be a better way to raise tension than with a simple lives counter. It disappoints me how such an elegantly simple and darkly imaginative game couldn’t figure out this design problem and ended up with a mediocre game as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="doom"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Doom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The original, not 2016. This is another case like Super Mario Bros. where I think everyone that loves games should beat it. It's so fundamental to games as a medium and still holds up so well that it's just a requirement. One tiny tip though: the final episode in most releases, “Thy Flesh Consumed” was added as a set of challenge levels in Ultimate Doom. Those levels get pretty crazy, so it’s extra credit and not part of the homework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="quake"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quake&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
While Doom let me have fun from the beginning, Quake took some warming up to. Doom starts you off gently with low numbers of shotgunners and imps, who can each be taken down with one shot. By comparison, the basic enemies in Quake can tear you to shreds immediately and require a few seconds of concentrated fire. Trying to play in a slow methodical way will have you getting demolished repeatedly, even when you feel like you're not making any mistakes. Enemies just seem to come from random corners, grenades are bouncing everywhere, and the levels are so complex that it can feel random and overwhelming. The key thing to realize is that while sprinting around enemies in Doom was a careless way to play, it's what you have to do just to survive in Quake. The basic enemies using powerful but slow grenades was meant to inform you that the best way to handle an enemy is to be in constant motion and maintain fire as you pass. Once you get the hang of the combat’s momentum, this game really get amazing.  The high speed mixed with enemies that demand careful reaction placed within intricate level design makes for an experience that simultaneously rewards instinctive skill and observational intelligence. As much as it’s become a video game boomer meme to say, I have to admit that Quake really does hold up beautifully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="fear"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F. E. A. R.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Dismissing games as just being good for their time can be a contentious idea. If Doom can hold up even as the father of its genre, doesn't that invalidate the idea that subsequent games should be given a pass for being dated? Of course, there is a lot more complexity to the question than that, but it does raise the point that it's difficult to judge games outside of the historical context into which they were released. F.E.A.R. received a lot of praise for its atmosphere and enemy design back in the day, but through today's lens its accomplishments seem much less impressive. The horror elements are certainly an interesting inclusion, but the way they're so disconnected from the rest of the game makes them feel like a random gimmick more than a key element. The enemy AI does make smart moves, but it's plain to see how much of it is scripted. Enemies flipping over a table to take cover seems cool until you notice how they stand behind it for no particular reason until you enter the room. However, just because something's a gimmick doesn't mean it can't be appreciated. Even though movies are obviously fake, it's not something you hear complaints about, because the only important element is that the fictional setting stays internally consistent. In essence, playing F.E.A.R. feels like watching an old horror movie where you can tell how all the effects were done. It can be immersion breaking, but getting hung up on those details just isn't worth the time. The real question is if the shooting mechanics are still just as satisfying as intended and if the horror elements are still interesting enough to draw your interest, and both goals are met. It's not going to be impressing anybody the way it used to, but you can still have a lot of fun with it, and that's more than a lot of games in general can say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="doom2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Doom II: Hell on Earth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This game plays like a joke. That’s not to say it’s bad, it’s just that Doom 2 seems like it was a release of tension after the relatively straight-faced original. There are tons of ambushes, traps, gimmick levels, and funny situations that are scattered about the campaign, instead of the carefully considered structure and pacing that you may have gotten used to. In Doom, each episode required you to start with just a pistol, so the levels could slowly introduce ideas and escalate situations, resetting the stakes when the next episode started up. With one long campaign in Doom 2, it’s just a grab bag of random gimmicks until you reach the final boss. All the new monsters and funny level designs make it more fun than Doom, but not necessarily better overall. The highs are high, but the lows of getting repeatedly killed in unpredictable ambushes are incredibly low. It’s still an easy recommendation, just expect to roll your eyes a few times before the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="deathstranding"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Death Stranding&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Death Stranding’s gameplay of carrying packages from point A to point B is alright. It gets the job done. Obviously, it’s supposed to be a vehicle for the main theme of the game, expressed on the back of the box as reuniting a shattered world. You’re carrying packages across a series of isolated cities, uniting them under one banner and connected to a single network. I won’t give any plot spoilers here, but given that the game is narrative-focused, I need to comment on whether I think it was able to convey the theme of unity well enough to justify a purchase. As such, I’ll say that this game has absolutely no teeth when it comes to conveying a message. This game wants to be a political commentary on the increasing level of division in America, directly stating that before the game’s titular disaster, Americans wanted to put up walls between groups of people and hated those outside their nation. This mentality became dominant after the Death Stranding event, and this is what you’re working to rectify. However, this ideological conflict isn’t actually presented in-game. When arriving at most cities, the people talk about how much they would love to be connected to the network and how they’re so excited to be part of a greater community. Once you hook them up, they say that you’re a fantastic guy and give you gifts for doing them the favor. The few times you have to prove yourself aren’t even about proving the strength of a unified society, but in picking up an extra shipment for them to show how reliable your delivery service is. There’s no push back, there’s no discussion, it’s not going to convince anyone or open someone’s heart because the height of the game’s thematic conveyance is self congratulation for having the correct opinions. I thought the plot itself could pick up the slack, but its message is almost entirely unrelated to the rest of the game's themes. It’s a decent enough central plot, but it has the same issue as the rest of the narrative in that it has no punch, and the motivations for the antagonists go essentially undefined. Whether it's in gameplay, plot, or dialog, you’re always going to have a sense that there should be something more to tie it all together. Everything is in a state where it’s enjoyable, it’s fine, but there isn’t a moment that will stick in your memory or any ideas that will give you a lot to chew on. If that level of thoughtfulness was the goal of the game, it didn’t succeed, but if the goal was to make a new style of game to get people talking, I have to begrudgingly admit its success. This is normally where people would say the game’s so unique that it deserves some leeway, but if you want a game that’s all about meditatively going from place to place as you consider the themes of the game, play Rain World instead. I feel like that game accomplished everything this game wanted to in a much, much more elegant fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="wolf2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wolfenstein II: The New Colossus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
No one expected Wolfenstein: The New Order to be good, and this game proves that the developers felt the same way. The New Colossus copies TNO almost beat-for-beat, as if they were unsure what exactly they got right or what was safe to change. However, the safe sequel has dangers of its own, and this game managed to run into all the usual pitfalls. Not only is the plot almost the same, the emotional beats meant to grab your interest are nearly identical, so the story is a write-off. The gameplay is just as good as the original, but since it doesn’t exceed it in any capacity, it’s easy to see how The New Colossus is generally accepted as a downgrade. That doesn’t mean the gameplay isn’t fun, and I enjoyed it a lot, but if you’re looking for anything other than satisfying gunplay then you’re in the wrong place. It puts me in a tough spot when it comes to a recommendation, because I got my money’s worth from it and had a blast, but spending any time thinking about its other parts leaves me confused and frustrated. I suppose that boils down to telling shooter fans to pick it up when it’s cheap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="shadowofthetombraider"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shadow of the Tomb Raider&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I played the original Tomb Raider this year and was blown away by its focus on smart movement, and even though that hasn’t been a focus in the reboot games, I still enjoyed Tomb Raider 2013 for its cinematic style. It did a good job of reestablishing Lara’s character, providing a nice self-contained story for how she became the capable badass she was in the original games. The problem is that it doesn’t feel like Rise of the Tomb Raider and Shadow of the Tomb Raider were ever included in the planning process. They’re both stuck in a holding pattern with no set arc or end goal, just being stories about Lara going after one more treasure and becoming slightly more capable than she was at the start. Shadow of the Tomb Raider in particular puts a fine point on this lack of direction, given that the original version of the game had an ending cutscene that directly set up the events of the original Tomb Raider. This was edited with the game’s first patch, opening up the potential for more reboot series games. I wish these games were a full reboot rather than the quasi-rebooted-prequel status they’re stuck in now, so the developers could have enough room to tell some daring stories or do something new with the character. They got trapped by leaning so heavily on its status as an origin story in the advertising, so chances are good that we’re going to be indefinitely stuck in low-stakes prequel games until one flops. This may have already happened thanks to Shadow’s low sales, so I’m starting to despair for how this franchise was born and mismanaged to death twice over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="chulip"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chulip&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With games like the original Super Mario Bros. and Doom I’ve kept reviews short; you already know about them and should just play them already. For Chulip, I’m going to do it for the opposite reason. Chances are, you have no idea what this game is about. You probably don’t even know what system it’s for. And that’s why you should find a rom of it (it’s for the PS2, by the way) and play it. Go in completely blind and enjoy. I’ll add the parenthetical that figuring out how to beat the game is quite difficult, so it’s ok to quit the game once you get stuck and it’s not interesting anymore, but until that point I think you’ll have a pretty memorable experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="ratchetandclank"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ratchet &amp;amp; Clank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I completely missed the boat when it came to mascot platformers in the early 2000’s. I only owned a Gamecube and I never bought Mario Sunshine, instead spending all my time in 007 Nightfire and Custom Robo. So, I had no Crash, no Banjo, no Spyro, no Mario, no Jak, no Ratchet. My assumption going into Ratchet &amp;amp; Clank was that it gets recommended due to its nostalgia factor, given that it seemed like a fairly standard 3D platformer with an outdated sense of violent edginess. This just proves how idiotic assumptions and first impressions can be, because this game rips. Even with zero nostalgia for the series and genre as a whole, Ratchet &amp;amp; Clank is incredibly charming. The writing is witty and concise, the worn-out mechanical aesthetic feels original even 17 years later, the soundtrack is now one of my favorites, and the weapon selection is surprisingly interesting. It starts out pretty simply, but the difficulty hits a sweet spot halfway through where you start needing to have all your tools at the ready if you don’t want to get beat up ten times in a row. The last boss in particular was a perfect crescendo of difficulty and narrative stakes that I wasn’t expecting a mascot platformer could pull off. Don’t miss out on it, I’m definitely going to slowly work my way through the sequels until I get tired of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="jakanddaxter"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jak and Daxter: The Precursor Legacy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I followed up one mascot platformer with another, and this one was also a big surprise to me. I knew this game was developed by Naughty Dog, a team who has become famous for their story-focused games, so I was expecting this to be the narrative practice that turned the Crash Bandicoot team into the people who would make The Last of Us. As it turns out, the grim atmosphere and violence I was picturing when I thought of Jak and Daxter started with the second game, and this one is exclusively a lighthearted fantasy platformer. It shocked me just how simple this game is, following the most basic template of 3D platforming. Your goal is to collect power cells, which are scattered around the world or earned by completing simple objectives. You need to get a certain amount before progressing to the next set of levels, where you’re presented with a new number to get, and your search starts over again. If this sounds like Mario 64, it’s because that’s what it is in all ways except the name. You don’t collect power stars, you collect power cells. You don’t collect 100 coins for a star, you collect 90 orbs for a cell. You don’t collect 8 red coins, you collect 7 scout flies. You don’t need 70 power macguffins to beat the game, you need 72. The quest hubs are also the default set (grassland/desert/ocean/jungle/ice/fire/boss) with only a couple exceptions. This all sounds pretty dismissive, so I want to emphasize that Jak and Daxter isn’t a bad 3D platformer, it’s simply an unambitious one. If you played this game without the context of Naughty Dog’s legacy and how the series went on to greater ambitions, you would probably dismiss it as a run of the mill attempt to capitalize on the genre’s popularity. Having no load times between zones may have been enough to differentiate it back in 2001, but there isn’t enough to make it stand out today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="mm11"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mega Man 11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Making a game that’s simultaneously difficult and accessible is a difficult task. There should be a safety net for struggling players, but it should be unappealing enough to where it doesn’t become the dominant strategy. A good example of this is in Ratchet &amp;amp; Clank with its RYNO superweapon. It costs a whopping 150,000 bolts, compared to your standard weapons which require about 10,000. It takes so long to farm up the cash that players will fill out their standard arsenal and give it their best try before resorting to such tactics. Mega Man 11 on the other hand makes circumventing the difficulty incredibly easy. You can buy an E-Tank which completely refills your health for 80 bolts, dropped by enemies in increments of 100. You can also buy lives, weapon recharge tanks, rescues for when you fall into a death pit, a helper character who brings you whatever item you need, or a powerup that reduces the damage you take by half, along with various upgrades like reducing how much you slip on icy floors. The hardest part of the game will be your first stage, before you get enough bolts to stock your supplies. After that, it’s entirely possible to brute force your way through the game and miss out on its finer qualities. The stage design in this game is fantastic, and the amount of unique challenges and screen gimmicks really blew me away, but there isn’t much point in patiently mastering them when you can essentially give yourself infinite health. What’s a shame is that this problem was already solved in the games before Mega Man 7, where getting lives and E-Tanks required repeating a stage. Just like getting a RYNO, it was viable, but a pain in the ass. If you wanted to regulate difficulty by playing in this classic way, you’re not even allowed to, given that these special pickups are now limited to one per save file. You’re stuck in a position where you want to use some E-Tanks because they were always a part of Mega Man games, but you don’t want to use a lot of them because it cheats the difficulty. I couldn’t even presume to suggest how exactly you should limit yourself, given how everyone’s experience with platformers is different. I guess the only thing I can say is that along with my recommendation to play this game, I give a recommendation to challenge yourself a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="slycooper"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sly Cooper and the Thievius Raccoonus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This series is described as "stealth platforming", and I definitely should have considered that term more carefully before starting the game. I imagined Sly Cooper as a lighthearted take on the stealth genre, when it's more of a stealth-themed take on the platforming genre. The first level only reinforced my misunderstanding, introducing the basics of movement while breaking into a police hq to steal some documents. When the game subsequently began the standard 3D platformer cycle of hub worlds, missions, and bosses, it became disappointing how the majority of the stealth flavor was used up in the first thirty minutes. The platforming is solid and there's a good variety of challenges, but it's hard to avoid reflecting on your disappointment as you do the usual coin and trinket collection. While this all sounds pretty bleak, Sly Cooper is actually a good platformer, it's just a shame how its very first level gave me a mental picture of a game I would have adored rather than liked.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="recommendations"></category></entry><entry><title>Uni's 2018 Wrapup</title><link href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-22T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-11-22T18:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Uni</name></author><id>tag:birb.uk,2018-11-22:/uni-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Uni spent a few hours writing over 50 paragraphs of short game reviews of the things he played in 2018 so you better read it&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="a-look-back-at-about-6-games-from-2018-and-47-that-werent"&gt;A Look Back At About 6 Games From 2018 And 47 That Weren't&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holy balls I played a lot of games in 2018. This list includes all the games I played until the credits. The table of contents is alphabetized so you can find the games you're interested in quickly, but the paragraphs are ordered by when I played them, so you can see my memory resolution increase over the course of the document. I'm not including games that were replays like F-Zero GX and REmake, and three I quit (Sonic Mania, Killer 7, Hitman 2) are solid enough to where I don't feel the need to rail on them or anything. Enjoy~&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#alphaprotocol"&gt;Alpha Protocol&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#ac4"&gt;Assassin's Creed IV: Black Flag&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#notvania"&gt;Bloodstained: Curse of the Moon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#rondo"&gt;Castlevania: Rondo of Blood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#sotn"&gt;Castlevania: Symphony of the Night&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#celeste"&gt;Celeste&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#dangan2"&gt;Danganronpa 2: Goodbye Despair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#deadspace"&gt;Dead Space&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#deusex"&gt;Deus Ex: Mankind Divided&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#dmc"&gt;Devil May Cry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#dmc3"&gt;Devil May Cry 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#dmc4"&gt;Devil May Cry 4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#factorio"&gt;Factorio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#ff"&gt;Final Fantasy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#fotns"&gt;Fist of the North Star: Lost Paradise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#devtycoon"&gt;Game Dev Tycoon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#ghosttrick"&gt;Ghost Trick: Phantom Detective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#gow"&gt;God of War&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#gravityrush"&gt;Gravity Rush: Remastered&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#guac"&gt;Guacamelee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#hollowknight"&gt;Hollow Knight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#katamari"&gt;Katamari Damacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#lisbts"&gt;Life is Strange: Before the Storm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#luigi"&gt;Luigi's Mansion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#metro"&gt;Metro 2033 Redux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#metroidprime"&gt;Metroid Prime&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#oxenfree"&gt;Oxenfree&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#papersplease"&gt;Papers, Please&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#pikmin"&gt;Pikmin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#re2"&gt;Resident Evil 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#re3"&gt;Resident Evil 3: Nemesis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#re4"&gt;Resident Evil 4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#obradinn"&gt;Return of the Obra Dinn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#ruiner"&gt;Ruiner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#sh"&gt;Silent Hill&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#sh2"&gt;Silent Hill 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#sh3"&gt;Silent Hill 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#snakepass"&gt;Snake Pass&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#sc5"&gt;Space Channel 5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#sc5p2"&gt;Space Channel 5: Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#spiderman"&gt;Spider-Man&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#subnautica"&gt;Subnautica&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#mario3"&gt;Super Mario Bros. 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#tew"&gt;The Evil Within&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#tew2"&gt;The Evil Within 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#thief"&gt;Thief&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#touhou15"&gt;Touhou 15: Legacy of Lunatic Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#uncharted2"&gt;Uncharted 2: Among Thieves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#uncharted3"&gt;Uncharted 3: Drake's Deception&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#uncharted4"&gt;Uncharted 4: A Thief's End&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#valkyria"&gt;Valkyria Chronicles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#devil"&gt;We Know The Devil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#westerado"&gt;Westerado: Double Barreled&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://birb.uk/uni-2018.html#kiwami2"&gt;Yakuza Kiwami 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p id="factorio"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Factorio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you were to ask the average gamer about Factorio, they would probably say "What the hell are you talking about", but if you were to ask someone who HAD heard about the game, they would probably tell you that it's very addicting. With endless potential for improving your factory and a low-pressure environment to do it in, it's easy to get invested and keep incrementally optimizing for hours. However, if you're not the kind of person that typically likes those games, Factorio is difficult to recommend. It's the gold standard of its niche, but it doesn't spend much energy giving guidance or setting goals to entice the newcomers. Luckily, it has a low price point of $20, so it's worth a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="lisbts"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Life is Strange: Before the Storm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The first Life is Strange lived and died on empathy. The writing was good enough to strike a chord with people who could directly relate to the struggles on screen, but not good enough to make everyone else care. Personally, it was a memorable experience, but even I think making a prequel was a mistake. The events portrayed in Before the Storm were presented as a mystery in the first game, and were slowly revealed as you grew closer to other characters. To go back and remove all the mystery, and do so in three quick episodes instead of a full five, made it an unsatisfying narrative in multiple ways. Unless you're the biggest fan ever of Life is Strange, I wouldn't bother with this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="deadspace"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dead Space&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I think everything that needs to be said about it has been said already. It's atmospheric, polished, fun, and you should check it out if you haven't already. You may notice that "scary" was missing from that list, so you could think I'm damning it with fine praise, but Dead Space shoots more for tension than scariness. I think that might be part of its widespread appeal; even people who don't typically like horror games can enjoy it after getting in the groove.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="westerado"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Westerado: Double Barreled&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I think it was Jon Blow who said that a game has to be either fun or interesting, but not necessarily both. Westerado is both, and yet I wouldn't call it a well designed game. The concept is that you're searching for an outlaw who burned down your family's farm and you have to gather clues about who it was, because he's just one of one-hundred randomly generated townsfolk. By doing side missions and favors for people, you learn hints like "he's wearing a tall hat" or "he's wearing a blue suit" and you can accuse anyone, at any time, of being the villain. The problem is, while the villain is random, the sidequests and map aren't. The game only provides enough content for one satisfying serious playthrough, and after that you'll either be repeating lots of sidequests or trashing the script and accusing everyone of being the killer or going on a bank-robbing rampage. That said, the amount of polish that went into letting you fly off the rails is admirable, and that first playthrough is still a good experience, but it doesn't live up to its own endless-Western-generator concept. It's a nice snacky pickup next time a sale's on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="snakepass"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snake Pass&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A platformer without jumping sounds like a concept with Zooey Deschanel levels of disingenuous quirkiness, but Snake Pass actually pulls it off. Skillfully navigating an environment with the limited skillset of a snake provides for compelling gameplay, and you'll find yourself strangling your controller as you try to maintain your grip on each ledge. That's about the only string to the game's bow though, for better and worse. It's a nicely focused game, but if it starts frustrating you, there aren't any other redeeming qualities. Worth a look if the uniqueness of it all catches your eye, but you're also not missing much if it doesn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="ruiner"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ruiner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There isn't much to say about this game. It's a top down, cyberpunky action game that's... ok? The style's alright, the gameplay is standard, it's pretty short with a three hour run-time, not much to really hate here, but I also don't see much reason to pick it up compared to anything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="deusex"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deus Ex: Mankind Divided&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This game is beautiful.&lt;br /&gt;
That's about the extent of it, sadly. Prague as a focused city hub has gotten a lot of praise, but with it broken up by so many loading screens and filled with so few interesting things to do, I was content to just blow through the main story, which was about as standard as a Deus Ex plot can be. The augmentations and abilities were also standard stuff, so the game overall feels bland. It's the bare template of the Deus Ex immersive sim subgenre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="uncharted2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncharted 2: Among Thieves&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Going back to play the Uncharted series was like cutting down the tree of cinematic gaming and looking at its growth rings. Compared to how thin the first game was, Uncharted 2 was a great evolution, but it's still pretty close to the center. If I go any further with this explanation the only center we'll reach is the trauma center for tortured metaphors, so to be direct, this game was probably pretty cool at the time but doesn't hold up. It leans too much on long gunfights, with one at the end throwing you more than 75 dudes in a row, and cover-based shooting isn't as fresh as it used to be. Luckily, the story's pretty alright and the characters are good, but the gameplay issues keep it from being a timeless classic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="uncharted3"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncharted 3: Drake's Deception&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I said I would stop the tree metaphor, but it's actually perfect for describing this game. It's another ring in the tree, expanding past the old one, but the growth is much thinner this time. We're still shooting, we're still climbing, the story's alright, the set pieces are a little better, and the gunfights are a bit less tedious. It's exactly what you would expect with no surprises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="hollowknight"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hollow Knight&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This might be the hardest game ever for me to critique. It's good, it's original, Metroid fans adore it, and it's packed with content for the price, but I didn't have much fun with it. I found exploration to be a chore with a bizarre and unhelpful map system, in a world full of enemies too simple to be interesting and too uninteresting to be fun. The atmosphere and a couple breathtaking moments were enough to keep me playing until the end, which is more than I can say for most games in the genre at least. I guess it must be pretty good for someone who doesn't care for these games to think it was basically ok, but that doesn't mean I can personally say anything other than "it was basically ok".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="tew"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Evil Within&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Last year I wrote a little article about how Nioh should be appreciated outside of the expectations associated with its marketing, and that's exactly how I feel about The Evil Within. It was sold as the next game from Resident Evil 4's creator Shinji Mikami, so people were disappointed when it didn't stick to the Resident Evil 4 template. The same over-the-top sensiblities are here, but the action has been refined to smoothly unify a wide variety of setpieces. The breakneck pace of these moments creates an explosive love letter to the horror genre, starting in a mental hospital, evolving into a nightmarish butcher shop, which dumps you into a spooky town in the woods, all within the course of an hour. It rests in this sweet spot between an action game and a survival horror game, asking for you to be crafty with its mechanics to improvise in each scenario, as you're graded on your ability to keep your supplies high. It took me a while to understand just what the game wanted out of me, and my survival-horror mindset made my playthrough a bit of a slog at first, but once you understand what the game's really going for, it's a very special sort of experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="uncharted4"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncharted 4: A Thief's End&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Another ring on the tree. It has better tech than Uncharted 3, making it a visually stunning game, but it's mostly the same. I think it wrapped up the series pretty well though and it has the best story of all of them, so I guess I'm cool with it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="guac"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guacamelee&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This game insulted my intelligence. When the combat tutorial included air juggles, I was excited for where the game was going, but it was all downhill from there. You can juggle, but the game doesn't trust you to do so and you have no incentive to use it. You get new abilities, but the game doesn't trust you to think, so every obstacle is a just a giant colored square. I guess that's also why it's so linear when it claims to be about exploration. Just don't bother with it, try Hollow Knight. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="gow"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;God of War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
"Shameless" is how I would describe this game. It's such a blatant attempt at converting a popular series from the last console generation into something trendy that I can't even endorse the few good parts. The action mechanics were crippled to make room for a pretty mediocre story which is somehow so self-satisfied that it gives you multiple teasers for the obligatory second installment. And I don't mean they left a plot thread unresolved, I mean there's a dream scene when you finish the game that shows you how the next game is going to start. It almost loops back around to where it's self apologetic instead of self satisfied, saying "sorry you didn't fight the god we talked about for the whole game, but we promise he's in the design document". I can't endorse this kind of stupidity on any level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="dmc3"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Devil May Cry 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The definitive action game. I'm not usually a fan of action games, but this one feels great, partly due to the style system and partly due to the super memorable boss lineup. Every action game should really have something like the gunslinger style, where you can stop and shoot in two directions to keep your current target locked down along with disrupting one who's sneaking up on you. It lets you maintain a smokin' sick stylish flow where you benefit from your situational awareness in a way other than dodging. I can also go through the bosses by heart, and while remembering a few bosses isn't a very big accomplishment, I finished like 50 games this year, and I played this one towards the beginning, so I think remembering all of them and their dialog speaks well of how much personality this game has. I think if other action games were like this, I would be much more willing to get into them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="re2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resident Evil 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Everyone knows I love the 2002 Gamecube Resident Evil Remaster, but I never had much interest in the PlayStation games. I love REmake for its incredible polish, something the PlayStation games famously lacked without the advantage of hindsight. That said, I was pleasantly surprised at how good RE2 was. It's a huge step forward from the original, with more of pretty much everything. More monster types, more zombies, more replay value, more cool characters, and more borderline nonsensical story. That said, it's naturally going to feel a bit dated, but I heard a rumor that we might see a remade version of it soon, we'll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="sotn"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Castlevania: Symphony of the Night&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I've been pretty hard on this game in the past, being a massive fan of the classic-style linear Castlevania games. I could still throw out the same complaints of being slightly aimless and extremely unchallenging, but the amount of polish and charm SotN has is absolutely insane. The visuals, unique weapon effects, optional content, and general attention to detail make for a game that's oozing with love. The biggest shame about it is that while it contributed the second half of the word "Metroidvania", not many games other than its direct followups seem to follow in its footsteps rather than Metroid's. I would like to see some games break out of the Metroid formula  and try for Symphony of the Night's level of environmental interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="dmc"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Devil May Cry&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I liked Devil May Cry 3, but I can only say I appreciate Devil May Cry. It's a landmark game, but it had to put so much effort into breaking new ground that it didn't get to dig very deep. Even so, it's not the worst 3d action game I've ever played, and that's pretty incredible considering it essentially created the genre. If you're an action game fan and haven't tried it, you should probably play it to show some respect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="alphaprotocol"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alpha Protocol&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This game is bad. It's ugly, the plot is dry, the protagonist is an absolute bellend no matter how you play him, the shooting feels awful, the interface is ugly, and I love it anyway. I was even planning on refunding it when I first played, but I had nothing better to do and people said your choices really start to matter later on, so I kept with it. And wow, they were actually right. It's one of the few RPG's where your treatment of other characters, your skills, and your performance in-game actually affect how the story will play out. I took advantage of this to be the biggest dick I possibly could, and it ended up being one of the most hilarious gaming experiences of my life. Characters will legitimately get tired of your shit, which is something more RPG's need to do, because it makes your failures hysterical while giving your successes a shine of smug superiority. If you have enough patience to wade through some bad gameplay, absolutely pick this game up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="sh2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Silent Hill 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I tend to shy away from criticizing the specifics of game narratives, because I'm not that kind of a writer. That said, I was always somewhat disappointed with how games don't usually blend gameplay and narrative very gracefully. It's possible to represent the themes of a story in gameplay, and conversely possible to use the style of gameplay to inform players of the character they're controlling. The perspective of the narrative could change based on the player's playstyle, in addition to the more direct method of choice and consequence. Silent Hill 2 did all that in 2001 and I didn't even know it, and it's made me retroactively disappointed in pretty much every game touted as a storytelling masterpiece that I've ever played. The story presentation is nothing short of masterful, and the atmosphere is up there with the best I've ever seen. The simple gameplay and wandering might be enough to hurt people's enjoyment, so I won't lavish it with the best-game-ever title that it often receives, but it's damn good and in the running for my top 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="sh"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Silent Hill&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Wait, why did you play Silent Hill 2 first? Well, it's because I heard Silent Hill doesn't really hold up, 2 is better, and the stories aren't connected anyway. The real question you should be asking is why do people think Silent Hill doesn't hold up. I can understand distaste for 3d graphics as lifelike as origami, but this game accomplished a lot with its limited resources. Its atmosphere still works amazingly well, and the level design is even better than Silent Hill 2's. It's different from its successor, but not necessarily a lesser game. When you play it, you might start by thinking it looks a little rough, but by the end you'll wish more games had such an engrossing world to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="ac4"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assassin's Creed 4: Black Flag&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It's easy to forget that one of the biggest gaming franchises started out with an innovative title that actually worked to distance itself from its parent series, Prince of Persia. The obvious reason for that is because so many iterative Assassin's Creed games have come out since then, but the subtle reason might be because the game in the series most celebrated for its innovation is an absolute disaster. I played Black Flag because it had been called "the GOOD Assassin's Creed game" for years, only to find it's entirely half-baked. The missions on land are uniformly terrible with their clunky stalking sequences, the ship combat is only visually interesting, the mobile game style ship management is mind-numbing, and I found the story to be hilarious in how much it missed the mark. Imagine you're at a design meeting and asked to make a story about pirates. Chances are, you'll write the words "fighting over treasure" in the middle of a sheet of blank printer paper, hand it in, then go for drinks. For some reason, Black Flag opted for a slow story about politics in the piratical community, with the Assassin's Creed signature of standing next to historical figures as they do the thing they're famous for, as they give a wink to the camera and say you're a cool dude. Honestly I could go on for ages about all the things I don't like about this game but this has already gotten too long so whatever just don't play this absolute tripe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="dangan2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Danganronpa 2: Goodbye Despair&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The first Danganronpa game was a big surprise to an anime skeptic like myself. Even though it was a visual novel steeped in anime tropes, it created an air of mystery with its unique premise and setting that got me hooked. It's kind of a shame that the sequel doesn't try to replicate that mystery. To give my best spoiler-free example, in the first game, when everyone's locked in a school and told to murder each other, they quickly appreciate the locks on their doors. The inability for students to get into each other's rooms was relevant to how the plot progressed, and something you had to remember as you conducted your investigation. In Goodbye Despair, someone accidentally breaks the lock on your room early on, and... it's just never brought up again. If anything, it's played for laughs. There's still some good investigating and debating to do here, but the mood that pulled the first one together is gone. The ending as also laughably bad, so even if you liked the first game, this might not be worth it. Maybe if you're really in the mood extremely specifically for more Danganronpa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="rondo"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Castlevania: Rondo of Blood&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It's more classic Castlevania, what can I say, I like it and you know how it plays. That said, I'm also a fan of Dracula X, which is considered a botched port of Rondo, and I wouldn't be as dismissive of it now that I've played both. Rondo has all the cool cutscenes, voiceover, extra bosses, and effects Dracula X doesn't, but the difficulty curve is comparatively ludicrous. At one point, you fight the bosses from Castlevania 1 back to back to back, then fight a new one you haven't seen before, who sends out an attack as you land your final blow just to make sure you didn't get by with one health remaining. This game just loves laughing in your face like that. It might be the coolest classic-vania, but definitely not the most fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="subnautica"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subnautica&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I tend to stay away from these kinds of games, in every way you can interpret "these", namely early access, survival, and crafting. That said, I had a pretty good time with it. Evolving from your escape pod, to a tiny base, to a bigger base, to a multiple vehicle bay station felt great, with the non-randomized world providing a subtly guided experience. The story was intriguing, and I wasn't expecting a story at all, much less a good one. I would be able to easily recommend this game if it wasn't the most poorly optimized game I've ever played on my PC. Even after setting everything to low, I had to reduce the resolution from 1080p so it didn't give my graphics card hypertension. Then, there were a few bugs, which weren't enough to break the game but enough to be distracting. If you have a super PC, it's winter, you're ok with things running a bit warm, AND are interested in the game itself, then you're good to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="gravityrush"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gravity Rush: Remastered&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As an active member of the Gravity Rush fan community, I cannot ethically say I'm giving an impartial review. Luckily, I never claimed any of these reviews are impartial, and these games are the cat's pajamas. I love the picaresque narrative with the world's most plucky and lovable protagonist, I love using gravity shifting to stumble around like I'm a drunk who wandered onto the set of Doctor Strange, and I love the musical and architectural details that flesh out the world of Hekseville. Is the combat good? Nope. Do I care? Nope. Please play these games, they make me happy and need more love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="ff"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Fantasy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Playing this was meant as a history lesson, and that's about all I can recommend it as. It's cool to see where JRPG's as we understand them today began(yes I know about Dragon Quest, but it's different ok whatever), but the genre has moved on a long way since then. The balance is questionable and it's pretty grindy, so it was fun to see that's where modern JRPG's get it from, but the quality of life features and stability of modern titles improve the experience immensely. Maybe check it out, but don't feel bad if you stop halfway through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="papersplease"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Papers, Please&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This game sits comfortably on the pantheon on indie darlings for a good reason. When most games interpret "interactive storytelling" as "we need to ensure players don't rip out the pages of our story", Papers Please embraces and tells its story through interaction. Putting that on top of a well stylized presentation and wholly unique premise, it's a game I think everyone should check out as an testament to the breadth of gaming's potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="celeste"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Celeste&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Speaking of indie darlings, Celeste is one of the top runners for top indie of the year. We must not have had many good indies in 2018 I guess. It's like you turned on the indie game machine, set the twee dial to 7, the quality dial to 6, clicked the child-in-an-uncaring-world button, and kept the lever on the pixel-platformer setting because it's been stuck there for a few years and no one wants to risk getting electrocuted. I can't complain about it much, because it's functional and looks pretty good, but... it's an indie platformer about overcoming challenge with a lot of spikes. Cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="devil"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We Know the Devil&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you want to spend a few bucks to have a very gay hour and a half, this is the visual novel for you. I enjoyed it, because that's pretty much what I wanted, but I have to admit that it feels rushed. That hour and a half number is how long it took to go through it twice for two of three endings, and it's hard enough to cover three characters worth of development in a two hour long film. Luckily, the same people recently made another game (Heaven Will Be Mine) that's apparently a lot more fleshed out, and I'm looking forward to playing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="devtycoon"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Game Dev Tycoon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It's what it says on the box, a game development tycoon game. It does its job about as well as you could expect, with how vague the factors contributing to a game's success are compared to something like a theme park. Trying goofy game concepts is fun, and when you make your personal dream game into a big hit, it's extremely gratifying. That said, you're pretty much doing the same thing over and over when you make games, instead of expanding and evolving like you would with a park or a building. I still give it a recommendation, because it's a neat little distraction for the price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="oxenfree"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oxenfree&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I have mixed feelings about this game. It's all about the narrative, and while it succeeds in telling a good story, but it rests on top of mediocre character drama. You're meant to feel like you naturally fit in with your Scooby gang, when you can interject dialog and steer conversations naturally to react to the situation or bond with people. Or maybe you're not meant to feel that way because certain people aren't likable, or maybe you're supposed to follow the personality of the strongly characterised protagonist? I honestly don't know, especially when the endings seem to judge you for not role playing correctly, but even the best ending is pretty bleak. The plot and characters just don't quite gel, so even if it has some great writing, I feel unsatisfied by it. Luckily, it's pretty short and pretty cheap, so it barely walks away with a positive assessment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="touhou15"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Touhou 15: Legacy of Lunatic Kingdom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Well, another Touhou game, exactly what you would expect. Difficult, bright, anime girls and flashing light. The new point device mode is a pretty interesting idea, but it may have made the game a little too hard. Pierrot of the Star Spangled Banner is a great track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="metroidprime"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metroid Prime&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Converting 2d to 3d is hard, Metroid Prime succeeded, everyone likes it, it's gotten all the praise it needs. I found the backtracking and wandering pretty tedious at times, especially when you have to do an end-game collectathon and revisit each area, but I have to admit that it's still pretty good overall. I'm not in love with it, but its status as a classic is deserved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="sc5"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Space Channel 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This game sits next to Gravity Rush on the bench of mediocre games I absolutely adore. The 60's retro-future aesthetic is a perfect fit for a rhythm game, with excessive grooviness blasting from every detail. It's kinda weird to compare this game to Symphony of the Night or The Evil Within, but the thread that draws me in to each of these games is the soul and passion you can feel when you play. Just be aware that it can get pretty difficult, but even with some trouble it won't take you more than three hours. Might as well give it a try, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="pikmin"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pikmin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What a weird little game. It doesn't even feel like this should be a Nintendo game, with the bizarre mix of cartoony visuals and terrifying implications having a Sega-like feel. The learning process is uncharacteristically hands-off, letting you make mistakes and be unable to finish without starting over. That's what I like about this game though, it treats you like a smart guy who can figure stuff out, take risks, and plan on his own. Nintendo's characteristic polish without Nintendo's characteristic patronizing design philosophy can be a beautiful thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="thief"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thief&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Yes, the good one, not the new one. I was actually surprised at just how good this one actually is, when it came from that awkward time in PC gaming where the standard controls for an FPS were still up in the air and mouse-look was a relatively new concept. The level design is fantastic, and stealth games today could learn a lot by going back and looking at the approach options on display here. Its age might show in the graphics and the awkward balance of audio and visual stealth mechanics, but it's still a blast to play even all these years later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="kiwami2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yakuza Kiwami 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Yakuza rocks. Ever since Yakuza 0 came out in the west, it's been enjoying a little renaissance where people have had a second chance to jump into such an iconic series. Kiwami 2 maintains the legacy of quality, and provides another solid Yakuza experience. That experience is admittedly pretty formulaic by now, but the new engine makes the game beautiful, and enhancing the combat with ragdoll physics is exactly what Yakuza deserves. If you already liked Yakuza, you'll like this, if you haven't played any, go play 0, if you don't like Yakuza, what the FUCK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="spiderman"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spider-Man&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I looked forward to this game for quite a while, so it's a little awkward I don't have much to say about it. It's good in the ways I wanted it to be good, it's bad in the ways I knew it would be bad. Fun swinging, great rendition of New York, adequate story, repetitive side stuff and comic-book level dialog. I enjoyed it, but nothing worth evangelizing or complaining about. Again, it's exactly what it says it is on the box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="dmc4"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Devil May Cry 4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I don't even consider myself a Devil May Cry fan and this game was kinda disappointing. There's good action for you to appreciate, but there's a lot less charm than Devil May Cry 3, and a lot less innovation compared to Devil May Cry. Having to repeat the game in reverse at the middle is a particularly sad way to wrap up the game, even if you get to play as a style-switching Dante again. It feels very unfinished, and it left fans feeling the series in general was unfinished until the DMC5 announcement finally came. I don't want to make this game sound terrible or anything, because it isn't, but I will also say I'm glad the mainline series didn't end like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="metro"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metro 2033 Redux&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I don't know what this game wants to be. Its best strength is its potential for immersion, and I played in ranger mode to get that experience, but there was too much time working past bugs and poorly implemented AI companions to feel invested. There are one or two chapters that play to those strengths, and then the game stops trying and becomes an action movie. The quality keeps tanking with each terrible action set piece, and one particularly heinous stealth section broke my game multiple times. Don't put yourself through it, no matter how good people say it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="valkyria"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Valkyria Chronicles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ok, I have to admit something to y'all, I've only been putting games in this list if I've finished them, and that's technically true here, but after I made it 15% of the way in I skipped every single cutscene. With 3 or 4 per mission, and judging by the length of Youtube compilations, I skipped about 7 and a half hours of stuff. This checks out with the HowLongToBeat time of 31.5 hours, and I have 23 hours played. So I enjoyed the tactics aspect, and I would recommend it for the cool spin on the genre, but good lord do you have to be patient to enjoy this. Patient for cutscenes, patient with the controls, patient with the technical issues, patient with the interface, it's a bit of a mess. Enjoyable, but messy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="katamari"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Katamari Damacy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Check it up, funk it up, minna damatte ore ni tsuite koi, yeah&lt;br /&gt;
Check it up, funk it up, minna hisshi de ore ni tsuite koi, come on&lt;br /&gt;
For real though this game is just... inspired. It's super fun and the soundtrack's great. If you haven't played this game yet, go do that. Anyone can appreciate it, genuinely. It's satisfying on such a basic level I think everyone can dig this game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="re3"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resident Evil 3: Nemesis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is the gaming equivalent of puberty. You look at Resident Evil 2, you look at Resident Evil 4, and you're like wow, Resident Evil 3 must have been awkward. And it was. This attempt at combining action and horror didn't end up feeling polished, like having a dodge function which isn't bound to a button of its own, but activates when you try to shoot an enemy. Riposting zombies like you're in Bloodborne sounds neat, but because the ability is also tied to your attack, its usage as an alternative to attacking is a confusing thing to wrap your head around. Nemesis chasing you around also sounds pretty neat, but he's easy to shake and not very scary after the second encounter. The splitting narrative paths were fun, but the binary selection is a far cry from how much RE2 accomplished with its multiple playthrough system. The strides it took are admirable, but it remains an awkward transition game instead of a great game in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="sh3"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Silent Hill 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The debate about Silent Hill 3 is the eternal flame of the fandom. A lot of people love it, a lot of people think it's mediocre, and it's a stalemate that's hard to break even on a personal level. It's great in a lot of ways, and if you analyzed it in a vacuum, there wouldn't be much doubt regarding its quality. The problem I have with it is that Silent Hill 1 and 2 both introduced a brand new type of horror to gaming which I can still appreciate today for how fully realized they are. Silent Hill 3 doesn't carry the torch of innovation, instead just using the existing parts to make more. More can be fine, but just making more of the same doesn't feel like the Silent Hill ethos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="luigi"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luigi's Mansion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I have a lot of respect for this game, in how a horror-themed Mario spinoff was what Nintendo made to sell the Gamecube. When you play it though, you can kinda see why it was chosen to take point. The way you control Luigi with the two analog sticks and almost never use the face buttons feels suspiciously like they wanted to train kids how to use the new controller before they got into more complicated games. It's about the only thing the game expects of you, and while there are nice touches and some cute theming, it's not novel enough to hold up the entire experience anymore. Not a bad game, but things have moved on since then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="sc5p2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Space Channel 5: Part 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The fact that this never made it to America until the special edition for PS2 is a crime. I love Space Channel 5, and this game improves on it in every way. The low resolution prerendered backgrounds are gone, the side characters and bosses got fleshed out, and there are fun bonuses like endless mode and unlockable costumes. It's my favorite rhythm game of all time, which isn't REALLY saying much because I haven't played many, so I guess I'll say it's my favorite game released for Dreamcast. It's really, really cute, and equally fun. It's also on Steam for some reason, so really, you should give this game a try.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="tew2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Evil Within 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I had more fun in my initial playthrough of this game than the first, and it has all the same charm, but I'm reluctant to say it's better. Instead of blending horror and action into a thrillingly tight experience like the first game, it goes for a more relaxed style where you can take your time exploring in open world segments. It's a change that doesn't leverage the strengths The Evil Within has as a setting. The first game wanted to be a fast-paced trip through a variety of horror setpieces, so a dreamlike world was chosen to bind the pieces together. Turning that dream world into a relatively stable environment with lower variety is wasted potential, and the slowness associated with that change also removes the unique intensity of the first game. It does have some unique strengths of its own though, being smoother the whole way through and much more impressive on a technical level. The writing is also surprisingly strong for a game even tangentially associated with Shinji Mikami, and Sebastian Castellanos is one of my favorite game protagonists in recent memory. I had a ton of fun with The Evil Within 2, and I'm not exaggerating when I say it's one of my favorites of the year, it just didn't go in the most satisfying direction overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="ghosttrick"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ghost Trick: Phantom Detective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In Japan, this game is simply titled "Ghost Trick" which is a way better title if only for how it isn't misleading. I went into this game hoping for some good paranormal investigation, but the gameplay's actually just possessing and wiggling objects in predetermined ways to prevent people's deaths. It's a charming premise for a game and a story, but when it comes to actually playing it, it's nothing more than adequate. Just as the gameplay wasn't as nuanced as I hoped, the story doesn't trust you to figure things out and rehashes information constantly to make sure you're on track. I would have appreciated this game more if it was 25-50% shorter and gave players a chance for deduction instead of outright telling you things, but I also have to admit that it was still an overall good experience. Check it out if you're into visual novels, but not if you want something puzzley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="fotns"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fist of the North Star: Lost Paradise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Everyone's seeing this set of reviews from my twitter, where I pretty much already said all I need to say about this game, so I'll just say that again. It's meant to be a fanservice mashup of Fist of the North Star and Yakuza, and sadly, that's ALL it is. I was hoping that Fist of the North Star would be the injection of originality Yakuza needs to break out of its formula, while Yakuza helped North Star's similar mix of gravitas and humor really shine. However, it ended up being just a celebration of the memes of both series, which can't be enjoyed as much when it doesn't have the serious moments to play off. Combining that disappointment with the outdated Yakuza 0 engine, playing this after Yakuza Kiwami 2 was a letdown. Not having fun while blowing up people with a hokuto hyakuretsu ken is pretty much impossible, so I can't write it off, but it's crazy how an idea with this much promise didn't end up as some of the most fun I've had in a game in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="punchout"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mike Tyson's Punch Out&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This game is on the pantheon of legendary NES games, but I'm not sure it's as good as people remember. The first half is great, boxers have a lot of personality and you can learn as you go, but the later ones are all just tough dudes you need to memorize. It changes from a wacky back and forth fight into high speed Simon Says. I took the time to beat Mike Tyson, but the fight's pretty much the same every time so I wasn't satisfied by my effort at all. The Wii one is easily the better experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="re4"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resident Evil 4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just like Symphony of the Night, I've been hard on this game in the past for redefining a series I had previously enjoyed. Also just like Symphony of the Night, I've come around to appreciating just how much heart this game has. Not only did this game pretty much invent the concept of using a horror setting to push players to mastering action mechanics, it did so with style. It's almost tragic to look back on all the third person shooters this game lead to, which had you dryly sitting in cover, with enemies lacking a wide set of meaningful interactions. Even Resident Evil 5 moved more towards typical shooter gameplay compared to the risk and reward this game facilitates with its combat mechanics. This game along with Vanquish give me the sense that third person shooting still has a lot of room for improvement, so you should probably go play both of those. They were also both directed by Shinji Mikami, so you gotta admit, this guy knows how to make games lively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="mario3"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Super Mario Bros. 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This game is probably the most unassailable classic game on this list, but it's not the best. Unlike the aforementioned third person shooting, I think platforming is a genre that has been explored pretty thoroughly, and hundreds of games have evolved from this one to make some great stuff. It's good and fun, no problems, but Mario is the template for every platformer you've ever played, so it won't be very exciting. You should play it anyway though, because as I just said, it's the template for every platformer you've ever played. It's good to have perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="obradinn"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Return of the Obra Dinn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This game is an absolute treat. If you haven't heard of it, because not many people have, it's a game by the creator of Papers Please (which I also liked, see above) where you investigate the mystery of the Obra Dinn, an East India Company ship where all hands were lost at sea. You have a list of the crew, a few photos, and have to piece together who is who and how they died by traveling back to the moment of their death using a magical watch. Since people don't usually shout their names, what killed them, and who all observers are from left to right, you have to use everything from uniforms to marks on the wall to make your deductions. The amount of clues and the cleverness of their placement is jaw dropping, and even minor crew members usually a solid clue to go off. The problem is that word "usually" is in there instead of "always". While I didn't have to check a guide, I tallied up my solutions and only 3/4ths were done with direct deduction, and the rest were "I know your position or your race, and I'm sure of a few other people, so I'll just swap the information around until the game clicks into place". The game won't let you guess everyone, as you need to solve three at a time for the entries to lock into your solution notebook, but it's also loose enough to suggest the game is fully aware that some clues are way too hidden away and a couple characters are too ambiguous to be decisive until the end. The game's pacing certainly doesn't help, as you're forced to experience every memory before you're able to freely investigate the crew. The other black mark on the game is its interface, presented as a book you're writing notes in. It's such a clunky way to navigate information that it feels like you're solving a rubik's cube with your elbows, and it took me a couple hours before I really understood how to navigate it. Even with the issues though, I love this game so much. It trusts players to be smart to a very gratifying degree, and I felt genuinely accomplished when I sorted out the mystery of the ship and each individual crewman. Absolutely play this game if you're even a little interested. It took me 7 hours to finish and it was so gripping I did it in one day. Really. Play it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="notvania"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bloodstained: Curse of the Moon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Even within a series of amazing games, Castlevania 3 stands out. It refines the thoughtful action of the first game while adding character swapping and branching paths to provide the most satisfying Castlevania experience yet. It's guaranteed to be one of your top NES games if you like a challenge, just be sure to play the Japanese version with the enhanced music.&lt;br /&gt;
Wait, I was supposed to write about Curse of the Moon, and ended up giving a shallow overview of Castlevania 3. Conveniently, if you would like to play a shallow overview of Castlevania 3, Curse of the Moon is right for you. When it copies screens from the original Castlevania games along with all their signature mechanics, I feel justified labeling it a clone. It's a $7 clone of a game I like at least, so I have to admit I left satisfied, but I don't have much respect for it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="recommendations"></category></entry><entry><title>It's not what it looks like! Some thoughts on Nioh and its context in gaming.</title><link href="http://birb.uk/nioh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-05T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-11-05T15:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Uni</name></author><id>tag:birb.uk,2017-11-05:/nioh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nioh was both hyped and maligned for being Team Ninja's attempt at Dark Souls, but there's more to it than meets the eye.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A frequently discussed topic in gaming is if you can fault a sequel for being radically different from its predecessors. Symphony of the Night, Fire Emblem Awakening, and Fallout 3 are still described with "It's a good game, but not a good game in the series" regardless of their positive reception as individual titles, highlighting the lasting influence of context. With quality being so subjective, managing the perspective by which quality is judged is crucial to framing the experience as whole, guiding players into understanding the intended experience before they even start the game. This is what makes creating iterative sequels easy compared to revolutionary ones, running with a series' popular momentum instead of against it. Accurately communicating the goals of a game when it's only a spiritual successor has the problems of both, building upon the expectations of a prior franchise while morphing the goals significantly enough to create something new. Unfortunately for Nioh, its spiritual predecessor is a franchise linked with extreme fan expectations: Dark Souls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing action games to the Souls series has lost almost all meaning in the last few years, but when playing Nioh it's easy to see why the comparison is deserved. The repetitive structure of open areas punctuated by boss fights is a recognizable carryover, along with similar weapon movesets and a familiar bloodstain system. With those core features shared so directly, the knee jerk reaction is that Nioh is an attempt to capitalize on the popularity of a bigger series, while just dressing it up with Japanese aesthetic and a randomized loot system. However, looking at the game in this perspective maligns the game by implying the goals of Nioh are similarly duplicated. This is not the case, and the difference between them can best by summarized by their perspectives on difficulty and how it impacts the player's interaction with the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Difficulty has become a marketing buzzword partly thanks to Dark Souls' popularity, but fans will tell you that its difficulty was never the point, instead being a way to engross players in a compelling atmosphere. The world was the real focus, and fortifying the moody inhospitality of the visuals with punishing gameplay was an elegant design choice to make the world feel fully realized. This is the same quality that lead to Bloodborne's overwhelmingly positive reception, and is the prime example of how spiritual successors can achieve these design goals, even when so much has been changed from its predecessors. Nioh on the other hand doesn't even try to establish its world in this way, which can easily be mistaken for a failing when its goal to do so is only assumed. The levels are smaller, they aren't interconnected, and the difficulty of common enemies is a function of high stats instead of unique behavior, which seems like a general downgrade until consideration of what the game is really trying to accomplish. In Nioh, difficulty actually is the point of the game, and learning how to mitigate that difficulty in the way that suits you best is the experience the game is designed around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weapons and their customizable movesets are the most obvious example of this expanded freedom of choice. Each weapon has three attack styles with unlockable skills and buffs, some of which work passively and allow for synergy between multiple types of weapons. Ninjutsu utility skills and magic talismans are available without stat investment, and the skill points you use to upgrade them are separate from the ones used to unlock abilities for your primary weapon. While there are foundational skills almost everyone will take for each weapon type, such as the ones allowing you to do a stamina-regenerating ki pulse by dodging, the choice between gaining active skills for your primary weapons or passives in other trees leads to significant build diversity. Stats gained through leveling also grant weapon, ninjutsu, or magic skill points, adding another layer of strategy to character building and demonstrating just how important they are to Nioh's central goal of player choice. While a point in your weapon's primary damage stat may be the most useful overall, leveling up magic to unlock talismans is an equally valid choice when up against a particularly difficult boss. The most admirable part of all this is how almost any mix of approaches is viable, including ones that would normally seem like a joke. Most high-level players use a mix of magic and melee, but even ninjutsu, which is usually relegated to a secondary roll, can be honed enough to burst late-game bosses with ease. Armor skills help make this diversity possible, with bonuses boosting a variety of effects which players can specially seek to compliment their character construction. To help mitigate grinding associated with finding a player's ideal gear, the crafting system allows for boosting an item's gear or rerolling its skills, allowing even for rigid sets to be customized. On top of that are unlockable guardian spirits and milestone bonuses, making for a truly impressive amount of player choice, an idea which extends into the levels' flexibility for different strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a game centered around its world building and atmosphere, sprinting past all the normal enemies directly to the boss is an unfortunately common strategy. When a boss fight requires healing resources and multiple attempts, it's natural that after the first few runs, players will favor getting back into the action quickly and circumvent the intended methodical experience. Nioh instead embraces a flexible approach, with small but broad maps which allow players to run to the boss quickly even from the starting shrine, or instead take the time to exploring to thoroughly prepare. Naturally, there are downsides to the fast approach: failures are punished with a longer run back, you'll miss the experience points held by enemies, and you won't have as many healing items in the subsequent levels. The healing system in Nioh is one I initially misunderstood, where you need to find hidden spirits throughout each level to increase the amount of healing items granted at shrine checkpoints. This increase is shared among a cluster of levels, with each new region requiring collection of a new set of spirits. At the start of the game I found this to be pointless busywork, but after trying the game without actively searching for them, I discovered that they aren't as critical as they seem. Bosses may be fast and brutal, but their moves are well telegraphed and the hitboxes are fair, with most attacks being easily avoidable even without the use of the invincibility frames provided by dodging. Bosses can also run out of stamina, be parried, or weakened by magic just like you can, providing players of all play styles with tools to intelligently exploit weaknesses and circumvent the need for healing items. If those options fail, spending the time to get a full set of elixirs at least represents a grind-free way of increasing your chances. In general, the game accounts for how players choose to engage in or ignore certain mechanics, allowing progression and backup strategies regardless of how they've chosen to play. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of that sounds very complimentary, but Nioh doesn't always succeed in these ideals it lays out. Before going into it however, I feel the need to frame my perspective, given how much the game revolves around player choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I solely used a katana when attempting missions for the first time, but replayed a mission using each weapon type at least once&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I used medium armor, first an early game set with close combat damage then a late game set based around skill damage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I used no ninjutsu or magic past in my first playthrough, but respecialized into ninjutsu and magic afterwards to test them out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I never summoned help or used a guide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I frequently skipped finding Kodama to gain healing items, never specifically seeking them out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I only did side missions which interested me, mostly being ones which didn't retread a map used in a main mission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach follows what most players call a knight archetype, focusing on the fundamental melee mechanics while balancing speed and defense. It's what players often choose when looking for the most consistent and balanced experience, but Nioh fails in delivering such an experience in the first place. Almost every boss has a one-shot-kill move, and many get powered up in later phases of the fight. You may go against a boss once, get clipped by its laser, then restart only to get clipped by it again as the boss sweeps it around in the second phase of the fight. Not only is this poor boss design in the first place, it also homogenizes armor choices. Increased protection may seem worthwhile in the exploration stage of a level even if the boss is going to one-shot you, but the low enemy variety means you've solved each enemy's pattern relatively early in the game anyway. The other consideration for your armor is how stamina usage increases with weight class, which would be worth attention if not for set bonuses. These bonuses are incredibly strong and override any other priorities, with a good example being how I entered the final mission more than 50 levels beneath the recommended number but killed the final boss in four attacks. Armor becomes less about player choice and more about picking an optimal solution as you progress towards the end of the game, when players should ideally be appreciating the diversity which comes from higher level equipment. The crafting system becomes tedious as a result, not being as much about blending effects to create unique solutions as it is repeatedly crafting the same set items as you level to keep your gear up to date. It can actually feel more efficient to not update your gear at all when set crafting requires items dropped from bosses, and defense numbers don't mean much when bosses one-shot you anyway. This might be bearable if the open stages at least let build creativity flourish somehow, but the aforementioned lack of enemy variety doesn't entice players to engage with them except as a function of fighting and preparing for bosses. This is where players will be split on their reception of Nioh even after accepting its differences from Souls, hinging on whether they can accept repetition and samey level design in favor of solid mechanics and unique boss fights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nioh's problem isn't that it wandered from a proven formula, but that it didn't polish its own vision of focusing on player choice. The bottlenecks imposed by the limits of the gear system and imbalanced bosses, combined with repetitive usage of enemies and maps, makes the game commonly feel sufficient rather than excellent. It does occasionally hit those peaks of excellence, with some bosses being so beautiful or with such fun AI that the repetition can be enjoyable. Notably, the humanoid bosses are some of the most fun I've ever fought, falling back or pressing their advantage based on your relative amounts of stamina in a way that feels realistic and intense. Even against the bosses designed to counter melee-focused players, I was able to beat them much more consistently than I could in the Souls series, highlighting how the combat has been polished enough to step out from the shadow of its predecessor. There really is a lot to love in Nioh despite its shortcomings, and it's well worth experiencing for its innovation and lovingly crafted aesthetics. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Nioh"></category></entry><entry><title>A Step into the Twilight Zone</title><link href="http://birb.uk/twilight-zone.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-03T18:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-10-03T18:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Uni</name></author><id>tag:birb.uk,2017-10-03:/twilight-zone.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Twilight Zone is my favorite TV Show of all time, and I wanted to share it with people for a Spooptober special.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm not much into horror, which makes it a little strange that The Twilight Zone is my favorite show. It's considered to be one of the pillars of the genre, with an iconic style, memorable stories, and an intro that has embedded itself into the pop-cultural psyche. However, the age of the show and existence of modern alternatives have made the source material begin a slide into obscurity. So, I wanted to share my passion for this show and hopefully create a few more fans with a little guide for some of the series' best episodes. These ten will cover the breadth of the show's styles, along with a small explanation of what made each one so special. A few notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There won't be any major spoilers, only a basic premise or what makes the episode unique. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I won't be mentioning if an episode has a twist, so no spoilerinos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can watch the show on Netflix or Amazon Prime Video.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I included no episodes from season 4, which are pay-per-view for their full-length run time. These ones should all be free with your subscription to either service, and run at a brisk 25 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The place is here. The time is now, and the journey into the shadows that we are about to watch, could be our journey" - Rod Serling, Producer, Narrator, and Screenwriter of The Twilight Zone&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Where is Everybody?" src="http://birb.uk/images/whereIsEverybody.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Where is Everybody? (season 1, episode 1)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As a Star Trek fan, terrible first episodes are something I've come to expect, but this one does a great job at establishing the atmosphere of the series. It's quiet and tense, with shots that remind you of modern movies like "I Am Legend", even with comparatively primitive filmmaking tools. You could use this episode as an example for how far you can take a story without computers or a high budget, using creative methods to tell a gripping story of total isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="What You Need" src="http://birb.uk/images/whatYouNeed.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What You Need (season 1, episode 12)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While The Twilight Zone is primarily known for its horror, this episode shows the other side of the series with a cautionary tale. This is a natural fit for a show where the variables of reality are unreliable, putting people into unrealistic scenarios which test their character in a way that still feels realistic. When watching this episode in particular, it's natural to wonder how you would react if you were put in the shoes of the main character, and it's this thought-provoking nature that makes the show more than the sum of its parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Hitchhiker" src="http://birb.uk/images/theHitchhiker.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Hitchhiker (season 1, episode 16)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is an episode with huge influence on the horror genre, and for good reason. Horror is most effective when it taps into people's most basic fears, and this episode conveys the panic of being chased so well that movies and shows are still emulating it. As a result, you may figure out where the story is going before the episode wants you to, but it's a personal favorite and one of the best in the show's horror style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Monsters Are Due On Maple Street" src="http://birb.uk/images/theMonstersAreDueOnMapleStreet.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Monsters Are Due On Maple Street (season 1, episode 22)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I said that "Where Is Everybody?" is a good taste of what The Twilight Zone is all about, and if that's true, this episode is the main course. It's considered one of the best in the series for good reason, mixing the horrific, moralistic, cautionary, and even political elements together to deliver a story that will still resonate with modern viewers. If I had only one episode to convince someone that this series is still relevant, it would be this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A Stop At Willoughby" src="http://birb.uk/images/aStopAtWilloughby.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;A Stop At Willoughby (season 1, episode 30)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This episode may be more relatable to an audience today more than when it was originally released. It addresses anxiety, mental fatigue, and an inability to escape stress, the same malaise that seems to affect more people today than ever before. It's a great example of how The Twilight Zone uses metaphor and symbology (albeit in a heavy-handed way) to send a message and comment on everyday problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Eye of the Beholder" src="http://birb.uk/images/eyeOfTheBeholder.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Eye of the Beholder (season 2, episode 6)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The cinematography of this episode has made it one of the most iconic in television history. Television can often rely on a practical, easy-to-produce shooting style, so the way this episode breaks the mold with a unique artistic vision makes it wonderfully unsettling. Even if you already know the plot of this episode, it's worth watching for how meticulously it builds suspense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Invaders" src="http://birb.uk/images/theInvaders.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Invaders (season 2, episode 15)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
"Eye of the Beholder" is to visuals as "The Invaders" is to sound. The most dialogue you get at one time is Rod Serling's intro, and after that you're left to watch as the silent conflict unfolds. It touches on the basic fears of solitude and the unknown, in the same way that "The Hitchhiker" conveyed the primal terror of being chased. The way the episode worldlessly accomplishes this is incredible, and it's a must-watch if you appreciate minimalist story presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Shelter" src="http://birb.uk/images/theShelter.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Shelter (season 3, episode 3)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you're a fan of the more realistic and morally-focused side of the show, this episode is for you. With how plainly the story is told, it feels like a direct message from Serling about how insane society can be. It's a straightfoward story with an obvious message, but that dryness makes it one of the most relatable episodes in the entire series. You can easily see the events of this episode happening in real life, and that's what makes it uniquely terrifying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Midnight Sun" src="http://birb.uk/images/theMidnightSun.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Midnight Sun (season 3, episode 10)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is my favorite episode of the series, even if it's not popularly considered one of the best. The horror in this episode is unlike anything else in the show, with a threat that isn't hidden in the shadows or behind the supernatural. Other episodes may give you the creeps, but this one is set up to give an oppressing sense of dread. If you have anxiety problems and need to explain to someone what it's like, make them watch this episode. It's about as close to the real thing as you can get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Five Characters In Search Of An Exit" src="http://birb.uk/images/fiveCharactersInSearchOfAnExit.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Five Characters In Search Of An Exit (season 3, episode 14)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The only way I can describe this episode is by saying it's a wild card. The premise is simple: five people of various occupations are trapped inside a gigantic circular pillar, and need to get out. While that's all there is to it, the simple mystery to it and the odd cast of characters make it all feel like a strange dream. It's a great example of how the effectively the show can establish a mood even without the use of explicit horror elements, and is considered one of the show's best episodes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those episodes are some of my favorites, but there are a few notable exclusions that I would feel remiss if I didn't mention. If you've watched the episodes I've listed and want more, here's a few where you can go in completely blind and enjoy the mystery:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time Enough At Last (season 1, episode 8)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mirror Image (season 1, episode 21)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Obsolete Man (season 2, episode 29)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To Serve Man (season 3, episode 24)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nightmare at 20,000 Feet (season 5, episode 3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know on Twitter which ones you watched and which ones you enjoyed! Have a spoopy Spooptober!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="recommendations"></category></entry><entry><title>Uni's (first?) Ten Recommendations</title><link href="http://birb.uk/uni-recommendations.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-22T18:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-22T18:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Uni</name></author><id>tag:birb.uk,2017-06-22:/uni-recommendations.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Looking for something to play, or buy on the Steam Sale? Here's ten games I love, in ten different genres, so hopefully there will be something here you're interested in.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If I'm going to be posting game design discussion on this site, I thought it would be a good idea to put out some recommendations and give people a sense of how my preferences translate into something tangible. Even if you already know what my preferences are, I'll try to recommend one game in each major genre so everyone has something new to try. Just in time for the Steam Summer Sale!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://birb.uk/images/Shatterhand.png" width="66%"&gt;&lt;/img&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Platformer: Shatterhand, 1991, NES&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Shatterhand is my go-to example of design elegance. The focus of the game is beat-em-up combat, so punching was made to be the mechanism of all other player agency. Choosing which robot you want to accompany you is handled by punching selection tiles, and they attack when you punch. You get money by punching boxes, and can get a bonus amount by punching money sacks. The efficient use of a basic control scheme makes the game simple and satisfying, letting new players easily jump in while rewarding more experienced players who take the time to learn the strengths of each robot. While the game escalates into some absurd difficulty in the final stage, it's worth playing to see the height of what the NES could do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Strider" src="http://birb.uk/images/strider.jpg" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Action: Strider, 2014, PC/PS3/PS4/X360/X1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Strider's basic gameplay fits the mold of what most people call a Metroidvania, but it doesn't have the genre's endemic issues. It's fast paced, the movement feels fun from the start, there isn't much backtracking, and weapon/character stats have been stripped out in favor of direct upgrades. The simplicity makes for a very focused experience, where movement and combat flow smoothly with exploration. This all works because of the game's depth-first exploration style, in comparison to how most Metroidvanias are structured as breadth-first. Each new area starts linearly with action-platforming challenges, rewarding you at the end with an upgrade which opens the area to full exploration. It's a unique take on the genre, and makes for a fast and fun 2D exploration game which never bogs you down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="999" src="http://birb.uk/images/nineninenine.jpg" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Visual Novel: Nine Hours, Nine Persons, Nine Doors, 2010, DS/PC/PS4/VITA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This game has everything you could want in a visual novel, with a unique story, meaningful choices, and a fully-realized cast of characters. The (spoiler-free) premise is that the protagonist and eight other captives wake up on a mysterious boat, with only nine hours to make it through a gauntlet of lethal challenges and escape. The choices you make put you on unique story paths, which make subsequent playthroughs of the game just as interesting as your first. To make things even better, the recent re-release (Zero Escape: The Nonary Games) adds quality of life features which remove some annoyances from the original DS version. I wasn't sure if I should include this game on the recommendations list, because I think most core gamers have heard of it by now, but it deserves emphasis for how it leverages the strength of books and games in a way that has yet to be superceded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Riven" src="http://birb.uk/images/riven.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Adventure: Riven, 1997, PC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I've talked about this game in another article about the legacy of Myst, but I think it deserves discussion outside its monumental predecessor. At the most basic level, it's a first-person adventure where you explore the islands of Riven, taking in environmental clues and solving the occasional puzzle. While most adventure games focus on the puzzle solving, Riven challenges players to absorb the environment, navigating an adventure rather than solving contextualized puzzle boxes. This goal of making the islands of Riven more than a backdrop for puzzles was a success, but the few puzzles which test your observational skills are notably weak. Every detail requires your attention, but there's no feedback on your progress until you hit a wall and realize what you specifically need to know. These moments along with some clunky environmental interactions make the game far from a masterpiece, but I still highly recommend it for how much it managed to achieve. In most modern games three dimensional worlds are a standard, and you usually don't pay any thought to them unless they're particularly bad. Riven aspired to show the potential in those worlds, even if it had to do so with extremely limited technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Infinifactory" src="http://birb.uk/images/infinifactory.jpg" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Puzzle: Infinifactory, 2015, PC/PS4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
At first glance, this is yet another puzzle game about placing and pushing around blocks, but in reality it's a brilliantly executed abstraction of programming. Your basic task is to assemble blocks into a given shape and deliver it to the endpoint, by way of your specialized tool blocks. It starts out very simplistic, using conveyor belts and welders to make organized rectangles, but as the levels go on and the requirements get more complex you begin to appreciate the programming process. Complex problems become a sequence of specialized actions, you learn to compartmentalize each step, and the many ways you can play with these steps to solve problems allows for infinite creativity. The relaxing mood and creative freedom makes this game a great experience that I would recommend to just about anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alien: Isolation" src="http://birb.uk/images/alien.jpg" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Horror: Alien Isolation, 2014, PC/PS4/X1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
"Cinematic" has become a dirty word in gaming recently, being used as pejorative term for games that are over-reliant on cutscenes or have low player agency in general. It's appropriate that a game based on a movie franchise would be the one to bring some redemption to the term, and craft an experience that isn't reliant on set-pieces. There was an incredible amount of work put into making every moment feel cinematic, from how the station's ambient metallic groans change as it slowly falls apart, to how light sources are placed to direct your view and cast menacing shadows. Even people who aren't fans of horror can appreciate the ways that Alien Isolation smartly uses its visuals and sound to establish moods and create scenes. While the cat-and-mouse game against the Xenomorph is simplistic compared to the meticulously designed environment, there's such an incredible level of polish that I consider it a must-play for people interested in cinematic gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="F-Zero" src="http://birb.uk/images/fzero.jpg" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Racing: F-Zero GX, 2003, GCN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The fantasy racing genre has been gaining traction with games like Redout and Fast RMX, but the standard these games are held to is consistently F-Zero GX. They all have the same basic gameplay of balancing speed, maneuverability, and hull integrity, but it's the way F-Zero engages you outside the races that's uniquely great. Completing a story mission or Grand Prix will unlock racers and custom parts for purchase, and any sort of race will award you with the tickets used to purchase them. Higher difficulties award more tickets and unlock the best racers, so your skill is always being pushed to the limit and your successes are consistently rewarded. Even if you don't care about unlocking all the characters, the mechanics are so fun to use and the maps so distinct that the intrinsic rewards of learning the game are enough to drive you forward. It's a case of "easy to start, hard to master", but the constant rewards push you into mastery in a natural way that's incredibly fun from start to finish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Wild Guns" src="http://birb.uk/images/wildguns.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Shooter: Wild Guns, 1994, SNES/PS4/PC (to be released)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you were to take Metal Slug, put the camera behind the characters, only allow them to move laterally, and set it in a wild west robot invasion, you would get Wild Guns. Hopefully that was enough to sell you on it, but there are a few other differences that make it stand out from its token-taking cousin. There are much fewer bullets coming at you at once, and to make their trajectory from the background to foreground understandable, there's an indicator to show you where each will hit. You can either dodge or shoot it out of the air for bonus weapons and ammo, so there's a layer of risk and reward that you're constantly managing. These additions go a long way to make the game fair, and it maintains the fast-paced fun from Metal Slug while getting rid of the questionably fair bullet curtains. Wild Guns hits a perfect balance between difficulty and accessibility, a rarity for arcade shooters of its era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mark of the Ninja" src="http://birb.uk/images/ninja.jpg" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Stealth: Mark of the Ninja, 2012, PC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can learn a lot about the goals of a stealth game by the ways it informs players of their situation. Metal Gear Solid 1 has a radar which displays the alert state and view cone of each guard, encouraging players to be confident, but alert states disable the radar to create frantic action. Metal Gear Solid 3 gave players much more primitive options for tracking enemies to slow down the pace and emphasize careful observation. Mark of the Ninja is more informative than either: enemy view cones are visible, all noises are displayed with a visual radius, and your tools show what they will do as you aim them. By removing most uncertainties, players don't need to default to playing it safe, and can instead focus on using their tools creatively. The challenge of the game isn't about being patient, it's about recognizing and capitalizing on opportunities. Unlocks tied to in-game challenges promote players to think past simple strategies, and the suits awarded for them provide unique bonuses and tool capacities. Having so many options makes replaying the game feel like a necessity, and it's one of the very few games that I beat on ng and ng+ back to back. Considering how quickly I drop a game when it stops being fun, that should really tell you something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Fallout" src="http://birb.uk/images/fallout.gif" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;RPG: Fallout, 1997, PC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I'm not sure any game has been as thoroughly overshadowed by its descendants as Fallout has. Older fans tend to value Fallout 2's capacity for choice, and newer fans value New Vegas' accessibility and a story full of options. Fallout has a much smaller scope than either of these games, but it makes for a more focused experience in general. Unlike Fallout 2 or New Vegas, your main quest is your main focus, with a time constraint attached to it to ensure you don't get distracted. The world is small to accommodate the deadline, and there aren't many sidequests that exist for their own sake. This sounds like a very limiting design for an RPG, but the urgency makes you pay attention to the world, and you get personally involved in your character's quest. The atmosphere similarly benefits from keeping an axe over your head, establishing the world as compellingly dangerous. By the time you've progressed past the time limited quest, you've become so invested in the world that you naturally want to see your ultimate goal through to the end. Fallout may be considered awkward compared to its openly designed sequels, but it strikes an elegant balance between role-playing and linear narrative that the other games were unable to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="recommendations"></category></entry><entry><title>Hitman: The History, The Flaws, The Future</title><link href="http://birb.uk/uni-hitman.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-11T23:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-05-11T23:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Uni</name></author><id>tag:birb.uk,2017-05-11:/uni-hitman.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Square Enix is withdrawing from IO Interactive, the developer of Hitman, and I wanted to talk about why this game's had such a rocky history and what the end of its life cycle might mean.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Square Enix recently announced its withdrawal from IO Interactive, the development studio behind the latest entry in the Hitman franchise. While there hasn't been any definitive announcement about how this will impact the ongoing support for Hitman, it's almost certain that this means a halt to the development of the second season of episodes. Hitman has been a game full of controversies from the start, and with this one possibly being the last, it's a good time to look back at history of the game, its issues, and the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest issues of Hitman's release came the earliest, with its episodic development and online DRM. Hitman launched with a tutorial map, a slightly bigger introductory level, and the first main stage of the game in a Paris fashion show. The intro pack which included only these levels was priced at $15, with a season pass available for a full $60. This pricing model was an attempt at letting players try the game before they fully commit, but it was met with harsh criticism from players looking for a more complete experience at launch. The DRM which forced players to stay online for unlocks was similarly criticised, especially with server connectivity issues at launch. While the gameplay was uniformly praised, the limited amount of launch content and DRM issues were enough to keep Steam community reviews of the game around a cold 50%. Only in April 2017, after over a year of episodes and updates did the reviews tilt to the "Mostly Positive" rating with 75% positive reviews. Even during that slow climb, not all episodes equally contributed, with the second episode representing the high point of community reception. Marrakesh was considered a combination of two weak maps, Bangkok claustrophobic, Colorado the weakest in general, and only Hokkaido a successor to the standards established by the first two episodes. While each map was still generally positive, the inability of IO Interactive to consistently put out levels as great as Sapienza put them in a bind with their pricing structure. In addition to buying the starter pack or full experience, players could also buy individual levels for $15. While buying every level this way would lead to a higher total cost, it also meant that it was commonplace for customers to skip the majority of Hitman's content. I even contributed to this, recommending to multiple people that they buy the intro pack, Sapienza, and Hokkaido on sale while skipping the rest to get the best value. This represented massive uncertainty for IO Interactive, having to put as much development bandwidth as possible into new episodes without any guarantee of a proportional amount of customers. The episodic structure may have allowed for community feedback and testing which resulted in an overall better quality game, but the double edge of allowing minimal consumer investment apparently made it unsustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among these big episodic releases were gameplay updates and balance changes, which were similarly a mixed bag. While I mentioned before that people praised the core gameplay as some of the best in the entire series, questionable balance decisions dulled community enthusiasm. The change most often discussed were the NPC view cones, which were moved from the chest to the head in the Summer bonus update. This is a change most people may not have consciously noticed, and it makes the game more realistic, but there was a significant knock-on effect that hurt the game overall. With the change coming months after levels had been put out, the behavior players were used to became unpredictable, and the natural way guards idly look around a room made them inconsistent and frustrating. Worst of all, this change broke some of the tightly designed Escalation missions, making them impossible to do without using rule-bending strategies like throwing coins as breadcrumbs until you had enough space to hopefully get past. Escalation missions in general ended up being a missed opportunity, with most requiring five playthroughs of goals that were often either tedious or trivial. When playing them, it's common to have to exactly replay what you did on an earlier stage because the game only checks for the current criteria, and the more difficult limitations like explosive laser barriers don't meaningfully change the way you approach a mission. Ideally, each step of an escalation would completely upend the prior approach by giving criteria that blocks the most logical strategies for the prior step and promotes creativity in the new one. Having to kill your target without getting spotted by cameras might be an additional challenge, but it's not a new way to fundamentally approach your goal. When you find a creative approach, there's also a chance that your strategy will get patched out, the most notable example being wall-banging, shooting targets through walls with a powerful sniper rifle. This change is a good representation of Hitman's balance update problems in general, frustrating expert players with repetition and limited options while not expanding on other mechanics and content to make up for it. It's another case where expert players became less likely to enthusiastically recommend buying the full game, during a critical period when an infusion of new customers was sorely needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the main missions and escalations, user contracts, challenges, and elusive targets are available, which are again good systems which never reached their full potential. Contracts mode allows users to create any mission that they can successfully execute, and anyone else can play those missions, so the two most important criteria for a contracts mode have already been established. The problem is how there's no control of this system in almost any fashion, with no mechanism for contracts to be rated or shared in way in the client. The amount of contracts you can put out is limited to ten, but the only way to get rid of them is to override the oldest one with the newest one. There are definitely quality community contracts, but with no way to find them, it's usually not worth the time investment. Challenges on main missions were IO Interactive's chance to essentially put out contracts of their own, asking players to break out of the default opportunities and strategies and get rewarded for their creativity with unlocks. However, they are the opposite of this, being a laundry list of opportunities to complete before you get all the unlocks you want. Having a system that rewards players for replaying and learning levels was a good inclusion, but this basic approach wasn't enough to be called new content. A professional difficulty mode was also recently patched in to function as a global set of challenges, with more attentive guards, disguise restrictions, and save limitations, but this was another case of not adding enough actual new content or promoting unique strategies. It actually had the opposite effect, promoting the safer and more restricted play that experts had already mastered and moved past. This also happened with the Elusive Targets, which were one-try-only missions set on existing maps with a new NPC target. Having performance pressure on a target with new AI was definitely an interesting idea, but they often came with other additions that made them less exciting. Previously free areas became secured, and targets often had such limited behavior that you could never fully leverage your map knowledge. This combined with how you were only allowed one try and the unlocks gated behind a Silent Assassin rating meant that most players either didn't want to even try, got frustrated with any failure, played it boringly safe, or just looked up a guide on Youtube. These smaller pieces of content in general ended up being unsatisfying or not worth the time, in another case where potential customers couldn't be assured by the community that the $60 game they were considering had enough content to be worth it. The constant stream of updates was commendable, but the additions never resonated with a particular audience, and were unlikely to have a positive return on investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all that said, I still believe that Hitman set up the framework for an amazing game. There are plenty of mechanical quirks, but I personally put over 100 hours into the game, most of which included just running around and enjoying the sandbox environments. Poisoning everyone as a rogue chef, sniping everyone in a stylish suit, or sneaking in windows and smothering people as Santa Claus will always be fun, and I see myself playing it again in the future. Even with flaws in the supporting content, the most basic building blocks like the disguises and gameplay flexibility have been incredibly strong and make the game still worth the price of admission. The real problem was Hitman's inability to keep expert players consistently engrossed while drawing in new players outside of the big episodic releases. Without having core fans consistently marketing the game, and in some cases advising against a full investment, the sustainability of the episodic release structure collapsed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common phrase I've used to talk about Hitman's issues is "missed potential", and I feel like that applies to the game's future as well. As was said before, most of the problems surround the central mechanics of the game, rather than within them, and season two could have capitalized on what season one had established to make something even better. Now that players have done the basic challenges in season one, they can handle more involved ones in season two; now that there's a catalog of simple escalations, more mind-bending ones can be put out instead. Even if IO Interactive didn't want to change view cones and sniper rifle penetration back to how they were, new levels could be built with those limitations along with new fun interactions to provide a compromise between fun and the balance they prefer. Even with the expert players being annoyed by some of the changes, they criticise because they want to cheer, and genuinely care about Hitman realizing its full potential. The perfect example of this is the Hitman series speedrunner &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/TheKotti"&gt;TheKotti&lt;/a&gt;, who has put out community tools like &lt;a href="https://thekotti.github.io/about.html"&gt;Hitman Roulette&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href="http://www.hitmandb.com/"&gt;contract sharing page&lt;/a&gt;, while also vocally criticising IO Interactive for their questionable balance decisions. The development experience and feedback from season one, along with dedicated fans who are ready to promote the game when it rises to its potential, meant that season two could have been the solution to all the problems that have plagued the game until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, it seems like the reality of the future is that Hitman will become the Firefly of its genre, dying as a flawed gem at the end of the first season. Fans of the series may have been willing to give Hitman a chance, but Square Enix can't rely on that investment for the numerous aforementioned reasons. Hopefully, IO Interactive will still be able to push minor updates, and ensure players don't lose their progress to a DRM server shutdown. A few final balance changes and well designed escalations/contracts could increase the game's quality of life immensely, and the existing gameplay is solid enough to hold the game together even without much revision. It would be great if IOI's allowed to hold on just a bit longer to polish the game, and avoid full deprecation even with Square Enix retracting new feature development. We can only hope they get the chance to sign off in a way that leaves dedicated fans with something to enjoy and revisit until we can play as 47 again.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="hitman"></category></entry><entry><title>Some thoughts on Myst, Riven, The Witness, and other stuff.</title><link href="http://birb.uk/uni-myst-witness.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-12T08:44:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-04-12T08:44:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Uni</name></author><id>tag:birb.uk,2017-04-12:/uni-myst-witness.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Scattered thoughts on Myst, Riven, and the Witness, or why I like bad games more than a good one; not really any spoilers, there's some vague references to what happens in game but nothing that will give away a solution or plot.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Myst is a game that was truly groundbreaking for the medium. While its setup of a mute player-insert protagonist walking around quiet environments and solving puzzles is something that's become popular in recent years, Myst intertwined the concepts of exploration, mystery, and narrative back in 1993 in a way that hadn't been seen before. Its sequel Riven carried on that legacy of innovation, building on the concept of exploration while moving away from the a deliberately puzzle-oriented structure in an attempt to leverage the unique strengths of first-person adventuring. Nineteen years after the release of Myst and Riven, with their impact on gaming impossible to calculate, The Witness was released in an attempt to recapture what made those games so intriguing in the first place while stripping away the flaws a more distant perspective could reveal. However, even with each game sharing the core principles of first-person explorative puzzle solving, each one uniquely mixes these elements to leverage the strengths of the genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The island of Myst" src="http://birb.uk/images/myst-island.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myst's focus is on the titular island of Myst, a very small area filled with indecipherable puzzles and a small library which serves as a focal point. After exploring this library, you learn that these puzzles aren't as indecipherable as they appeared at first glance, with most of the required information accessible somewhere in the building. There's still solving to do but it's noticably separated from the exploration itself, with exploration used to establish all your tools and necessary information but  with solving as a separate process. As an example, at one point you need to find the code to open a safe, but it contains a necessary problem solving tool rather than the key to a new area. Once you get that tool from the safe, no further exploration is required, and all the logical elements you need to solve it are at hand. Even when the setup isn't this clear cut, the premise of using exploration to establish the tools for direct puzzle solving is Myst's core structure. It's a straight forward way to join the two concepts, but it's not without downsides. Most puzzles don't have requirements as explicit as a safe combination, and a small detail from one level might be required in an entirely different one later on. It boils down to a lack of direction, where the player is left to figure out how to correctly connect the puzzles to the environment. While most puzzles in Myst don't cause too much trouble in this respect, some definitely land on the side of esoteric, and it only takes one brick wall to bring you to a dead stop. Even after you get past a barrier like this, it can shift the mood from exploration to careful cataloguing, a problem which may have been solved if the puzzles and environments didn't have such an obvious layer between each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Riven" src="http://birb.uk/images/riven-rocks.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Riven is the direct response to this idea that separation between puzzles and environment is contrary to the goals of an adventure game. You may be doing the same first person exploration in Riven, but this time there's less than five puzzles to contend with, and discovery takes the main focus. Instead of combinations for safes, you're looking for meaning in symbols; instead of going to different worlds with their own puzzle themes, you're freely traveling to islands in an archipelago with their own pertinent details. Riven is not trying to test learning, it's trying to test observation and understanding, which uniquely fits its gameplay presentation. Such a slow burning experience can be incredibly rewarding at the end, but the main flaw is how unrewarding it can be on a second to second basis. Myst's puzzles may have felt tacked on, but they had the advantage of telling players they were on the right track. Riven doesn't have any such mechanism, and if a player doesn't immediately recognize the significance of a single environmental detail, it could mean hours of backtracking and searching. This isn't entirely a bad thing, as players usually aren't given this amount of intellectual trust, and most games don't have enough trust in their own design to not just slap markers on everything, but the amount of things to keep track of combined with an inconsistent camera means that most people will have to look something up eventually. Myst and Riven are both famous games for people to say "I loved that game as a kid, but I could never beat it, back then you couldn't just pull up the internet..." and so on. While Riven still provides an amazing experience, it needs what Myst needed: a followup which can take advantage of new technology and learn from design mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Witness" src="http://birb.uk/images/witness-island.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Witness seems to be the modern descendent of Myst and Riven, more so than any other modern first person exploration games like Amnesia and Soma. While The Witness wasn't made by the same people or directly related to Myst, its lead designer has spoken about the influence these games had on the Witness, and comparisons come naturally with a nearly identical gameplay premise. The most notable difference is yet again a shift in the style of puzzles to solve. Myst set them next to the environment, Riven made them the environment itself, and the Witness sets them outside the environment almost entirely. Riven and The Witness are almost diametrically opposed, with Riven's environment being the mystery to solve, and the Witness' environment serving primarily as a backdrop to its hundreds of mechanical puzzles. There aren't any moments aside from the optional areas where you'll feel like the solutions are esoteric, or that you missed a detail in a dark shadow somewhere on the island, but this also means that the environment isn't the player or the game's real focus. The Witness does have some good moments of environmental interaction, but the very strong majority of solutions exist only on each puzzle panel. The exceptions are often superficial, walking around until an environmental features lines up with a panel and reveals the correct solution. To put it simply, the elimination of what the lead designer called "pixel hunts" from Myst flattened the experience, raising the lows the lowering the heights a player would experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By overlapping each of these game's individual successes and failures, you can begin to see the strengths and weaknesses of the genre as a whole. The core element is the environmental design, being the key to every player interaction when the gameplay is so strongly based on discovery. Being so rigorously first-person, even in cutscenes, emphasizes how the whole point of the experience is for players to take in their environment with no distraction. The secondary strength is the puzzling, which can come in a direct way, an environmental way, or a mixed approach. Of these three, The Witness feels the most direct, Riven the most environmental, and Myst being the mix. While all these approaches are equally valid from a game design standpoint, the goal for secondary mechanics is to compliment the core experience, in this case being exploring an environment. The tertiary focus of these games is direct storytelling, instead opting for most details to be picked up naturally through exploration. Myst and Riven each have simple plots, but the details you pick up along the way are what define the narrative more than the direct plot points. The Witness is even more sparse, really only pulling back the curtain only after you've beaten the game, and has hardly any audio or text to distract from the visual experience. With this hierarchy of goals established, the game with the most aligned goals and implementation would have to be Riven. This doesn't necessarily mean it's the best game of the three, but it's designed in a way that suggests an understanding of the genre, with the environment being the center of every gameplay and narrative element. Myst had tried to accomplish those goals, but with its puzzles and story laid on top of the environments rather than integrated within them, Riven had the advantage of learning and refining those goals. This leaves me with some disappointment in the direction chosen for The Witness that I hadn't felt when I had played it before. The Witness almost feels like a step backwards, with the puzzles and environment are almost entirely separate and no narrative link to encourage exploration or promote interest. This isn't to say that moving away from rigid genre definitions automatically makes a game terrible, and the opposite is more often true, but as mentioned before The Witness ended up moving away from the strengths along with the weaknesses. There are definitely elements from Myst and Riven to ditch, with some bad layouts, quirky puzzles, and obvious technical limitations, but it would have been nice to take the same aspirations a step forward rather than a step back. It's not just The Witness shying away from these ideas, so I don't want to be too mean to it specifically, it's just a shame that the great-grandchildren of Myst and grandchildren of Riven have forgotten why those games were so beloved even with so many issues. I hope more games like The Witness can boldly sell themselves in a media markets naturally set up to appeal to as many people as possible, while bringing the genre forward in a way that shows how captivating a fully realized world can be.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="witness"></category><category term="myst"></category><category term="riven"></category></entry></feed>